<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Roman doctrine of repentance and of indulgences vindicated from Dr. Stillingfleet's misrepresentations.</title>
            <author>R. H., 1609-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 223 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66971</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25193</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08792663</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08792663</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41841</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66971)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41841)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1272:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Roman doctrine of repentance and of indulgences vindicated from Dr. Stillingfleet's misrepresentations.</title>
                  <author>R. H., 1609-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>124 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to A. Woodhead--National union catalog pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699. --  Discourse concerning the idolatry practised in the Church of Rome.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Repentance.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41841:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41841:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ROMAN DOCTRINE OF REPENTANCE AND OF INDULGENCES: VINDICATED From Dr.
<hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Miſrepreſentations.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Concil. Trident. Seſſ: 6. c. 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Docendum eſt, Chriſtiani hominis Paenitentiam poſt lapſum multo aliam eſſe a Baptiſmali; eaque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineri non modo Ceſſationem a Peccatis, &amp; eorum deteſtationem, aut Cor contritum &amp; humiliatum; verum etiam eorundem Sacramentalem Confeſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſaltem in voto &amp; ſuo tempore faciendam; &amp; Sacerdotalem Abſolutionem; Itemque Satisfactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem per Jejunia, eleemoſynas, Orationes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, MDCLXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41841:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41841:2"/>
            <head>The Roman Doctrine of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance <hi>Vindicated.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>1</label> HItherto I have explicated, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor'd to vindicate, the <hi>Roman Devotions.</hi> The other matter of great conſequence, wherein that Church hath ſuffered much wrong from <hi>Doctor Stilling fleet</hi> (as alſo before him, from <hi>Biſhop Taylor</hi> in his <hi>Diſſwaſive,</hi>) is the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctrine concerning
<hi>Repentance,</hi> and a <hi>good life</hi> in theſe. 5. Particulars following, wherein this Author informs his Credulous Reader, (according to what the General current of his diſcourſe repreſents), 1ſt, That the <hi>Roman</hi> Church holds no neceſſity of <hi>Repentance,</hi> but only once in ones life; i. e. <hi>in articulo mortis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolat. c. 3 §. 1. p. 181. Ibid. pag. 180.</note> (as he expreſſeth it out of Dr. <hi>Taylors Diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive,</hi> an Author of the ſame fidelity). 2ly. That the Roman <hi>Repentance</hi> or <hi>Contrition</hi> doth not include, or oblige any to, <hi>forſaking</hi> of their
<hi>ſin,</hi> or <hi>Reformation of life.</hi> 3ly. That it holds the <hi>Sacraments</hi> to confer Grace <hi>ex opere opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> on whatever ſubject,<note place="margin">Ibid. §. 6. p. 203.</note> or receiver of them, though never ſo <hi>indiſpoſed,</hi> or unprepared. 4ly. Of the eaſineſs for any in the Church, by this feat of the Sacrament of Penance,<note place="margin">Ibid. §. 2. p. 184.</note> remitting ſin, and conferring Grace <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> to change the <hi>Eternal</hi> puniſhment of ſin, (which is certainly remitted always together with the ſin it ſelf) into a <hi>Temporal</hi> one; or to change
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41841:3"/>
               <hi>Hell-torments</hi> into thoſe of <hi>Purgatory;</hi> and then of the eaſineſs of getting out of theſe with a little Money or Friends. 5. Laſtly of the
<hi>Roman</hi> Doctrine of <hi>Indulgences</hi> charged by him<note n="‖" place="margin">G. 6. §. 4, 9, 10.</note> with many groſs Abſurdities, and as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing Roman Catholicks from doing the beſt parts of their Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>8</label> Lay theſe things together, and ſee what a Monſter this Author makes here of the Roman Catholick Religion, and of that Church, which before
<hi>Luthers</hi> time, when there was none, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, any better than it, was called in our Creed, <hi>the Holy Catholick Church,</hi> and which is ſo ſpread over the face of the Earth, and the Nations flowing into it. And who would think, that a Church, that taught ſuch doctrines, as he here preſents to his Proteſtant Reader, ſhould keep ſuch a doe about Abſtinences, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Penance, and Perſonal Satisfactions, and the Juſtification by, and Merit of, Good Works? about long Offices and many Hours of Prayer; about Poverty, Celibacy, Solitude, Silence, Hair-cloath, Diſciplines? which, if he ſaith, they are not really performed, yet, he muſt confeſs in this Church, at leaſt they are taught, and called for; Or, if he ſaith, they are only vaingloriouſly, &amp; hypocritically performed, ſo, to ſpeak truth, he muſt know hearts. Who would think, I ſay, a Church ſhould make ſuch a noiſe about theſe things, of many of which among Proteſtants is deep ſilence, (unleſs to revile them) when as, after this Author hath caſt up a true account of it, this Church holds, &amp; teaches
<hi>Repentance</hi> only neceſſary to any perſon once in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41841:3"/>his life; and that, not extending to any reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, or forſaking of his ſin; nothing leſs; but only to ſome ſorrow for his ſin, and that but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſorrow, at one time, and that at the hour of his death, ſufficient? that the Sacraments freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Grace, and put every one in the ſtate of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, come and take them who will; prepared, or unprepared? only if he, that goes to them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth ſuch his ſins; and doth not reſolve againſt receiving any benefit by them, — <hi>Onely</hi> (ſaith he)<note n="‖" place="margin">c. 3. §. 6. p. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>that there be no mortal ſin unconfeſſed, that there be no actual oppoſition in the Will to the Sacrament; as for inſtance, if a man that goes to be baptized, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves with himſelf not to be baptized;</hi>
[i. e. not to have the benefit of Baptiſme], And that thus eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one is rid of <hi>Sin,</hi> and its <hi>Eternal</hi> puniſhment. And then, for the <hi>Temporal</hi> that remains, the
<hi>charges</hi> come to a very ſmall matter, and this puniſhment is redeemed too; and ſo away, ſtraight to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. So that he ſaith of Catholicks — <hi>That it is the hardeſt thing that may be,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 212.</note> 
               <hi>for any one to want grace among them, if they do but ſuffer the uſe of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon them; and that they are the gentleſt givers of it imaginable; for all they deſire of their Patients for Grace, is only for them to lye ſtill; but if they ſhould chance to be unruly, and kick away the Prieſts, or their rites, I know not then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what may become of them.</hi> And page 181. he ſaith —
<hi>That it is impoſſible to imagine a doctrine that more effectually over-throws the neceſſity of a good life, than theirs doth:</hi> [It ſeems the Proteſtants
<hi>Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by Faith alone</hi> is nothing to it]. In all which I think, in common prudence he ought to have ſhewed a little more moderation, if he intended to have gained belief even with his own party.</p>
            <p>Now, out of Charity to thoſe who may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41841:4"/>by him, I ſhall, without much engagement, in the particular controverſies, briefly ſhew to the pious Reader, that this Author, in none of theſe points fore-mentioned, hath dealt faithfully, or truly related the Doctrine of the Roman Church; and I deſire the Readers faith to my words no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the following Teſtimonies make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>3</label> 1. For the firſt then, the <hi>Non-neceſſity</hi> of
<hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> ſave at the <hi>Hour</hi> of <hi>Death.</hi> For the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary hereof,<note place="margin">1. Of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance not to be deferr'd.</note> Firſt, It is clear out of the Doctrine of the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> that no perſon that hath the uſe of Reaſon, can enter into the ſtate of Grace, or Juſtification; can be capable of the benefit of any Sacrament, even that of Baptiſme, much leſs of the reſt, the Sacrament of Penance, of the Euchariſt, &amp;c. without an Actual <hi>Repentance</hi> preceding. [See <hi>Conc. Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi>
6. Where ſpeaking of the preparation for obtaining Juſtification, it requires in ſuch perſon—<hi>ſidem, ſpem, Dilectionem dei,</hi> and, <hi>adverſus peccata odium, &amp; deteſtationem, hoc eſt eam paenitentiam, quam ante Baptiſmum agi o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet; &amp; propoſitum inchoandi novam vitam, &amp; ſervandi mandata;</hi> quoting the Text, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.28.
<hi>Paenitentiam agite, &amp; baptizetur unuſquiſque re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum in nomine Jeſu Chriſti,</hi> and Mat. 24.19. — <hi>Baptizantes eos in nomine Patris,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>&amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes eos ſervare quaecunque mandavi vobis.</hi> Again, for the Sacrament of Penance, after a relapſe, the Council declares it to require yet a greater prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration by
<hi>Repentance</hi> than Baptiſm doth. — <hi>Ad
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41841:4"/>quam novitatem vitae</hi> (ſaith it<note n="‖" place="margin">Seſſ.
14. c. 2.</note>) <hi>&amp; integritatem, per Sacramentum Paenitentiae ſine magnis noſtris fletibus &amp; laboribus, Divinâ id exigente Juſtitiâ, pervenire nequaquam poſſumus.</hi> Again, for the Sacrament of the Euchariſt, here the <hi>worthy</hi> Receiver ought to be already in the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Grace;</hi> &amp; all, guilty of any Mortal Sin, are required to prepare themſelves not only with <hi>Repentance,</hi> but the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Seſſ.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 7. — <hi>Eccleſiaſtica autem conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo declarat, eam probationem neceſſariam eſſe, ut nullus, ſibi conſcius mortalis peccati, quantumvis ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi contritus videatur, abſque premiſſâ Sacramentali Confeſſione, ad Sacram Euchariſtiam accedere debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at.</hi> For the <hi>time</hi> alſo, the ſame Church requires of all her Children, at Leaſt once a year, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Confeſſion of their ſins, in order to the holy Communion; though it is the practice of many to receive it every Feſtival, or once a week; or at Leaſt once in a fortnight. So that thoſe, who hold no neceſſity of <hi>Repentance,</hi> ſave at the hour of <hi>Death,</hi> muſt alſo hold no neceſſity of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> of <hi>Faith, Hope, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> or the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> of being a member of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or of the <hi>Church,</hi> but <hi>in articulo mortis.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>4</label> This being the Doctrine and Practice of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church, concerning Repentance, conſider what juſt cauſe this Author had in diſparagement thereof to ſay<note n="‖" place="margin">p. 182.</note> — <hi>We dare not flatter men ſo</hi> [in teaching that Repentance only <hi>in articulo mortis</hi> ſerves the turn] <hi>into eternal miſery; we cannot but declare to them the neceſſity of a ſincere repentance and holy life in order to Salvation</hi> [as if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> declared no ſuch thing] And —<hi>we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abſolve thoſe, whom God hath declared he will not abſolve,</hi> [i. e. the impenitent; but doth he not number among theſe men not to be abſolved, the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41841:5"/>old ſinner repenting on his death-bed, whom the Popiſh Prieſt with his two fingers and a thumb ventures to abſolve? whom, he ſaith, God hath declared he will not abſolve, if his words here have any application to his former. He goes on] <hi>Indeed for the ſatisfaction of truly penitent Sinners our Church approves of applying the promiſes of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in Scripture, to the particular caſe of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; which is that we mean by Abſolution.</hi> Here (if I rightly underſtand him) this Author ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes
<hi>Abſolution</hi> only uſeful for the ſatisfaction of the truly penitent; not alſo neceſſary for the effectual Remiſſion of their ſin, if Mortal. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, in his deſcribing it only, an <hi>Application of the promiſes of pardon in Scripture,</hi> he ſeems to make Sacerdotal Abſolution nothing differing in its ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or efficacy from a Laick's; for, ſurely, theſe may alſo apply ſuch Scriptures, as they ſee need, to the Penitents comfort. How his Superiors may like of this, I know not.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>5</label> But here it ſeems neceſſary, that Proteſtants ſhould be undeceived in this matter, and further acquinted, That the Churches Act of Sacerdotal Abſolution is not only beneficial for the conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of true Penitents, but neceſſary for the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all their <hi>mortall</hi> ſins, by, or before God; and that, when ever ſuch Abſolution can be had, and they, not out of an invincible but faulty ignorance hereof, do neglect, or contemn it, they can have no juſt hopes, the Ordinance of God ſtanding as it doth, of the Remiſſion of any ſuch Mortal ſin, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted after Baptiſme, by God himſelf. And for this, I refer any, who think this matter worthy their further inquiry, not to the Fathers or Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Doctors, but even to <hi>Biſhop Andrews</hi> in his Court-Sermon, and Comment on
<hi>Jo.</hi> 20.23. —
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41841:5"/>
               <hi>Quorum remiſeritis peccata,</hi> &amp;c. where concerning Sacerdotal Abſolution its having a juſt ſhare in Remiſſion of ſin—<hi>We are not</hi> (ſaith he),<note place="margin">pa. 58.</note> 
               <hi>the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God thus ſtanding, to rend off one part of the Sentence: There are here expreſſed, three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:</hi> 1 <hi>The Perſon of the Sinner in quorum;</hi> 2 <hi>of God, in remittuntur;</hi> 3. <hi>Of the Prieſt remiſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. Three are expreſſed, and where three are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, three are required; and where three are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, two are not enough. It is St.</hi> Auguſtine <hi>that thus ſpeaketh of this Eccleſiaſtical Act in his time</hi> — <hi>Nemo ſibi dicat, occulte ago paenitentiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hom. 29. de 50.</note> 
               <hi>apud deum ago. Novit deus qui mihi ignoſcit, quia in corde ago. Ergo ſine cauſâ dictum eſt, quae ſolveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis in terrâ, ſoluta erunt in Caelo: Ergo ſine cauſâ Claves datae ſunt Eccleſiae Dei; Fruſtramus Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium Dei, fruſtramus verba Chriſti.</hi> Thus He. where alſo he takes notice, that the Ordination of Prieſts (even thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) is only by theſe words, <hi>Quorum remiſeritis peccata,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 57.</note> &amp;c. — <hi>Neither are they</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that are ordained, or inſtituted to that calling, ordained or inſtituted by any other words or verſe, than this. Yet not ſo, that abſolutely without them, God cannot beſtow it.</hi> [A thing alſo ſaid by Catholicks.]
<hi>But ſpeaking of that which is proper and ordinary, in the courſe by him eſtabliſhed, this is an Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Act, committed, as the reſidue of the Miniſtry of reconſiliation, to Eccleſiaſtical Perſons.</hi> [I add: and ſo properly and ordinarily, we to obtain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion <hi>i. e.</hi> of ſuch Mortal ſins, by their Abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if we expect it from God's]. And according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the words of the Abſolution of Penitents run thus in the Engliſh Liturgy— <hi>I, by the Authority of Jeſus Chriſt committed to me</hi> [i. e. in theſe words here, <hi>Quorum remiſeritis peccata</hi>] <hi>abſolve thee,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41841:6"/>And—<hi>God ordinarily proceedeth</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Biſhop</hi>)
<hi>in remitting ſin by the Churches Act.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag 53.</note> And hence
<hi>they have their parts in this work, and cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded; no more in this, than in other acts and parts of their function. And to exclude them, is (after a ſort) to wring the Keyes out of their hands, to whom Chriſt hath given them;</hi> is <hi>to cancel, and make void this clauſe of Remiſeritis, as if it were no part of the Sentence; To account of all this ſolemn ſending and aſpiring</hi> [or breathing on them. <hi>Jo.</hi> 20.22.] <hi>as if it were an idle and fruitleſs ceremony.</hi> Be this Sacerdotal Act, then, only declarative; be it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the Evangelical Promiſes, or what you will elſe; yet it is a ſpecial Authority given to Chriſts Miniſters, ſo that ordinarily for Mortal ſins, which ſins only, after Baptiſme, put us out of the ſtate of Grace, it ſeems, without the <hi>remiſeritis</hi> of the Prieſt, there is no <hi>remittuntur</hi> by God; if we take the Judgment, not only of the Roman Doctors, but of
<hi>Biſhop Andrews.</hi> To whom give me leave to add the words of Mr. <hi>Thorndike</hi> on the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that it may make the more impreſſion on ſome conſidering Proteſtant, when he ſees the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſuch a truth to force a confeſſion from the pens of ſuch Perſons contrary to ſecular intereſt. He, at his Majeſties happy return, in his <hi>Juſt Weights</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">ch. 18. p. 122.</note> making many propoſals of the
<hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> mentions this among the reſt, the reſtoring the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Keys,</hi> as to impoſing Penances on ſuch, whoſe ſins have voided the grace, or, effect of their Baptiſme (called by Catholicks Mortal Sins) that ſo by the Churches Miniſtry they may obtain a true and valid remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, — <hi>It will appear</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table caſe, to conſider, how ſimple innocent Chriſtians are led on till death, in an opinion, that they want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41841:6"/>requiſite for the obtaining and aſſuring of the pardon of their ſins; when it is as manifeſt that they want the Keyes of the Church, as it is manifeſt, that the Keys of the Church are not in uſe for that purpoſe.</hi> S. <hi>James ordaineth, that the Presbyters of every Church pray for the ſick, with a promiſe of pardon for their ſins. This</hi>
[promiſe] <hi>ſuppoſeth them quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, by ſubmitting their ſins to the Keys of the Church, which the Presbyters do mannage. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe belongs not to the Office of Presbyters upon other terms</hi> [but by their ſubmitting their ſins to the Keys]. And after—<hi>In the mean time</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Forgiveneſs of Sin, according to S.</hi> James, <hi>comes by the Keys of the Church; Recovery of Health, from the Prayers of it.</hi> Again, in his Epilogue, l. 3. <hi>ch.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 94.— <hi>If this be ſaid</hi> [i. e. that when the Churches Miniſtry cannot be had, a deſire thereof ſerves the turn, for pardon of ſuch ſin]. <hi>I will allow</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that he, who refuſes the Miniſtry of the Church (rendring him a reaſonable preſumption of attaining reconcilement with God, by the means of it, according to the juſt laws of Chriſtianity) can have no cauſe to promiſe himſelf pardon without it.</hi> Thus He. Though it is true, that he maintains the Church hath no power to forgive ſins immediatly, but only by the medicine of Penance; and, that he ſuppoſeth alſo ſome ſuch caſes, wherein the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of Mortal ſin may be obtained without the Keys, as differ from the Doctrine of Catholicks. Pardon this Digreſſion, becauſe I hope it may be uſeful. Now to go on in the preſent matter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>6</label> Next; ſetting aſide theſe neceſſities of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in order to the Sacraments, to Juſtification, to an Holy life upon pain of offending againſt the vertue of Religion, and Charity; and conſidering it barely, as it is an Affirmative Precept; Here,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41841:7"/>Though it is generally true of theſe Precepts, (and ſo of this) that <hi>non obligant ad ſemper;</hi> for ſo one ought continually to do nothing elſe but practiſe ſuch a particular command; and as much all, as any one; and ſo a man muſt be ſaid to be bound neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily in the next inſtant after his ſinning, to exerciſe immediatly an act of Repentance, or elſe to ſtand Guilty of incurring a ſecond Mortal ſin; and theſe Mortal ſins too to multiply, as the inſtants do, wherein the act is longer deferred;) yet 1ſt. After ſinning, a preſent Obligation is maintained by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick writers of no further perſeverance in, or bearing any affection to, ſuch ſin; For this were ſinning a new; all ſinning is at all times prohibited — <hi>Loquimur</hi> (ſaith <hi>Lugo</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">D. Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentia diſp. 7. §. 11.</note>) <hi>de mer â dilatione Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiae, ceſſante omni continuatione pec<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cati praeteriti &amp; omni affectione erga illud.</hi> Which if any one thinks hardly poſſible to be obſerved, <hi>viz.</hi> to lay aſide af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to ſin, without an actual diſaffection to, and diſplicency of it; not to hate God, and as yet not to Love him; this ſtill the more haſtens an act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance? 2ly. The Act of penitency is made by Catholick writers as neceſſary after ſin, as the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Loving God is; and, if we will follow the moſt common opinion of them, though they ſay, it is hard to preſcribe to ſinners <hi>poſitively</hi> a <hi>ſet time,</hi> after which any longer delay of Repentance would be another Mortal ſin; yet <hi>negatively</hi> it is not hard to name it; <hi>viz.</hi> That Repentance is not for any long time to be deferred; and then for the poſitive time, they firſt tell us; the ſooner, the better; and the ſafer;
[<hi>Conſultiſſimum eſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>P. Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Moral. Theol. l. 5. tr. 6. c. 2.</note>) <hi>ſtatim poſt commiſſum peccatum ad paeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam confugere.</hi> And the Roman Catechiſm<note n="‖" place="margin">De Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Sacram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paenitent</note> is yet more pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, —
<q>
                  <hi>Neque enim</hi> (ſaith it) <hi>ad ullum</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:41841:7"/>
                  <hi>temporis punctum, cum in memoriam praeterita peccata redeunt, vel jam aliquid offendimus, contritione animus debet vacare</hi>]</q> this being the Key by which, after Mortal Sin, we can only re-enter into ſuch a condition, wherein we can have any title to Chriſt, or Heaven; and then they remit every one, for this ſeaſonable time, to the dictate, and remorſe of his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; or the directions of thoſe whom he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints with it. Of which matter thus <hi>Suarez</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">De Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent. Diſp. 15. §.
6. n. 20.</note>
               <q>
                  <hi>Hanc obligationem [paenitendi,</hi> i. e. <hi>ſub mortali peccato] magis explicamus per modum praecepti negativi, non differendi converſionem ad Deum uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad mortem; vel diuturno tempore</hi>— <hi>Ex hac autem obligatione negativâ neceſſario infertur affirmativa, al'quando excreendi hanc contritio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ante mortem. Illud vero tempus, ſi non ſit poſitivâ lege praeſcriptum, prudenti arbitrio ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius hominis, vel alterius qui (ejus conſcientiâ cognitâ) poſſit auxilium praeſtare, committen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt, ut penſatis circumſtantiis omnibus ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicet, an incipiat nimia eſſe dilatio, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aliquam regulam certiorem, aut magis particularem aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare poſſum, tam in hoc precepto, quam in aliis affirmativis; praeſertim circa actus, qui ad Deum ordinantur, ſolâ ac nudâ ratione naturali perſpectis.</hi>
               </q> [though in relation to other things mentioned before (our Juſtification, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) it is neceſſary, when ever they are.] And the very ſame he ſaith elſe-where of the act of the precept of
<hi>Charity,</hi> or of <hi>Loving</hi> God.
<q>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">De Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Diſp. 5 §. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Articulus temporis non tam affirmative, quam negative aſſignari poteſt; ſicut in praecepto
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41841:8"/>reſtitutionis, dicitur obligare ad non multum differendum reſtitutionem, licet non poſſit aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari primum inſtans reſtitutionis.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>So</hi> Card. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go <hi>de Paenitentia.</hi> Diſp. 7. §. 11. n. 248. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring that of
<hi>Repentance</hi> with the obligation of the precept of <hi>Loving God.</hi> And ſee <hi>Paul Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mann</hi> Theol. Morall. 5. tract. 6. c. 2. n. 6. quoting S. <hi>Thomas, Caietan,</hi> and others, to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>7</label> Yet mean while it is moſt true, that there is no time in this life that can be ſtated too late wherein to perform ſuch a <hi>Repentance</hi> as may be
<hi>Salrificall;</hi> and that, if deferred till death, yet this may be valid, [may; but I do not ſay, always, or often, is; nor yet the Roman Doctors; who warn all to take heed of ſuch a procraſtination, and in this matter cite that of St. <hi>Auſtin-Paenitentia, quae, ab infirmo peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi> [<hi>petitur,</hi> i. e. of the Prieſt, to preſcribe him penance] <hi>infirma eſt; quae autem a moriente pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur, timeo, ne &amp; ipſa moriatur.</hi> And again,<note n="‖" place="margin">De Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Serm. 57.</note>
               <q>
                  <hi>Agens Paenitentiam ad ultimum &amp; reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ſi ſecurus hinc exit, ego non ſum ſecurus.</hi> And— <hi>Nunquid dico, damnabitur? non dico. Sed dico etiam liberabitur? Non. Et quid di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis mihi? Neſcio; non praeſumo; non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitto</hi>]. </q> And ſo, if we put the caſe, that one lives a wicked life for three-ſcore or four-ſcore years, yet I ſuppoſe, will a Proteſtant Miniſter on his death bed exhort ſuch a one to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, nor pronounce it fruitleſs; therefore neither may they expect the Catholick ſhould do this, when ſuch a perſon, dying in that Church, adds to his <hi>Repentance</hi> the <hi>Sacraments;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41841:8"/>Confeſſion</hi> of his ſins to the Prieſt, the receiving his
<hi>Abſolution,</hi> the <hi>Holy Communion,</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem unction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>8</label> Laſtly, if, after all this ſaid here, this <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> or Biſhop <hi>Taylor,</hi> can produce ſome Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies out of other Catholick Writers to this purpoſe; that <hi>Repentance,</hi> conſidered meerly as an <hi>affirmative praecept,</hi> and abſtracted from all thoſe neceſſary ends mentioned before, (in reſpect of all which God conditionally requires it), it not obligatory, as in caſe of neceſſity, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mortal ſin if deferr'd any longer, ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>articulo mortis;</hi> Yet this ſeems far from ingenuous dealing, either from ſuch Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to deduce in general theſe Authors affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>that God hath commanded no man to repent ſooner than the Article of his death</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Rom. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolat. c. 3. p. 181.</note>; or, if ſuch things were rightly deduced from theſe Authors, therefore to accuſe the Church of ſuch a Doctrine: Since, where the Doctors of the Roman Church are divided in their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and her Councils are not found to have ſtated any thing therein, here either none of theſe opinions may be charged on the Church; or elſe, in Charity, that rather ought to be ſo, which to us ſeems the more reaſonable and true. Moſt of the Doctors of the Church in any Age are not Writers; nor, of theſe Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the major part School-men, or Caſuiſts, or applying themſelves to their Subtilties. And ſo long as the Church, I mean in her Councils, cannot be charged with a doctrine that ſeems to us malignant and corrupt, it ſeems vain to tell men, ſuch a doctrine is taught by ſeveral in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41841:9"/>the Church, when as its Subjects have many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Teachers in the ſame Church, that (with its allowance and Countenance) inſtruct them otherwiſe, and better. (For Example: What Catholicks are there, that do not receive from their Teachers frequent Exhortations to a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy repentance for their ſins, and Reformation of their lives: the chiefeſt Common-place in Divinity? and amongſt whom they do not firſt lay this <hi>Foundation of Repentance from dead works,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1</note> as the Apoſtle calls it?) But here eſpecially thoſe, who defend their ſeparation from the Communion of a Church by reaſon of its erroneous or corrupt Doctrines, are not excuſed at all in their ſhewing ſuch Doctrines taught (by ſome) <hi>in</hi> it; but only, if they make appear that theſe are taught <hi>by It;</hi> and the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief</hi> of them alſo exacted from its ſubjects. For, where the Church hath determined no ſuch corrupt Doctrine, we may ſtill abide in this Church, and believe otherwiſe: or, if we be of its Clergy, teach what is better. Much leſs then, may we complain for ſuch groſs and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt doctrine taught by ſome, when a greater number of others give us that, which is more pure and refined. And this here ſaid, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times theſe men, when it is for their Advantage, ſeem to be ſenſible of: as this Author, ſpeaking of the manner of the Sacraments conferring Grace, <hi>ex opere operato, Although</hi> (ſaith he<note n="‖" place="margin">c. 3. p. 109.</note>) Caſſander <hi>produce ſome particular Teſtimonies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it of perſons in that Church, yet we muſt appeal for the ſenſe of their Church to the decrees of the Council of Trent.</hi> But this he ſaid, when
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41841:9"/>he conceiv'd the Council to maintain a groſſer ſenſe of <hi>Opus Operatum,</hi> than ſeveral of their Writers.</p>
            <p>And from theſe Conſiderations, I conceive may be returned a reaſonable anſwer to Biſhop <hi>Taylors</hi> defence made in his <hi>diſſwaſive</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">chap. 2. Sect. 1.</note> for his charging (as he doth very frequently) that, which he calls (though indeed it is not, in that manner as he relates it, without their limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) a Common opinion of the Roman Doctors, or Caſuiſts, upon the Roman Church. He there ſaith for his defence of charging the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the School-men upon the Church—
<q>
                  <hi>That, if by the Doctrine of the Roman Church we mean ſuch things only as are decreed in their Councils, it is to be conſidered, that but few things are determined in their Councils:</hi>
               </q> [Here for his purpoſe, he ſaith <hi>few things,</hi> but elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where the multitude of them is exclaimed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by himſelf, and others]: But, if <hi>few;</hi> hence it follows; that few are required of him, for enjoying the communion of that Church, to be aſſerted or believed: But not; that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Common opinion of Caſuiſts is to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted, or pronounced by him a Doctrine of the Church, leſt her Doctrines ſhould be
<hi>few.</hi> Again he ſaith
<q>
                  <hi>That, if they</hi> [the Roman Doctors] <hi>will not be reproved for any thing but what we prove to be falſe in the Articles of their ſimple belief, they take a Liberty to ſay, and to do what they liſt, and to corrupt all the world by their Rules of Conſcience.</hi>
               </q> I Anſwer. That That ſo many of theſe Doctors, as he can prove to err in any thing, he may alſo take as much
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41841:10"/>liberty to reprove: but not, reprove or defame the Roman Church, or diſſwade her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for that error, which ſhe doth not own. Laſtly, He ſaith,
<q>
                  <hi>That their own men tell us, it is the Doctrine of the Church, when they ſay</hi> Communis omnium. <hi>It is the doctrine of all their men.</hi>
               </q> I Anſwer. <hi>Communis omnium</hi> is only <hi>opinio</hi> or <hi>ſententia;</hi> and that in ſuch things wherein he cannot deny the Church to have left to all their Liberty to think ſo, or the contrary. But when theſe men would ſay it is the Doctrine of the Church, he cannot but know their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com expreſſion, not
<hi>communis omnium,</hi> but that ſuch point is <hi>De ſide,</hi> from which none may diſſent. Again, this their <hi>Opinio omnium</hi> muſt admit many limitations. Firſt, Of ſuch School-men, or Caſuiſts as have writ of ſuch a Queſtion: and this extended only to thoſe of ſuch time as the Author writ in, not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; (when perhaps ſuch opinion, better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, may be changed). Secondly, Of ſo many of them as he hath ſeen; and, as ſuch perſon apprehends their ſenſe, in which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps too much addiction to his own opinion may cauſe a miſtake. And, in this particular point concerning <hi>Repentance,</hi> what ever
<hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naldus</hi> and <hi>Navarr</hi> ſay (though they ſay it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with limitations omitted by Doctor <hi>Taylor,</hi>) yet that it is not <hi>Sententia Communis Omnium</hi> is clearly ſhewed before. I ſay therefore, this Injuſtice of ſome late Proteſtant Writers in loading all the ſuppoſed Common Opinions of School-men, or Caſuiſts upon the back of the Church, if well conſidered, might ſave them,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41841:10"/>for the future much labour in raking into par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Authors, and picking out ſome odious ſentences, when their deſign is not the diſſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men from the reading or crediting ſuch Roman Authors in all that they ſay, for which ſuch ſearch were pertinent; but, from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Roman Church, as to which it ſignifies nothing.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>10</label> 2. For the Second; Of the <hi>Roman Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> or
<hi>Contrition,</hi> that it doth not include,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life neceſſary to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</note> or oblige any to, a forſaking of their ſins, or a
<hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>life:</hi> The contrary to this is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident and obvious in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> See <hi>Seſſion.</hi> 4. c. 4. —<hi>Declarat S. Synodus, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritionem non ſolum ceſſationem a peccato, &amp; vitae novae propoſitum &amp; inchoationem</hi> [i. e. from the beginning of the Contrition], <hi>ſed veteris etiam odium continere.</hi> And
<hi>Seſſ.</hi> 6. c. 14.—<hi>Docendum eſt in Paenitentiâ contineri non modo ceſſationem a peccatis</hi> [or a new life; ſo far it goes along with Proteſtants];
<hi>verum etiam Sacramenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem Confeſſionem, ſaltem in voto, &amp; ſuo tempore faciendam; &amp; Sacerdotalem Abſolutionem; itemque Satisfactionem per Jejunia,</hi> &amp;c. Thus much it goes beyond Proteſtants, and requires more in a ſincere Repentance, and a return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the grace and favour of God, than they do. Again, <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 14. <hi>can.</hi> 13.—<hi>Si quis dixerit op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timam paenitentiam eſſe tantum novam vitam</hi> [as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41841:11"/>ſome Proteſtants are there ſuppoſed to ſay, and Catholicks ſay ſo with them, excepting the <hi>tantum</hi>] <hi>Et pro peccatis quoad paenam tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem minime. Deo per Chriſti merita ſatisfieri pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ab eo inflictis, &amp; patienter toleratis, vel a Sacerdote injunctis, vel ſponte ſuſceptis; ut jejuniis, orationibus,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>Anathema ſit.</hi> Here alſo as it ſaith <hi>nova vita</hi> with the Proteſtants; ſo, in the reſt, it preſents to God ſomthing beyond them. Again <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 14. c. 8. ſpeaking of the Penitents ſatisfaction—<hi>Habeant autem</hi> (ſaith it)
<q>
                  <hi>Sacerdotes prae oculis, ut ſatisfactio, quam imponunt, non ſit tantum ad novae vitae cuſtodiam</hi> [or as before, <hi>ut vitioſi habitus male vivendo comparati contrariis virtutum actionibus tollantur</hi>] <hi>ſed etiam ad praeteritorum peccatorum vindictam &amp; caſtigationem.</hi>
               </q> Here are ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Penances required by the Church, for preſerving of the Penitents <hi>nova vita;</hi> which perhaps Proteſtants will allow; but exacted fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ad praeteritorum peccatorum vindictam</hi> too; This Proteſtants do not preſs. See <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 14. c. 4. in the Definition of Contrition one clauſe to be
<hi>Propoſitum non peccandi de caetero;</hi> in which alſo is included, and preſſed by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors a reſolution to avoid and remove, for the future, the former uſual neareſt occaſions of ſinning: Again ſee in the Deſcription after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> of <hi>Attrition</hi> this to be one clauſe—<hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas non peccandi</hi> [a <hi>Velleitas</hi> being not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient]. And ſee before. <hi>c.</hi> 2.
<hi>Novitas vitae</hi> made the end of all the Labours of Repentance. <hi>Ad quam tamen novitatem &amp; integritatem per Sacramentus Paenitentia, ſine magnis noſtris fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41841:11"/>&amp; laboribus, Divinâ id exigente juſtitiâ, pervenire nequaquam poſſumus.</hi> So <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 6. c. 6. One of the Diſpoſitions for obtaining Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is ſaid to be Repentance, and in it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly — <hi>propoſitum inchoandi novam vitam, &amp; ſervandi mandata:</hi> And, when Juſtification is ſo attained,— <hi>Nemo,</hi> (ſaith the Council) <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumvis juſtificatus, liberum ſe eſſe ab obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one mandatorum putare debet.</hi> And afterward <hi>Nemo ſibi in ſolâ fide,</hi> [you know againſt whom this was levelled] <hi>blandiri debet, putans fide ſolâ ſe haeredem eſſe conſtitutum:</hi> urging that of St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Saetagite, ut per bona opera certam veſtram vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationem &amp; electionem faciatis.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>11</label> And in the Councils mentioning <hi>bona opera</hi> here, it is ſtrange to ſee, of what contrary errors and ſeducements the Roman Church is impeached by her Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. Heretofore her Religion was decried, for that Catholicks held Juſtification by, and truſted for Salvation in, the <hi>merit</hi> of their <hi>good works:</hi> that they did them indeed, this was not denied; but did them with a ſaulty intention, and for a wrong end. And two of <hi>Bellarmin's</hi> five Books of Juſtification are written againſt Proteſtants in defence of the <hi>neceſſity,</hi> and of the <hi>merit,</hi> of <hi>good Works;</hi> and the Poſſibility of the obſerving Gods Commands, as to a ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from all <hi>Mortal</hi> ſin: But now they are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted on the other ſide; and now Catholicks are diſcovered to hold no Neceſſity of Good Works, of a New life, or forſaking of ſin: Now, for
<hi>Salvation</hi> with them it ſerves the turn, only to procure a <hi>Sigh</hi> or two, a
<hi>very little ſorrow</hi> for our ſin paſt, <hi>confeſs,</hi> be <hi>abſolved,</hi> ſin on,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41841:12"/>and ſo to Heaven. Again, it was the accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Proteſtants heretofore,<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lv. Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut. 3. <hi>l.</hi> 4.
<hi>c.</hi> §. 2. Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. conc. Trident. De Paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> (in their mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying of juſtifying Faith) that the rigidneſs of the <hi>Roman Contrition</hi> drave men to deſpaire, and left their Conſciences very unſettled, and tortured, in not knowing the juſt meaſure or quantity of it neceſſary for the remiſſion of their ſin; And <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſpends two Chapters (<hi>De Paenitent, l.</hi> 2. cap. 10, 11.) to free the Roman Church of this Charge; And now a complaint is brought againſt the <hi>Littleneſs</hi> &amp; eaſineſs of the Roman Contrition. How ſhall it pleaſe them?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>12</label> We ſee Contrition is defined in the Council of
<hi>Trent,</hi> in order to receiving the Sacrament of Penances — <hi>Animi dolor &amp; deteſtatio pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peccato commiſſo, cum propoſito non peccandi de caetero;</hi> which purpoſe is ſuppoſed alſo to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude an <hi>actual</hi> ceſſation from Sin before Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and the Sacrament, for that diſtance of time between our exerciſing this Contrition, and our receiving of the Sacrament; (<hi>Ceſſatio a peccato, novae vitae propoſitum, &amp; inchoatio,</hi> ſaith the Council); what more would theſe men have? The Continuation of an actual new life? This is that which is to follow the <hi>effect</hi> of the Sacraments, the infuſion of <hi>Sanctifying Grace,</hi> our <hi>Juſtification,</hi> our new Birth, and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation,</hi> by them. When Repentance is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by Proteſtants to the Baptiſme of the <hi>Adulti,</hi> doth it include an actual good life to precede ſuch Baptiſme? See Dr. <hi>Hammonds</hi> deſcription of this Repentance, in his <hi>Practical Catechiſme,</hi> c. 6. §. 2. p. 311. — <hi>The reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to forſake ſin and live Godly, is ſuppoſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41841:12"/>Baptiſme, to make the perſon capable of it. On the other ſide, the actual forſaking of ſin, is the conſequent task of him that makes a right uſe of the Grace of Baptiſm for his whole life after.</hi> Thus He. And p. 313. <hi>The forſaking of the heart</hi>
[which he calls a little before <hi>a general Cordial removing of ſin</hi>] <hi>is here meant by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> [i. e. before Baptiſm]; <hi>and the forſaking in the actions, is that to which the ſtrength is made over</hi> [to us] <hi>in Baptiſm.</hi> So he ſaith 1. <hi>l.</hi> 3. §. p. 56.—That <hi>ſorrow for diſpleaſing of God, and a real ſincere reſolution to amend and forſake ſin, have the promiſe of Mercy belonging to them.</hi> And indeed, if an <hi>actual</hi> good life be neceſſarily required before the Sacraments, before remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſin, or Juſtification, for what certain term is it ſo, before theſe may be adminiſtred or obtained? and is not <hi>perſeverance</hi> alſo in ſuch a good life neceſſary, (for, any relapſe undoes all)? and then, none are to receive the Sacrament, nor can obtain remiſſion of ſin, or Juſtification, but upon perſeverance firſt; i.e. but in the hour of their Death. But if this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſpeaks not of the <hi>Act of Repentance,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to the Sacraments, or Juſtification; but of that which Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> calls
<hi>the State of Repentance,</hi> or of Regeneration<note n="‖" place="margin">Ib. l. 1
<hi>l.</hi> §. 3. p. 54</note> there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more known than this Doctrine of the
<hi>Roman</hi> Church; That there muſt be not only a purpoſe, but actual ceſſation from all mortal ſin ſo long, as there is any continuance of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in ſuch a ſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>13</label> In the Name of God then, let us here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare together, concerning Repentance or a due
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41841:13"/>ſorrow for, and deteſtation of ſin, and the Living an actual New life, the Doctrine of the two Churches; to ſee which carries more ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and ſeverity in it. The
<hi>Proteſtant</hi> Clergy exhort a Perſon, relapſed after Baptiſm into a vicious life, for the regaining of Gods favour and pardon of his ſin, and for obtaining of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, to a due ſorrow for, and deteſtation of his ſin, and a ſtrict reformation of his life for the time to come: (For, a <hi>Sacrament</hi> for any fallen after Baptiſm, by which they may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the ſtate of Grace, they acknowledg none). Next: If a <hi>Penitent</hi> happen, after ſuch ſorrow for his ſin, and a new life led for ſome time (or at leaſt ſeriouſly purpoſed, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed) happen, I ſay, to return to his former, or perhaps a more, vicious courſe, they forſake him not, here; but firſt they either tell him, that his former faith, repentance, and good Life, obtained not at all for him any remiſſion of his ſin, or Juſtification, for lack of Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (wherein they muſt hold that none fallen from Baptiſmal Grace have remiſſion of ſin, or Juſtification, till the hour of their death); and ſo, that Perſon remains ſtill accountable to God for his former ſins before his laſt relapſe: Or they tell him; that ſuch former remiſſion, and Juſtification, and Gods Mercy thus deſpiſed, do ſo much the more aggravate this his ſecond fall; and make his preſent condition worſe than his former was, before any Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Next, they anew refer him to repentance, and to an actual new life again, for his cure, and the making his peace; becauſe Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41841:13"/>cannot be bounded by them: and this they ſtill preſcribe to him in all his relapſes, <hi>toties quoties:</hi> though aggravating much ſuch his falls to him, and forewarning him, that Repentance is not to be had, at any time, without Gods <hi>Grace;</hi> and that, after ſo many affronts of Gods mercie, may juſtly be feared his abſolute denial thereof. And, when ſuch a relapſing ſinner at laſt lies on his death-bed, they ſtill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort him to Repentance; which they do not deny may be effectual upon a ſincere
<hi>purpoſe,</hi> though without an <hi>actual</hi> performance, of a good life, where death prevents it. And, the the ſick Man profeſſing ſuch a repentance and ſorrow for his ſins paſt, as ſeems to them true and ſincere, and upon this, deſiring Abſolution of them, they give it him: i. e. (as this Author will have it)<note n="‖" place="margin">Rom. Idol. p.
183.</note> — <hi>For his ſatisfaction they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to his particular caſe the promiſes of pardon in the Scripture.</hi> — I ſaid, <hi>ſeems to them true:</hi> for, as Doctor
<hi>Hammond</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Catech. p. 56. 1. l. 3. §.</note> — <hi>Though ſorrow for diſpleaſing God, and from thence a real ſincere reſolution to amend and forſake ſin, have a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of mercy belonging to them: Yet no man can certainly judg</hi>
[whether his repentance be ſuch], <hi>neither Confeſſor, nor Penitent himſelf, For</hi> 1.
<hi>the man himſelf may through ſelf-love take that for Godly ſorrow and reſolution of amendment which is truly ſorrow for his own danger,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And</hi> 2. <hi>the ſenſitive expreſſion being often as great for the one ſorrow, as the other, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor may eaſily miſtake likewiſe.</hi> Thus Doctor <hi>Hammond.</hi> Yet ſuch Patient, they ſay, the Confeſſor may abſolve, in hope of the truth of his repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:41841:14"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>14</label> After this manner the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Clergy deal with Sinners. Conſider we now the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-Catholick</hi> way. Here the Eccleſiaſtical Governors require of one fallen from his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Grace by Mortal Sin in the firſt place Repentance; i. e. not only an hearty ſorrow for offending God; but alſo a firm reſolution of a new life; but then, exact alſo beſides this, I ſay, for ſuch
<hi>Mortal</hi> ſin, (which only, and not <hi>Venial</hi> ſins, as thoſe called by Dr.
<hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pract. Catech. l. 1. §. 3. P. 60.</note> —
<hi>Sins of Infirmity, ignorance,</hi> or <hi>ſudden ſurreption, acted in matters of little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, reconcileable with a regenerate eſtate,</hi> do exclude from Gods Grace, and are the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry matter requiring ſuch a remedy) the repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Power</hi> of the
<hi>Keyes,</hi> left by our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Lord to his Succeſſors, which relief God hath provided in caſe of ſuch relapſes; (of which I ſuppoſe the Reader hath not forgot what was recited but now<note n="‖" place="margin">§. 5.</note> out of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and out of Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> too, &amp; Mr. <hi>Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike,</hi>) and to the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of
<hi>Penance</hi> or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, <hi>Confeſſion, Abſolution,</hi> and <hi>Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> In which it is ſufficient, that the Confeſſor, upon <hi>probable</hi> grounds of the true Repentance of his Penitent, pronounceth Abſolution, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, (as Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> conceded but now) neither he, nor his Penitent, can be <hi>abſolutely certain</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>15</label> Here, alſo, ſuch Perſon is inſtructed; that the Sacrament, he receives, conferrs more Sanctifying Grace, accordingly as the Suſcipient is better diſpoſed and prepared for it; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that it is fruſtrated, and void of its effect,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41841:14"/>ſo long as he is defective in a due Repentance. And, that of ſuch a due repentance (Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Attrition) none can be utterly certain: for ſo might he be certain of his <hi>being</hi> in the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> ſince the efficacy of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>non ponenti obicem</hi> is no way queſtionable: And as <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſaith<note n="‖" place="margin">De Juſtiſ. l. 3. c. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Nemo Catholicorum erit, qui non reſpondeat, poſſe hominem certo ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuere ſibi remiſſa eſſe peccata, ſi conſtet eum ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am egiſſe, vel agere, paenitentiam.</hi> [But ſaith he<note n="*" place="margin">Ib. c. 8.</note> — <hi>Hanc propoſitionem [Mihi evidens eſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a vera Converſio &amp; Paenitentia] dico non modo falſam eſſe,</hi> &amp;c. — And — <hi>Neque poteſt quis certus eſſe certitudine fidei ſe non ponere obicem; cum poſſit ex ignorantiâ gerere affectum ad peccatum</hi> [and ſo have a defect in his Contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Attrition] Quoting<note n="‖" place="margin">Ibid c. 7.</note> St.
<hi>Auſtin<note n="*" place="margin">Homil. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>Quamdiu vivimus hic, de nobis ipſis nos ipſi ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicare non poſſumus, non dico quid cras erimus, ſed quid hodie ſimus.</hi> And <hi>Innocent.</hi> 3. — <hi>Nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſcire poſſe, an, ut oportet, egerit paenitentiam.</hi> And that is it, that keeps all more prudent Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, formerly guilty of great and Mortal ſin, in a perpetual exerciſe of Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>16</label> He is inſtructed alſo, That, where the <hi>Sin</hi> it ſelf, and the <hi>Eternal</hi> puniſhment thereof (the pardon of both which go ſtill together, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily depends on a right Contrition) is not remitted, there neither can be any (nor to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny purpoſe) cancelling of the <hi>Temporal.</hi> 1. That therefore this is one end of Penances and Mortifications, whether voluntary, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, and that in the firſt place, that, if our
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41841:15"/>former ſorrow for ſin were any way <hi>defective,</hi> &amp; falling ſhort of true or ſufficient Contrition or Attrition, theſe may conduce and help to the perfecting of it, and rendring it ſuch as is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the Divine Majeſty: in which
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition,</hi> and ſo <hi>pardon</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> and freedom from <hi>Hell,</hi> lies our chief Concernment. To which end, alſo, ſuch Penances were anciently given before
<hi>Abſolution</hi> pronounced; but are to the ſame end ſtill as effectual, when performed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, in caſe, I ſay, that ſuch repentance be ſtill deficient.</p>
            <p>[Of theſe Penances, in order to advancing our ſorrow for ſin into a true and acceptable Contrition, and ſo by it procuring remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>guilt</hi> of ſin, and the
<hi>eternal</hi> puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thus <hi>Bellarmin.</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">De Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent. l. 4. c. 12.</note> — <hi>Opera laborioſa, quae cum Dei auxilio fiunt a paenitentibus ſive ex con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruo, ſive ut diſpoſitiones, concurrere, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe ad culpae remiſſionem, &amp; mortis aeternae li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berationem, Scripturae &amp; Patres perſpicue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent:</hi> Citing that paſſage of <hi>Tertullian</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">De Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiae.</note> — <hi>Si de cruciatu Exomologeſis retractatis, Gehennae recordemini, quam vobis Exomologeſis extinguit.</hi> And thus he ſpeaks<note n="‖" place="margin">De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg. l. 2. c. 18.</note> in his anſwer to <hi>Chemnitius,</hi> who with other
<hi>Lutherans</hi> and Reformiſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, that Penances were anciently impoſed not for any ſatisfaction before God and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming and expiation of ſins, but only for the preſerving of Eccleſiaſticall dicipline &amp; ſcandal given to the Church.—<hi>Cum ipſe cum Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranis caeteris contendat paenitentias veterum diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinae cauſâ, non autem ſatisfactionis coram Deo, &amp; redemptionis, &amp; expiationis peccatorum inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutas,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41841:15"/>tamen fatetar ſe hoc etiam poſt remum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Patres non raro legiſſe</hi> [of which ſee much in <hi>Morinus</hi> de Paenitent <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi>
11. and 12] After which he adds— <hi>ſed profecto juſtius erat, novos Lutheranorum errores ex doctrinâ veterum Patrum corrigere, quam ex novis illis erroribus de Patrum doctrinâ &amp; Sententiis judicare.</hi> So De Paenitent. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 12. — <hi>Concurrunt &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>noſtra opera paenalia ad culpae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionem &amp; mortis aeternae liberationem ut diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitiones, ſicut actus ſidei,</hi> &amp;c. And ſee him elſe-where<note n="*" place="margin">De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent. l. 1. c.
12.</note> recommending the practice of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Penances for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> perfecting of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to thoſe, who deſire the benefit of an Indulgence, — <hi>Fieri enim poteſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ut aliquando Indulgentia non ſortiatur effectum, ob defectum ejus, qui illam ſuſcipit,</hi> &amp;c. [i. e. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of Contrition, without which the Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, how large ſoever, nothing profits any.] And, for this reaſon, to obtain the benefit of an Indulgence, are Penances alſo by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor impoſed. And thus <hi>Eſtius</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">4 Sent. Diſt. 15. §. 10.</note>— <hi>Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factio Chriſti per ſe ſufficientiſſima ad tollendam omnem paenam: ſed Divinitus ſic ordinatum, ut illa nobis non applicetur ne quidem ad ſolutionem paenae aeternae, niſi &amp; ipſi per opera quaedam pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalia Chriſto compatianiur,</hi> And — <hi>Sunt</hi> (ſaith he)
<hi>Conditiones quaedam paenales ex parte noſtrâ requiſitae ad hoc, ut paſſio &amp; mors Chriſti, tanquam pleniſſima ſatisfactio, nobis ad tollen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum reatum paenae aeternae appl'cetur.</hi> And of the Fathers he ſaith<note n="‖" place="margin">Ib. §.
13.</note> the ſame as <hi>Bellarmin</hi> — <hi>Probant manifeſtius ca loca, quibus ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factiones paenitentium iidem Patres extend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41841:16"/>&amp; valere dicunt, ad remiſſionem paenae aeternae.</hi> [And indeed, till this ſecured by a ſound Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, all Satisfactions for the temporal no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beſtead us]. See alſo <hi>Ibid.</hi> §. 14. where he cites thoſe words of the Apoſtle<note n="‖" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</note> — <hi>Quae ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum Deum triſtitia eſt paenitentiam in ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſtabilem operatur.</hi> And the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> in forbidding to the Prieſts the impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſlight Penances for greater crimes, leſt ſo they be partakers of others ſins, ſeems alſo to intimate, that where only ſlight Penances are performed, there many times happens to be a defective Contrition for the ſins, and ſo they not remitted, or at leaſt an eaſie relapſe into thoſe ſins that are remitted. See more of this matter below §. 58.]</p>
            <p>They tell him therefore, that, when this ſeeming Contrition, if not ſo at firſt, becomes afterward by the help of ſuch mortifications true and ſincere,<note place="margin">D. Tho. Supplem q. 9. Art. 1. Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez De Panit. Diſp. 20. §. 5.</note> and ſuch as God accepts, then only it is, and not before, that the Sacrament of Penance confers its proper effect, remiſſion of ſin, reconciliation to God, &amp; infuſion of Grace.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>17</label> 2. Beſides this end of Penances, ſuch Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is taught the neceſſity of them on two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accounts. 2. The next <hi>Per modum medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinae,</hi> and <hi>in novae vitae cuſtodiam</hi> (as the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent</hi>) for curing him of his former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes and vitious habits, and preventing ſin for the future; for mortifying the Body, its Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Luſts, and weaning him from ſuch things,<note place="margin">1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 9.17.</note> the affection to which betrayed him formerly to ſin. Which cure, and prevention of mortal ſin for the future, and ſo of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41841:16"/>anew the <hi>Eternal puniſhment</hi> thereof (without which prevention all ſatisfaction for ſin paſt is but as it were a loſt labour, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth to us, as to our Salvation) is alſo a ſpecial end and deſign of <hi>Penances.</hi> For (as
<hi>Suarez.</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">De Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent Diſp. 38. §. 4.</note> obſerves) — <hi>In hoc Sacramento magis intenditur ſalus Paenitentis</hi> [i. e. from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal puniſhment] <hi>&amp; ejus emendatio, quam ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactio pro paenâ [temporali] Quocirca illud praecipue debet attendere Confeſſor ut ſatisfactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem imponat accomodatam curationi &amp; praeſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni a peccatis; in quo oportet ut integritatem, &amp; ſeveritatem habeat: quod ſi in hac parte ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienter peccatori provideat, quamvis in caſtigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one</hi>
[i. e. in order to ſatisfaction <hi>pro paenâ tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porali</hi>] <hi>remiſſius agat, nunquam graviter erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit.</hi> Indeed according to the preſent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of Chriſtianity, when the whole world is crouded into the Church, and <hi>great</hi> ſins are grown more
<hi>univerſal</hi> and common, and as they become more common, ſo alſo appear (though they are not) much leſſer; and a too fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile <hi>commutation</hi> alſo of <hi>Penance</hi> hath much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxed the Churches ancient diſcipline; &amp; <hi>Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> likewiſe for great Crimes done moſt-what anciently, only upon ſome conſiderable neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, hath been more uſually joyned with <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> the infirmity, ſhall I call it? or hardneſs of moſt penitents relucts now to undergoe ſo great and laborious Penances as may bear a juſt proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their faults; (i e. as to removing the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal puniſhment temporal thereof, in this world or the next): and ſo, if they ſhould think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves over-charged with too heavy Penances,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41841:17"/>perhaps they would do none at all, but neglect and withdraw themſelves rather from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and ſo loſe the benefit of Penances alſo, as they are preſcribed them for the cure of ſin; and thus, whilſt the Confeſſor endeavours, by the proportionable Penances he preſcribes, their releaſe from all <hi>temporal</hi> pains, they, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſted with it, and ſo performing no penances at all, would continue in their former Vitious habits, and ſo incur the <hi>Eternal;</hi> In this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect therefore, conſidering the modern indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of many Penitents, ſome relaxation of ſuch <hi>ſatisfactory</hi> penances may be neceſſary, where Purgatory is the worſt of it; and where, with, or without, ſuch penances, Salvation is ſecure; But for Penances in order to prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing relapſes into ſin, and as they conduce to the effecting a true Reformation of Life, here a convenient ſeverity is alwaies neceſſary, and is by all diſcreet Confeſſors obſerved. The effect of which (<hi>viz.</hi> a Sinners amendment of life, and ſo leaving off ſin, and exemption from
<hi>eternal ſufferings</hi>) is incomparably of an higher conſequence, than is the freedom, in ſuch ſtate, from all temporal Purgations.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>18</label> 3. This of the ſecond; A third uſe of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances is
<hi>per modum ſatisfactionis;</hi> for Caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and taking revenge on himſelf-for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Sin;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7 11 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31, 32</note> and, by this (I mean, from the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Chriſts all ſufficient ſatisfactions procured thereby) preventing Gods temporal Judgments, and puniſhment thereof; ſuch, as are removable; for, ſome puniſhments of ſin (as death) are not ſo: Of which ſee more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low §. 65.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:41841:17"/>And here alſo he is taught, that the more Penance, and the more devoutly performed by him, takes off the more of ſuch future tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral puniſhments; and that, if the Prieſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth ſmall puniſhment for great faults (when perhaps he aims more at the cure of the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents ſinning for the future, than the expiation of the puniſhment of the paſt) that he is not therefore to think himſelf quitted of all the debt he owes to God, at ſo eaſie a rate; and that no whit leſſer or ſmaller <hi>fruits worthy of Repentance</hi> are required by God in the preſent, than in any paſt ages: (therefore alſo are the Clergy charged by the Council of Trent<note n="‖" place="margin">Seſſ. 14. c. 8.</note>— <hi>Convenientes ſatisfactiones injungere,</hi> and not <hi>leviſſima quaedam opera pro graviſſimis delictis</hi>) and that therefore ſuch Penitent, when, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps out of reſpect to his frailneſs and indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, ſmall penances are impoſed for great ſaults, ſtands ſtill engaged, if he would avoyd the remainder of ſuch puniſhments, to a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther performance of ſuch penal works, as he knows bear ſome nearer proportion to the weight of his former ſins. And—<hi>Quando Confeſſor leviorem multo paenitentiam imponit propter fragilitatem paenitentis, quam peccata e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus mereantur, debet illum admonere</hi> (ſaith <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez,</hi> Ibid.) <hi>illam non eſſe ſufficientem paenam; ſed propter ejus indiſpoſitionem cum illo benignius agi; ne forte ex levitate paenae occaſionem ſumat peccandi; &amp; ut fortaſſe moveatur ad alias vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarias ſatisfactiones aſſumendas.</hi> And
<hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin</hi> De Indulg. l. 1. c. 8.—<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t plurimum longe plus eſt, quod explandum reſtat per non
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41841:18"/>injunctas paenitentias, quam quod expiatur per injuntas.</hi> And c. 7. §. Ex his— <hi>Immo: Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes cum paenitentias imponunt, hortantur paenitentes, ut ipſi etiam ſponte aſſumant alias, cum credibile ſit impoſitas non eſſe aequales crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus.</hi> So <hi>Eſtius</hi> 4. Sent. diſt. 15. §. 41.—<hi>Si Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos officio ſuo defuerit [injungendo opera leviae pro delictis gravibus] vel etiam juſt â quadam ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione adductus minorem quam pro exigentiâ delicti ſatisfactionem injunxerit, omnino videtur paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, qui eum defectum vel ſcit, vel ſcire debet, teneri ad ſatisfactionem aliquam ultra aſſumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam; idque donec tota ſatisfactio perveniat ad quandam aequalitaetem cum paena temporali pro peccatis debitâ; cujus ratio eſt, quia quamdiu nondum fecit fructus dignos paenitentiae, nondum ſatisfecit divino praecepto.</hi> Matt. 3.8. And then if another Conſideration be added to this, that a leſs penance <hi>enjoyned</hi> by the Spiritual Judg is (by vertue of the Keys) as much, or more effective, than a greater, that is
<hi>Sponta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous</hi> and arbitrary, which alſo wants the merit of our Obedience; (all obedience being a kind of Mortification): I ſay, if this Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be added, the impoſing of light penances, where are great ſins, though it may be to many penitents very acceptable, yet is to them no ſmall dammage; and did they well conſider their own intereſt, they would ſeriouſly requeſt greater.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>19</label> Having thus ſhewed, that this Sacrament of Penance is no ſuch ſlight buſineſs, as this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor repreſents it, I proceed. After this
<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> received, and the ſuppoſed effect of it, <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and
<hi>remiſſion</hi> of his former
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41841:18"/>
               <hi>ſins;</hi> this Penitent is further inſtructed, that there is neceſſary an actual good life, which was before purpoſed and <hi>reſolved,</hi> and an actual ceſſation from all <hi>Mortal</hi> ſin: And that, upon relapſe into ſuch ſin, and his former wicked courſes, this <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> is loſt; and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, not into as bad, but much worſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than that before his Repentance, and Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, by reaſon, of the Grace of God ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted and deſpiſed, and as it were by force e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected; of his great ingratitude to ſo great mercy; of his ſinning now, when by ſuch grace received, he might much more eaſily have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyded it; of the breaking his penitential re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions; laſtly, by reaſon of the great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, from God's Grace now juſtly more withdrawn, of renewing again his Repentance. So that, though, <hi>toties quoties</hi> by the ſame means repeated, he may <hi>poſſibly</hi> riſe again from ſuch a fall; (as alſo ſaith the Proteſtant too); Yet, ſince this riſing cannot be without the help of <hi>Grace,</hi> even for the firſt ſtep of it, <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> it is juſtly to be feared, leſt this, before deſpiſed, be afterward denied.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>20</label> Laſtly, For prevention as much as the Church can, of ſuch dangerous relapſes; if their ſpiritual Confeſſors have obſerved in any (notwithſtanding what ever promiſes made in Confeſſion), after often uſe of the Sacraments, no ſuch actual change of manners, or ceſſation from former ſins, and reformation of life to follow; the Sacrament for the future to ſuch a one is to be ſuſpended, and not conferred, till the ſincerity of his Repentance is further clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41841:19"/>and rendred more probable: Eſpecially upon their diſcovery in any perſon ſuch ill ſymptomes as theſe; 1. That he hath ſinned as frequently after his former Confeſſion, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it: 2. Hath neglected to uſe the means for avoyding ſuch ſin preſcribed him in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: Hath not removed or remedied the former occaſions, or temptations to ſin, to which he hath been adviſed, or alſo hath enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelf: Or, 3. That the ſin is of very gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral practice, from which men are more difficult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weaned. The Sacrament, I ſay, on ſuch a one not to be haſtily conferred, till ſome actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al reformation for a certain time be practiſed, and ſome penances uſed in order to the beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a ſound Contrition, and former bad ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits appear ſome way corrected, and near oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of ſinning removed. —<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t poſſit de illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us diſpoſitione &amp; propoſito vitandi peccata morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſtare,</hi> ſaith Suarez. Which cautions of not admitting habitual and often relapſing ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners (i. e. as to Mortal ſins) <hi>toties quoties</hi> to the Sacraments occurr frequently in the Roman Caſuiſts and Schoolmen.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez De Paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. Diſp. 38. §. 7. n. 7. Layman moral. Theol. l. 5. tract. 6. c 4. n. 10.</note> And ſee the many Authorities to this purpoſe diligently collected by <hi>Monſieur Arnaud</hi> in his Book, <hi>De la fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quente Communion, part.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 45. and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, the inſtructions to Confeſſors of St. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo Borromeo,</hi> not long after the Council of
<hi>Trent, Ibid. c.</hi> 36. &amp; 38. The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> alſo in requiring Confeſſors not to impoſe ſlight Penances for great Crimes, <hi>ne alienorum pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum participes efficiantur,</hi> Seems much more to enjoyn the non-admittance of a ſlight pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41841:19"/>of Repentance, or amendment of life for great and inveterate Sinners, in order to conferring on them the Sacraments; in as much as a defect in their Repentance or Contrition is much more dangerous, than a defect in their ſatisfaction; the non-remiſſion of the ſin it ſelf, and its eternal puniſhment, following the one; the non-remiſſion of ſome temporal ſuffering only, the other.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>21</label> This being the proceeding of the two Churches in this matter, Both requiring <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> and (where life continued) an <hi>actual Reformation;</hi> but the latter exacting much more alſo, beſides theſe, and laying many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yoaks upon Sinners (as to the Sacrament of Penance) which Proteſtants are not willing to bear; conſider, what juſt cauſe this Author had, in diſparagement of its Laws and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, to ſpeak on this manner.<note n="‖" place="margin">p. 181.</note>— <hi>To what end ſhould a man</hi> [living in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>] <hi>put himſelf to the trouble of mortifying his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and forſaking his ſins; if he commits them again, he knows a preſent remedy,</hi> toties quoties; <hi>it is but confeſſing with ſorrow, and upon Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he is as whole as if he had not ſinned.</hi> Again,<note n="‖" place="margin">p. 182.</note> — <hi>We cannot but declare to Sinners the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a ſincere Repentance and holy life, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Salvation.</hi> Again,<note n="*" place="margin">p. 180.</note> — <hi>We believe, that as no man can be ſaved without true Repentance, ſo that true Repentance doth not lye meerly in Contrition</hi> [or ſorrow only] <hi>for ſins. Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in Scripture implys a forſaking of ſin, and without this we know not what ground any man hath to hope for the pardon of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> although he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41841:20"/>it, and be abſolved a thouſand times over.</hi> Hence the doctrine imputed to the Roman-Church, wherein his Proteſtant Reader muſt believe him, is; in the
<hi>firſt,</hi> that no man needs to put himſelf to the trouble of <hi>forſaking his ſin:</hi> In the <hi>ſecond,</hi> that there is no neceſſity of a <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Repentance,</hi> or <hi>holy life,</hi> in order to <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> In the <hi>third,</hi> that true Repentance (where life continued) implies not a <hi>forſaking of ſin;</hi> and upon this he <hi>chargeth the Doctrine of the Roman Church as prejudicial to piety.</hi> Thus men write
<hi>ad Populum,</hi> and for thoſe that can know nothing, but as themſelves inform them. Now, if theſe men in theſe things do ſpeak of ſome matters of Fact, or Practice only, not Doctrine; or of ſome Doctrines found to be held or taught by ſome in that Church, but not owned by <hi>It;</hi> let them then not cenſure the Churches Doctrine, but ſuch particular practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or doctrines. But indeed, ſhould their ſtile run ſo (as in truth it ought) it could no way ſerve their deſign, <hi>viz.</hi> the Diſſwading men from ſuch a Churches Communion; from which ſuch <hi>partioular</hi> doctrines, or practices, cannot juſtly deter them, becauſe they are ſuch things, as none by embracing its communion, are obliged to; and any member of that Church may as freely cenſure, as themſelves do. But ſuppoſing the very worſt, that ſuch a harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Doctrine did find <hi>many</hi> Patrons, and ſome malignant Doctrine were <hi>very commonly</hi> taught in this Church; yet doth this afford to none a juſt pretence for departing out of it, ſo long as this Church obligeth none to the <hi>belief</hi> of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41841:20"/>ſuch Doctrine, or makes it part of their Faith; and ſurely theſe perſons that diſcover ſuch a doctrine faulty, receive no harm by it; nor know they how ſoon the Governours of this Church (the Divine Providence ever watching over it) may take notice of, and rectifie it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>22</label> III. I proceed to the <hi>Third,</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> Doctrine (as he relates it) of the <hi>Sacraments</hi> their conferring Grace <hi>ex opere operato</hi> on what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſubject or Receiver of them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Of a right diſpoſition in the ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipient neceſſary to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring Grace.</note> though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo indiſpoſed or unprepared; only <hi>if all Mortal ſin be confeſſed</hi> (he ſaith not, repented of); <hi>and if there be no actual oppoſition in the will to the Sacrament; as for inſtance; If a man when he is going to be baptized, reſolves with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that he will not be baptized, or while he is baptizing, that he will not believe in the Father, Son, and the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Roman Idol. p. 206.</note>
[i. e. that the party in receiving it, reſolves in himſelf againſt receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the effect of it]. For the Contrary of this, Firſt, ſee the expreſs Declaration of the Council of
<hi>Trent</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Seſſ 14. c. 4.</note> concerning that Sacrament that moſt concerns Sinners after Baptiſme; the Sacrament of <hi>Penance,</hi> — <hi>Falſo quidam calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niantur Catholicos Scriptores, quaſi tradiderint Sacramentum Paenitentiae, abſque bono motu ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipientium, gratiam conferre: quod nunquam Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Dei docuit, nec ſenſit.</hi> To which this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, though preſſed by his Adverſary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,<note n="‖" place="margin">See p. 200. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> returns no Anſwer. So alſo, Seſſ. 7. can. 7. it ſaith — <hi>Dari gratiam per Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſemper &amp; omnibus, quantum eſt ex parte Dei;</hi> [but] <hi>ſi recte ea ſuſcipiant.</hi> And can. 6.
<hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41841:21"/>Novae legis continere gratiam quam ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant &amp; gratiam ipſam conferre,</hi> [But] <hi>non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentibus obicem.</hi> This in General.</p>
            <p>Come we to the particular Sacraments, and ſee what particular diſpoſitions and preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are required for receiving any benefit by them, 1. For the two <hi>Sacramenta Mortuoram</hi> (as they are called) the Sacrament of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and of <hi>Penance,</hi> which confer juſtifying Grace; this Council. Seſſ. 6. can. 6. (urged by <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> long ago to this purpoſe), declares, that <hi>ſuch Juſtification</hi> by any Adult, or already having the uſe of Reaſon (for we ſpeak not here of Infants) cannot be had, whether with, or without the Sacrament, unleſs the ſubject what-ever be thus pre-diſpoſed; that he have 1. <hi>Fidem</hi> (where we cannot but remember the <hi>Fides ſola juſtificat</hi> maintained by ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, but the Council is not content with this). 2. <hi>Spem,</hi>
3. <hi>Dilectionem Dei</hi> [ſuch a one, <hi>quâ illum omnis juſtitia fontem diligere inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit</hi>], 4. <hi>Odium &amp; deteſtationem peccati (per eam paenitentiam,</hi> ſaith the Council, <hi>quam ante Baptiſmum agi oportet</hi>) and laſtly 5. <hi>Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum inchoandi novam vitam:</hi> The Council, I ſay, declares no Juſtification (which Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the
<hi>Opus operatum</hi> of theſe two <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of the <hi>Dead</hi> in ſin) to be received by any Subject not thus pre-diſpoſed. And for the firſt of theſe Sacraments, ſee here in expreſs terms — <hi>Paenitentiam ante Baptiſmum agi o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet:</hi> and in the form of Baptiſme, the Adult <hi>Catechumen</hi> is firſt, to profeſs his Faith, and his renouncing Satan and all his works. For the Second, the Sacrament of Penance; ſee the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41841:21"/>Council. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 14. <hi>c.</hi> 4. declaring Contrition (as it is deſcribed in what is ſaid on the laſt point) perfect, or imperfect (called
<hi>Attrition</hi>), to be a neceſſary diſpoſition to the <hi>Opus opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>24</label> Which <hi>Attrition,</hi> that it may attain the effect of this Sacrament, or Juſtification; the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil declares alſo, that it muſt be (not any Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion naturally flowing from danger, and the fear of puniſhment; but) an Attrition Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, not having its original purely from our ſelves, but from the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> ſuch as is <hi>Donum Dei</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">c 4.</note> and
<hi>impulſus Spiritus Sancti;</hi> that it muſt alſo exclude <hi>voluntatem</hi> [or
<hi>affectum</hi>] <hi>peccandi;</hi> and contain alſo a <hi>ſpem veniae</hi> from God; which
<hi>ſpes veniae</hi> hopes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving a favour, and that done purely for ours and none of his own intereſt, muſt neceſſarily include a <hi>love</hi> to the <hi>Benefactor;</hi> and though the <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is as yet the moſt predominant in ſuch Attrition, and the Council hath not mentioned a <hi>love</hi> of him here, yet it is ſufficient, that the Council hath before, <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 6. affirmed in General, that there is no
<hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or remiſſion of ſin to be had by any Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament without a
<hi>love</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in ſome degree, and alſo hate of ſin as offending him; though, this not aſcending to that degree of <hi>Love</hi> or <hi>Hate,</hi> as a perfect Contrition hath, <hi>viz.</hi> to a loving of God, and hating ſin <hi>ſuper omnia, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabilia, &amp; deteſtabilia:</hi> therefore <hi>Cajetan</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Opuſe. Tom. 1. Tract. 4. Q 1.</note> on the Queſtion, <hi>An Attritio poteſt fieri Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritio,</hi> calls Attrition—<hi>Imperfect a diſplicentia peccati, imperfectum propoſitum non peccandi;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41841:22"/>imperfectuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Dei Amor.</hi> And a little before — <hi>Quâ paenitentes, in confuſo, tam totum tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus futurum, quam comparationem peccati ad alia odibila, quam etiam comparationem Dei ad alia amabilia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">l. 1. §. 3.</note>
               <hi>in voluntate ſuâ, habent.</hi> And Dr. <hi>Hamond</hi> in his Catechiſme<note n="‖" place="margin">p. 56.</note> confeſſeth, — <hi>That, though a bare ſorrow and compunction only reſpecting preſent terrors, hath no promiſe of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, yet if that which begins thus by Gods Grace, uſing ſuch terrors for ſoftening the heart, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves farther into ſorrow for diſpleaſing God, and from thence into a real ſincere reſolution to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and forſake ſin, theſe ſuperſtructions have a promiſe of mercy belonging to them, though the foundation had not:</hi> Now ſuch is the Council's Attrition, <hi>Donum Spiritus Sancti.</hi> Laſtly, ſuch an Attrition it is (which was ſaid before of Contrition<note n="*" place="margin">§. 15.</note>) as none, in his hating ſin, and loving God, yet can be abſolutly certain that he hath attained that Attrition which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires and accepts of, for his beſtowing the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental effect; (for otherwiſe, ſince this effect on Gods part never fails to be given to the rightly diſpoſed; thus one might be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of his Juſtification, and his being in the ſtate of Grace, which the Council ſaith<note n="‖" place="margin">Seſſ. 6. c. 9.</note> none can be, ſave by Revelation). The ſureſt ſign and note of ſuch a ſufficient Contrition, or Attriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is an actual change and Reformation of life; which is the moſt certain fruit of a truly chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and converted heart. This of the Pre-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions in the ſuſcipient neceſſary to receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the effect of theſe two Sacraments, which indeed is no ſuch eaſie preparation, if, as to the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41841:22"/>repentance required in the latter of them, all that be conſidered, which hath been ſaid in the laſt Point, and that, which the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſaith
<hi>Seſſ.</hi> 14. <hi>c.</hi> 3. That — <hi>Ad novitatem [vitae] &amp; integritatem</hi>
[remiſſion of ſin, the effect, or <hi>opus operatum</hi> of this Sacrament of Penance]
<hi>ſine magnis noſtris fletibus &amp; Labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Divinâ id exigente Juſtitiâ, pervenire nequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam poſſumus:</hi> and that therefore the Fathers call it, <hi>Laborioſus quidam Baptiſmus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>25</label> But yet ſomwhat more than this is required as a worthy diſpoſition to the other, called <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta vivorum, Confirmation, Euchariſt,</hi> and
<hi>extreme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction.</hi> For, all theſe for work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their due effect, require the Suſcipient to be actually in the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> at leaſt for any thing he either actually knoweth, or (if not culpably ignorant, either by neglecting to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelf, or by miſtaking the true weight of <hi>Sin,</hi>) might know, of himſelf to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Which when he knows, before receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe other, he is inſtructed to repair to the
<hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Penance.</hi> Now ſuch, as are here ſuppoſed to be in the ſtate of Grace, are alſo ſuppoſed to have not only the pre-diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for Juſtification (mentioned before), but the infuſed habit of <hi>Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>26</label> Only, if the Queſtion be put, whether alſo, for a due preparation, ſuppoſe to the receiving the benefit of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> (to which, beyond any other Sacrament, is required the greateſt reverence) an actual and ſenſible
<hi>Devotion</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes neceſſary, ſo that, without their diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this in themſelves, they are to deſiſt from
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41841:23"/>the other, It is ſtated by many of the Roman Doctors (yet not by all) Negatively, <hi>viz.</hi> That the want of this <hi>Devotion</hi> (or rather of their
<hi>ſenſe</hi> of it, which happens ſomtimes to the greateſt Saints), ſo they uſe their beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to acquire it, is not neceſſary to obtain the benefit of this Sacrament, and an augmentation of Grace. Of which, thus <hi>Suarez</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">De Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. Diſp. 7. §. 4.</note> againſt <hi>Cajetan</hi>—<hi>Doctrina contraria nimis rigida eſt, ac praeter humanam frugilitatem. Cum autem haec pendent ex Chriſti voluntate &amp; inſtitutione, pie potius credendum eſt, ſeſe in hoc humanae fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilitati accommodaſſe; praeſertim quia gratia ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitualis in homine manens tantae eſt dignitatis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Deum, ut vincere poſſit &amp; ſuperare leves omnes defectus, ac negligentias: &amp; ideo ipſa ſola eſt ſufficiens diſpoſitio ad hunc Sacramenti effectum.</hi> And Mounſieur <hi>Arnaud</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">De la frequent Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, part 3. c. 1.</note> ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently rigid in this matter, yet accords — <hi>That ſuch perſons</hi> [i. e. deficient in a ſenſible Devotion], <hi>may approach to the Communion, &amp; do receive the benefit thereof, provided their heart be right towards God, which may be known by their actions and works, which are the fruits of the heart, although they ſuffer ſome tepidity from the Aridities and ſterilities that hinder them from having thoſe ſentiments of Devotion, they deſire.</hi> If this then, thus circumſtantiated, be the <hi>want</hi> of <hi>Devotion,</hi> this Author ſo often men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as denied by the Roman Doctors to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny neceſſary obſtruction of the benefit of the Sacrament, it is confeſſed. But note, that ſuch a want of actual Devotion, that is, as is joyned with a deſire and endeavour to have it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41841:23"/>mean while, with an <hi>habitual</hi> poſſeſſion of it (for who hath the <hi>habit</hi> of <hi>Charity,</hi> as all Regenerate have, cannot want that of Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on); and is ſuch, as the Holieſt Perſons ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times cannot remedy, and this he ought to have told his Readers together with the other. This of <hi>Devotion,</hi> required particularly to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>17</label> Next; If we conſider the Sacrament of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction</hi> (becauſe, notwithſtanding the Text of Saint <hi>James</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.14.</note> — <hi>Is any man ſick a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you? let him call for the Prieſts of the Church, and let them pray over him, anoynting him with oyle in the Name of the Lord;</hi> it hath not eſcaped this Authors deriſion) the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo, or diſpoſition required in ſuch ſick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to receive the Spiritual benefit thereof, is, that they be in the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> (as was ſaid before): and this Unction is <hi>(ſi tempus &amp; Infirmi condit o permittat)</hi> to follow the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Penance, and of the Euchariſt admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred before it. Which <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Contrition</hi> of ſuch Perſon, ſince it cannot be by the Prieſt certainly known, therefore upon the ſignes of ſuch Contrition, and a deſire of the Sacrament, the Charity of the Church in ſuch an extremity denies it to none; though work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or not working its effect, according to ſuch Perſons due preparation, known only to God. And again, Since the Prieſt is not always at hand to apply ſuch Holy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> when deſired; therefore in caſe that ſuch Perſon, after ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, loſe his ſpeech, or ſenſes, the application thereof, which is only external, is not thought
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41841:24"/>fit, for this, to be with-held, becauſe the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thereof is conceived to depend on the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons former pious and penitent inclinations, when enjoying his Reaſon. This is the plain Song, on which this our Author hath made ſuch a ſtrange <hi>deſcant. p.</hi>
212. &amp;c, if ſomwhat to the commendation of his wit; yet little, of piety.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>28</label> Such are the <hi>Diſpoſitions</hi> requiſite to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pability of the effect of the <hi>Sacraments.</hi> But now, if in particular that of the Euchariſt be re-conſidered, not as a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> but <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> and the Repreſentative Oblation to God of the Paſſion, Merits, and ſatisfactions of our Lord: Here firſt; The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſpeaks not of it expreſly thus, as conferring or procuring any effect <hi>ex opere operato.</hi> 2dly. If the Schoolmen ſay this, they ſay it in no other ſenſe of this Sacrifice, than they do of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; namely, to the rightly diſpoſed, or putting no obſtacle to it, according as the Council,<note n="‖" place="margin">Seſſ. 22. c. 2.</note> explaining how it is Propitiatory, ſaith— <hi>Per ipſum fieri, ut, ſi cum vero corde &amp; rectâ fide, cum metu &amp; reverentiâ contriti &amp; paenitentes ad Deum accedamus, miſericordiam conſequamur,</hi> &amp;c. [i. e.
<hi>Quo Sacrificio cruentum illud, ſemel in Cruce peractum, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praeſentatur, atque illius ſalutaris virtus in rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſionem eorum, quae a nobis quotidie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittuntur, peccatorum applicatur</hi> *] And the Canon of the Maſs ſaith— <hi>Memento Domine famulorum tuorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib c. 1.</note>
               <hi>quorum tibi Fides cognita eſt, &amp; nota Devotio,</hi> &amp;c: In both which we ſee the Perſons, to be benefited, are ſuppoſed to be
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41841:24"/>rightly diſpoſed. But Thirdly, For any, though never ſo
<hi>indiſpoſed,</hi> it is true and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that the Oblation of the Euchariſt, being the moſt prevalent, and acceptable interceſſion, and addreſs, mortals can make to his Divine Majeſty, may benefit them by way of Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration, ſo as do alſo our <hi>Prayers;</hi> and ſo in all Ages it hath been ever ſolemnly offered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, as for all our neceſſities, and for all perſons, ſo for ſuch impenitent and indiſpoſed; that God would give them Repentance, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary diſpoſitions for the receiving of his ſanctifying Grace, and remiſſion of their ſin; and many times ſuch Oblation hath its effect, (as alſo have our Prayers) to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing ſuch a mercy of Gods Grace for them
[<hi>Hujus quippe oblatione</hi> (ſaith the Council<note n="‖" place="margin">Ibid. c.
2.</note>) <hi>placatus Dominus gratiam &amp; donum paenitentiae concedens, crimina, &amp; peccata etiam ingentia di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit</hi>]; But this effect, as to particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, not affirmed to be conſtant, or never fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And this <hi>Bellarmin</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">De effect Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram l. 2. c. 1.</note> anſwered long ago, in expounding the language of ſome School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men concerning the Maſs profiting the indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed —<hi>Loquuntur</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>de Sacrificio, non de Sacramento, Porro Sacrificium prodeſt impae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentibus per modum impetrationis; quia impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trat illis converſionem, &amp; paenitent am: quomodo etiam orationes noſtrae, licet non tam efficaciter id faciunt.</hi> And as this Author, p. 204 hath mentioned this Anſwer, ſo in reaſon he ſhould have told us his Exceptions to it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>29</label> To leave this Sacrifice (to which, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits thereof, Proteſtants are great Strangers,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41841:25"/>nor ſenſible of their loſs); and return to the <hi>Sacrament.</hi> Of theſe it hath been ſhewed, that all, for producing their effect, require a ſubject rightly diſpoſed: Next, Theſe Sacraments are ſaid to produce their effect, (though only on perſons rightly diſpoſed) <hi>ex opere Operato.</hi> 1ſt. In oppoſition to any neceſſary dignity, Sanctity, or Merit of the <hi>Miniſter</hi> thereof, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the
12th. Canon of the Council of <hi>Trent De Sacrament is in genere,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Seſſ. 7.</note> againſt that Propoſition of <hi>Wicloff</hi> and his followers, and ſome other Reformiſts mentioned by <hi>Soave,</hi> p. 233 —<hi>That a bad Miniſter doth not confer the Sacrament</hi>—<hi>Si quis dixerit, Miniſtrum in peccato mortali exiſtentem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>non conficere, aut conferre Sacramentum, Anathema ſit.</hi> 2ly. <hi>Ex opere operato,</hi> In oppoſition to the dignity, or the merit of the
<hi>Receiver</hi> of the Sacrament; which Sacrament worketh its <hi>effect</hi> on a ſubject, though not indiſpoſed, yet by no ſuch Diſpoſition <hi>meriting</hi> it. So <hi>Gabriel Biel</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">4. Sent. diſt. 1. q. 3.</note>—<hi>Praeter exhibit onem ſigni foris exhibiti non requiritur bonus motus in ſuſcipiente, quo de condigno, vel de congruo, gratiam</hi> [Sacramenti] <hi>mereatur: Sed ſufficit, quod ſuſcipiens, non ponat obicem;</hi> [or, where an <hi>obex</hi> is, have ſuch <hi>boni motus,</hi> as may remove it. See him <hi>Ibid. Diſt.</hi> 14. <hi>q.</hi> 2.] 3ly. <hi>Ex opere operato,</hi> In op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition not only to <hi>merit,</hi> but any <hi>diſpoſition</hi> at all in the receiver, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſo, that no diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though neceſſary as a <hi>cauſa ſine quâ non</hi> to the effect, or as to removing ſome obſtacles that may hinder it, yet is the <hi>efficient,</hi> or <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> at all, actually conferring, or immediatly
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41841:25"/>conveying the Sacramental Grace, but this is ſolely the <hi>opus operatum</hi> of the Sacrament. [And of this ſpeaks the Eighth Canon of the Council of
<hi>Trent</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Seſſ 7.</note> (nor hath <hi>Caſſander</hi> applied any other ſenſe to it, as this Author pretends he hath)<note n="‖" place="margin">p.
209.</note>. The words are — <hi>Si quis dixerit per ipſa novae legis Sacramenta ex opere operato non gratiam, ſed ſolam fidem divinae promiſſionis ad gratiam conſcquendam ſufficere, Anathema ſit.</hi> againſt that propoſition of the Reformers men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by
<hi>Soave,</hi> p. 264.—<hi>That by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Grace is not given in vertue of the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of them, called Opus Operatum, but that it ſufficeth</hi> [for obtaining ſuch Grace] <hi>only to believe the promiſe</hi> [of it]: and againſt thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Propoſitions ſet down before by him, p. 233.—<hi>That the Sacraments are not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; but men may attain the effect of them by Faith only.</hi> — And —
<hi>That the Sacrament hath never given Grace or remiſſion of ſins, but only the faith of the Sacrament.</hi> In which Eighth Canon the Council affirms—<hi>Solam fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem non ſufficere;</hi> not as if Faith were altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther needleſs to ſuch Sacramental effect; for therefore, it ſaith, <hi>non ſolam;</hi> but not it alone ſuffieicnt without the Sacrament;
<hi>without it,</hi> i. e. as it ſolely <hi>ex opere operato</hi> conferring the Grace, to which Faith alſo at the ſame time ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily pre-diſpoſeth.] 4ly. <hi>Ex ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re operato,</hi> in oppoſition to any <hi>diſpoſitions</hi> as neceſſary at all in the ſubject; but then, theſe School-men do mean of <hi>Infants,</hi> not of <hi>Adulti;</hi> becauſe in all theſe laſt, there is an Obſtacle of <hi>Mortal ſin</hi> to be removed; and this cannot
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41841:26"/>poſſibly be ſo, without the diſpoſitions of <hi>Faith</hi> and
<hi>Repentance. 5ly. Ex opere operato,</hi> In oppoſition to the Sacraments of the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> in which, Grace is ſaid to be received from the diſpoſition of the Suſcipient called <hi>opus ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantis,</hi> which was then <hi>ſignified</hi> alſo by theſe Sacraments, but not <hi>conferred:</hi> The contrary whereof is verified in the Sacraments of the
<hi>New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>30</label> Now, if things be found as they are here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, I deſire his Proteſtant Reader would conſider with what integrity this Author doth affirm, <hi>p.</hi>
202. this to be the Doctrine of the Roman Church —<hi>That the efficacy of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments doth not depend upon the preparation of the receiver, but the bare adminiſtration, or the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal work done.</hi> Again, p. 203. —<hi>That the Sacraments of the new Law do confer grace</hi> ex opere operato, <hi>i. e. by the thing it ſelf without any dependence therein upon the internal motion, or preparation of mind in him that doth partake of them.</hi> Again, how faithfully he deduceth, from <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> ſaying, <hi>That the Catholicks do not wholly exclude preparations in the receiver, but only</hi> ab efficientia <hi>from the efficiency of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Grace,</hi> p. 204. <hi>That the Efficacy of the Sacraments</hi> [which as I underſtand him is their <hi>actual producing</hi> ſuch an effect] <hi>in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring grace, doth not at all depend upon the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of the receiver.</hi> Again<note n="‖" place="margin">p. 206.</note> — <hi>That the preparation of our minds for the uſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments is unneceſſary. For if grace</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be effectually conferred by the force of the bare external action, which is acknowledged by them all, what need can there be of a due preparation of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41841:26"/>mind by the exerciſe of Faith, Prayer, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> &amp;c? From all which his concluſion is <hi>that the Roman Doctrine obſtructs the ſincerity of Devotion.</hi> In all which expreſſions, if this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor means, that according to the Roman Doctrine no qualification or diſpoſition in the Suſcipient is the <hi>inſtrument</hi> that effects or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Sacramental Grace, it is true, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to his purpoſe, or to his concluſion drawn from it, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſuch Doctrine obſtructs Devotion: But, if he means that ſuch diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not the <hi>efficient</hi> cauſe of ſuch Grace, and therefore it is not neceſſary at all to the effect, (as his words ſound), it is indeed much to his purpoſe, and infers his concluſion; but is moſt untrue. For many things are neceſſary to an effect, beſides the <hi>efficient cauſe</hi> thereof. To make uſe of an inſtance, himſelf mentions: <hi>Fire</hi> is the only <hi>efficient</hi> of the burning of wood, not the
<hi>drineſs</hi> of the matter, yet is <hi>drineſs</hi> in the wood, as well as heat in the fire <hi>neceſſary</hi> to the effect. And one may as truly argue in this, as he doth in the other; If the burning be effectually [<hi>i.e.</hi> efficiently] wrought by the fire, what need can there be of dryneſs in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Or, the efficacy [<hi>i. e.</hi> the efficiency] of the fire in its burning doth not at all depend on the qualification of the matter; or, ſuch qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concurrs not to the efficiency, therefore ſuch qualification is to ſuch effect, no other way, neceſſary.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>31</label> Secondly, Conſider with what truth he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, p.
206.—<hi>That Catholicks, when ſaying the internal diſpoſition of mind is neceſſary to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remove
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41841:27"/>impediments, do not mean by this internal diſpoſition the exerciſe of Faith, Prayer, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>by no means</hi> ſaith he [when as
<hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> in that Chapter, this Author cites, and therefore read, ſaith the expreſly contrary, and that ſix or ſeaven times over to this purpoſe —<hi>Opus operatum excludere fidem &amp; motum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum ab efficientiâ gratiae Sacramentalis, non tamen excludere ſimpliciter fidem &amp; motum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum</hi> [or in other places, <hi>fidem, &amp; paenitenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi>], <hi>ita ut Sacramenta (ut ipſi calumniantur) conferant gratiam accipientibus ea ſine ſide, &amp; ſine internâ converſione cordis</hi>]: But (ſaith he) <hi>they mean: That there be no mortal ſin unconfeſſed;</hi> [Now, ſuch mortal ſin may be confeſſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Faith,</hi> or <hi>Repentance,</hi> or any other diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to remove the obſtacle of ſuch mortal ſin: And next] <hi>That</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>there be no actual op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in the will to the Sacrament</hi> [which he explains thus]: <hi>As for inſtance, when he is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be baptized, he reſolves with himſelf that he will not be baptized, or while he is baptizing, that he will not believe in the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Thus he. Now, if any reflect on what we have proved before, is this ingenuous dealing? Is not this writing <hi>Controverſies</hi> for Ladies, for Women, for Laicks, and ſuch as cannot, or, from a contrary intereſt, will not make a ſearch into the truth of his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</p>
            <p>See again, what fidelity he uſeth, <hi>p.</hi> 209. (after his rejecting the common Doctrine of the Roman Authors, to ſearch that of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church rather in the Council of
<hi>Trent</hi>)
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41841:27"/>in his citing of the Eighth Canon of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Seſſion thereof to this purpoſe: That it affirms the Sacraments to confer Grace <hi>ex opere operato</hi> ſo, as to render Faith, or other diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the receiver needleſs; and mean while concealing one half of the Canon, that plainly ſhews the contrary.—<hi>Si quis dixerit per ipſa novae Legis Sacramenta ex opere operato non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferri gratiam,</hi> ſo farr he repeats it; <hi>ſed ſolam fidem divinae promiſſionis ad gratiam conſequendam ſufficere;</hi> this he omits; and the <hi>Sola</hi> is not at all conſidered by him. As if, from the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks ſaying,
<hi>Sola fides non juſtificat,</hi> he ſhould prove that they hold Faith not neceſſary at all to Juſtification: What this Canon oppoſetli, and how it is diſtinguiſhed from the Twelfth; I think I have given a ſatisfying account before<note n="‖" place="margin">§ — 29.</note>: Yet, after this, ſee with what a ſtrange confidence he concludes.
<hi>p</hi> 211. — <hi>I dare now appeal</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to the moſt indifferent Judg, whether what I objected to them concerning the efficacy of Sacraments, whether the minds of the receivers of them be prepared, or no, were not ſo far from being a calumny, that there is not ſo much as the leaſt miſtake in it: if the doctrine of the Council of</hi> Trent <hi>be embraced by them.</hi> Thus he— <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens os ſuum dicit, non ſum operatus malum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>33</label>
               <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> and the Roman Writers affirm, that this truth, <hi>That the Sacraments are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental cauſe of conferring Grace,</hi> is
<hi>Divine Revelation:</hi> and <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſpends two Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in producing the Scriptures that evidence it; and ſo ſaith, That the particular way or manner of their conferring Grace is a thing
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41841:28"/>not neceſſary to be determined, or underſtood, no more than that of the
<hi>Trinity</hi> is, or of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Articles of Faith. Yet, Here ſee <hi>p.</hi> 204. how ſolicitous this Author is to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the <hi>manner,</hi> as if the whole iſſue of the buſineſs depended on this; whether the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments be <hi>phyſical or moral cauſes;</hi> whether <hi>by a power inherent, or aſſiſtant;</hi> whether <hi>they produce Grace, or only the union of it,</hi> &amp;c. and, how candidly, he declaims againſt the impoſing ſuch abſurd, unreaſonable, and unintelligible things to be believed; and brings in the <hi>Alco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> and his <hi>wit-conferring Cap</hi> to be admitted with the like credulity: But takes no notice, that ſuch <hi>effect</hi> is proved, (or pretended by theſe Catholick Authors) to be <hi>Divine Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> (which they will not allow to the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> or to his <hi>Cap</hi>); nor ſhews he the falſity of ſuch an aſſertion in the diſproving of their Texts urged for it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>34</label> The Roman Doctors affirm, that, ſo one be in the ſtate of Grace, and ſo have the <hi>habit</hi> of <hi>Charity,</hi> and conſequently that alſo of
<hi>Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> an <hi>actual</hi> or <hi>ſenſible</hi> devotion, provided he uſe his beſt endeavour to be ſo devout, is not neceſſarily required for receiving the benefit of the Sacrament; (and the reaſon is given by them, becauſe this indeed ſeems too rigorous, and would cauſe too many ſcruples in mens minds concerning the preparation of a right devotion.) See this matter thus ſtated by <hi>Arnauld</hi>'s Adverſary<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Arnauld</hi> de la freq. Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. part. 3. c. 1.</note> who is held to ſpeak the moſt diminutively of a neceſſary preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. —<hi>This is the Doctrine of the Saints</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41841:28"/>he) <hi>that a man that hath not the devotion, and fervor of Charity he deſireth, but ſeems tepid to himſelf, is not obliged therefore to abſtain from the Communion; provided, he endeavour his beſt to excite himſelf to devotion, and humbly preſents himſelf in hope of benefit thereby.</hi> And again, c. 9. <hi>One often thinks he hath no Devotion, and yet ceaſeth not to have it. True Devotion is not a certain facility to apply ones ſelf to it; and a contentment that one reſents from it; but it is an effective will and deſire to pleaſe God.</hi> Now the Communicant here, being required by theſe Doctors to be in the ſtate of Grace, and to uſe his beſt endeavour to be alſo actually and ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<hi>Devout;</hi> ſee how ingenuouſly this Author conceals theſe two circumſtances, and chargeth on them the admitting perſons to the benefit of the Sacraments that are impenitent, and void of any Devotion, <hi>p.</hi> 207. —<hi>If want of devotion</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doth not hinder Grace being received, what arguments can men uſe to perſwade perſons to it? who will undergo ſo ſtrict an examination of himſelf, and endeavour to raiſe his mind to a due preparation for the participation of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if he knows before hand that he ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly receive Grace by the Sacraments without it?</hi> [i. e. without an endeavour to raiſe his mind to a due Devotion. But what Roman Doctor reacheth this?]. Again, p. 211. —
<hi>Whether one have any Devotion or no, he is ſure of Grace, if he doth but partake of their Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and need not trouble himſelf much about Devotion, ſince his work may be done without it. Never any Doctrine was certainly better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41841:29"/>for the ſatisfaction of impenitent Sinners, than theirs is,</hi>
[repreſenting the <hi>indevout</hi> and the <hi>impenitent,</hi> as the ſame; the indevout, through infirmity, or through neglect, appearingly, or really, all included.]</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>35</label> The like integrity this Author uſeth in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation concerning <hi>Extreme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> and its <hi>effect,</hi> p. 212. where he ſaith—
<hi>Not ſo much as the uſe of Reaſon is required for the effect of the bleſſed Sacrament of Extreme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction.</hi> And then deſcants<note n="‖" place="margin">p.
213.</note>—<hi>A hard caſe for thoſe who dye in mortal Sin! for if they could but expreſs any ſign of contrition by the motion of an eye or a fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, all were well enough, and they are ſure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Grace.</hi> And p. 214. —<hi>To make all ſure at laſt, the Exereme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction very ſweetly conveys grace into them, whether they be ſenſible or not.</hi> Whereas in candid and ſerious dealing, inſtead of jeſting, he ought to have repreſented the Roman Doctrine thus: 1. That for the Application of this Sacrament, the uſe of Reaſon in the Suſcipient is not neceſſarily required, if the perſon immediatly before, when having the uſe of Reaſon, appeared Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite, and deſired it.<note n="‖" place="margin">See be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore §. <hi>27</hi>
               </note>—And 2. That all ſuch perſons only, as have that true and acceptable contrition (known only to God) whereof they give external ſigns, do receive Grace, or the effect of this Sacrament, but no other. Let this ſuffice for the Third Point.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:41841:29"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>36</label> IV. For the Fourth Point. The
<hi>eaſineſs</hi> in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Of the Eternal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Sin, not eaſily changed into a Temporal.</note> by this feat of the
<hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ex opere operato</hi> remitting ſin, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring Grace, to change the
<hi>Eternal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> which is ſurely remitted with the ſin it ſelf, into a <hi>temporal</hi> one; or to change Hell-torments into thoſe of Purgatory; and then the eaſineſs of getting out of theſe too, with a little <hi>money</hi> or
<hi>friends.</hi> See <hi>Rom. Idol.</hi> p. 185, 186. The contrary of this, <hi>viz.</hi> That the procuring the pardon of <hi>Mortal</hi> Sin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted after Baptiſme, and conſequently of the
<hi>eternal</hi> puniſhment thereof (theſe two being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies remitted together) is no ſuch eaſie thing, hath been amply ſhewed in the Vindication of the <hi>Second</hi> and
<hi>Third</hi> Point. The Subjects of the Roman Catholick Church then are in this matter thus inſtructed: 1. That the due <hi>effect</hi> of the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Penance</hi> (repaired unto by ſuch delinquent) is neceſſary to the Remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch ſin, and its Eternal Puniſhment. 2. That this <hi>effect</hi> is not conferred on all that are Confeſſed (as this Author ſeems to take for granted that it is<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> p. 206. 498.</note>) but only, among theſe, on the rightly pre-diſpoſed by <hi>Faith,</hi> and a true and acceptable <hi>Repentance.</hi> Which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance includes not only <hi>ſorrow</hi> for ſin, but an <hi>actual amendment</hi> of life, and <hi>ceaſing</hi> from <hi>ſin</hi> (where life longer continued): and for the ſorrow, — <hi>Sine magnis noſtris fletibus, &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boribus, divinâ id exigente juſtitia, ad hanc no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatem, &amp; integritatem</hi> [viz. remiſſion of ſin, and former ſtate of regeneration] <hi>pervenire ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaquam poſſumus,</hi> (ſaith the Council of
<hi>Trent</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Seſſ. 14. c. 2.</note>). 3. That when all is done, the perſon is not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41841:30"/>certain that he hath attained ſuch a worthy and ſincere Repentance, Contrition, or Attrition, as infallibly receives the effect and benefit of the Sacrament. 4. That, if there ſhould happen any defect therein, the beſt way to <hi>compleat</hi> ſuch
<hi>Contrition</hi> (<hi>ad praeteritorum pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum vindictam &amp; caſtigationem,</hi> ſaith the Council<note n="*" place="margin">Seſſ. 14. c. 8.</note>) is the exerciſe of much
<hi>Penance,</hi> and <hi>Mortification;</hi> and the ſureſt <hi>ſign</hi> of ſuch Contrition <hi>compleated,</hi> is, a change of life, and perſeverance therein; and the ſureſt means, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, for ſuch <hi>perſeverance</hi> (<hi>ad novae vitae cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam, &amp; infirmitatis medicamentum,</hi> ſaith the Council<note n="‖" place="margin">Ibid.</note>) are <hi>Penances</hi> and <hi>Mortifications.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>37</label> 5. As to <hi>Penances</hi> their removing or taking away puniſhments, and ſo juſt <hi>Indulgences</hi> of Penance doing the ſame, They are taught;</p>
            <p>Firſt, That no ſuch Indulgence relates at all to quitting the puniſhment
<hi>Eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That no Penances or Indulgences are beneficial to the removing any <hi>Temporal</hi> puniſhment, ſo long as the perſon, by his ſin unrepented of, is ſtill liable to the
<hi>Eternal:</hi> and, ſuppoſe they were, yet this infinitely grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter debt ſtill uncancelled renders the diſcharge of the other not valuable.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That the remiſſion of the <hi>Eternal</hi> depends chiefly on the
<hi>ſincerity</hi> of their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Converſion to God, and <hi>change</hi> of
<hi>life;</hi> as hath been ſhewed before. And this thing (<hi>viz.</hi> leſt by any defect of theſe, there ſhould be ſome flaw in the pardon of the <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> puniſhment), keeps all pious Sons of this Church perpetually on their guard (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41841:30"/>what-ever <hi>Indulgences</hi> are paſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the
<hi>Temporal</hi>) to make good on their part the <hi>conditions</hi> that are required from them for the cancelling thereof. And if by the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Friends this Author ſpeaks of, as a means of evading theſe puniſhments, be meant <hi>Alms-deeds,</hi> and <hi>other mens Prayers,</hi> it is grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; That, both for the procuring <hi>Grace,</hi> and the <hi>Remiſſion</hi> of
<hi>Sin,</hi> and of theſe <hi>puniſhments</hi> attending it, they help much. And in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect granted again; that the Rich, both as to giving Alms, and by them procuring the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions of ſuch as are relieved, have a great advantage. And very fit they ſhould; having ſo many diſadvantages, and running ſo many hazards from their Wealth other waies. But then the Poor are no way inferiour to them; who, as they want the <hi>one,</hi> ſo are freed from the <hi>other.</hi> And we are told by our Lord, that more Rich incur theſe Eternal or Temporal puniſhments by the <hi>Temptations</hi> of their wealth, than eſcape them by the
<hi>Charitable</hi> diſtribution of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>38</label> From theſe things it appears, that, how <hi>eaſie</hi> ſoever the releaſment of ſuch puniſhment is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>Catholicks,</hi> it is made much more eaſie, or leſs difficult, among <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> For, 1ſt. For <hi>Sin,</hi> and the <hi>Eternal puniſhment;</hi> if Proteſtants require <hi>repentance, ſorrow for ſin,</hi> and an actual <hi>change,</hi> or reformation <hi>of life, Catholicks</hi> (as hath been ſhewed §. 10, &amp;c.) require alſo theſe, and much more; namely, a neceſſary repair to the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Penance, Confeſſion, Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution;</hi> and for the greater ſecuring of their
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41841:31"/>
               <hi>Contrition;</hi> or <hi>Repentance,</hi> of which none can be abſolutely certain, <hi>fletus, labores,</hi> penan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, mortifications, and <hi>dignos fructus paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae;</hi> and theſe not only <hi>ad novae vitae cuſtodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> but <hi>ad praeteritorum peccatorum vindictam.</hi> 2ly.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11.</note> For the <hi>Temporal puniſhment,</hi> 1. <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> hold after the <hi>Eternal</hi> remitted, ſuch a puniſhment to remain ſtill uncancelled; <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> deny it, and throw all puniſhment whatever into the Pardon of the Sin; and as ſoon as the ſentence—<hi>Dominus tranſtulit pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum tuum</hi> is paſt,<note place="margin">2
<hi>Sam.</hi> 12.13.</note> clear all accounts. 2ly. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> hold many faithful Souls, ſuch as have been more imperfect in their repentance, and negligent in Chriſtian-duties here, (as it muſt be granted of thoſe, who all find mercy, ſome are much more than others,) to be detained af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death for ſome time in a ſtate of <hi>Purgation;</hi> Proteſtants ſend all, (that go not to <hi>Hell,</hi> and the greateſt miſery) ſtraight to <hi>Heaven,</hi> and the moſt ſupreme happineſs. 3ly. <hi>Catholicks</hi> make divers <hi>Penances</hi> and
<hi>Satisfactions,</hi> impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or alſo voluntarily aſſumed, neceſſary for the diſcharge of ſuch <hi>temporal</hi> puniſhment, that by judging of themſelves they may prevent that of God:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31.</note> But <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> by denying ſuch <hi>puniſhments,</hi> have alſo no need of ſuch <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> and ſo releaſe them to their Subjects.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly: If, in ſome of her Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is ſaid by them to ſell theſe <hi>Pardons</hi> of Temporal Puniſhments very cheap, the
<hi>Proteſtants</hi> give them to all for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. This of the 4th. Point.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:41841:31"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>39</label> V. Come we to the <hi>Fifth:</hi> The
<hi>Roman</hi> Doctrine concerning <hi>Indulgences;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences beneficial only to thoſe <hi>in the ſtate of Grace.</hi>
               </note> charged by this Author<note n="‖" place="margin">p. 518.</note> with many <hi>groſs Abſurdities,</hi> and as <hi>excuſing Roman-Catholicks from performing the beſt parts of their Religion:</hi> i. e. (ſaith he) <hi>enjoyning Penances, accounted among them fruits of true Repentance; ſevere mortification; Faſting, frequent Prayers, and Almes</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">p.
526.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To the Contrary of this, I ſhall ſhew to his abuſed Reader, That neither the Abſurdities pretended by him, nor the omiſſion of any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Duty follow either from the Roman
<hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Indulgences,</hi> or the commonly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 1ſt. For the Doctrine of this Church; If this <hi>Author</hi> had done her juſtice ſo far as to accuſe or queſtion no more than what he found to be her doctrine in her Councils concerning this point; and, if he had ſaid here for right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Church,</hi> what he hath ſaid elſe-where,<note n="‖" place="margin">p. 209.</note> when for his own advantage:
<hi>That though ſome Teſtimonies of particular perſons may be produced</hi> [for ſeveral opinions] <hi>yet we muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal for the ſenſe of this Church, to the Decrees of its Councils;</hi> how many leaves might he have ſpared from his diſcourſe on this ſubject as wholly impertinent? Indeed ſo compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and cautious have the <hi>Church</hi>'s Decrees been in this matter, as that thoſe <hi>Proteſtants,</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:41841:32"/>who complain at other times of her oppreſſing their Faith with a multitude of <hi>Credends,</hi> here ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe her ſilence &amp; reſervedneſs. So <hi>Doctor Taylor</hi> obſerves in his <hi>Diſſwaſive</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">c. 1 §. 3. p.
39.</note>. <hi>That becauſe the Doctrines were ſo dangerous, uncertain, invidious, by the advice of the Biſhop of</hi> Modena, <hi>the Council of</hi> Trent <hi>left all the Doctrines, &amp; all the Caſes of Conſcience quite alone, and ſlubbered</hi> [or, better, paſſed over] <hi>the whole matter in this Queſtion in general, and recommendatory, terms</hi> —
<hi>That they eſtabliſhed no Doctrine, neither curious nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curious; nor durſt they</hi>
[i. e. the Council, bold enough in other matters] <hi>decree the very Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of this whole matter, the Churches Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> [And ſo all this our Author's Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about this
<hi>Treaſure,</hi> which amount to Ten of the Fifteen Queries he propoſeth, <hi>p.</hi> 518, &amp;c. and ſaith — <hi>That when be once ſeeth thoſe Queſtions ſatisfactorily anſwered, he may then think better of our Doctrine,</hi> are beſide the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and to be cancell'd, if he intends only to encounter the profeſſed Doctrine of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church. But we on the other ſide ſay, That theſe men deal not fairly, who, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending their diſceſſion from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and from the Communion of their Fore-Fathers urge ſuch Doctrines, as none, in ſtaying in this Communion, are obliged to maintain; and that the leſs this Church hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined or required our aſſent to in this point, the more freely may any, holding what ever ſeems to him the moſt probable, ſubmit to her <hi>Decrees:</hi> and hath the leſs cauſe to accuſe, or reproach her.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:41841:32"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>40</label> All then, that the Council hath ſtated and aſſerted in this matter is this<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Con. Trid. Seſſ
25. Deer. de Indulg.</note>, (as <hi>Doctor Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, F. Veron,</hi> and others have obſerved, who have endeavour'd for the fruſtrating ſuch Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes as theſe, to ſever points of
<hi>Faith</hi> from <hi>School</hi>-Opinions)—<hi>Indulgentias conferendi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatem ab ipſomet Chriſto Eccleſiae conceſſam fuiſſe, at que hujuſmodi poteſtate antiquiſſimis etiam temporibus Eccleſiam uſam fuiſſe: Hunc uſum Chriſtiano populo eſſe maxime ſalutarem, &amp; Sacrorum Conciliorum authoritate probatum &amp; in Eccleſiâ retinendum: Foſque Anathemate Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodum damnare, qui aut inutiles eſſe aſſerunt, aut eas concedendi in Eccleſiâ poteſtatem eſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant.</hi> This is all the Council hath determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And upon this, F. <hi>Veron</hi> in his <hi>Rule of Catholiek Faith</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">c. 17.</note> juſtly contends—<hi>That no more ought to be propoſed to ſeparatiſts to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, than what the profeſſion of the Catholick Faith, and the General Councils engage them to. That it is ſufficient to render one a true Child of the Church, if he ſubmit to theſe; and that other Queſtions, wherein the Council is ſilent, are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies and digreſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>41</label> Now, becauſe the <hi>Council</hi> in this her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, we ſee, defends her preſent Doctrine and Practice by that of Ancient times, and by what is approved in former Councils, if we look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Antiquity concerning this matter, we may there eaſily diſcover thus much.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That ſevere and long <hi>Penances</hi> were then impoſed on greater ſinners ſome way propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to their faults; and theſe not only for ſatisfaction of the
<hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>Scandal</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41841:33"/>times given to it in publick ſins, but chiefly for the Satisfaction of
<hi>Gods Juſtice,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing his wrath, for Reconciliation unto Him, Remiſſion of their ſins and Eternal puniſhment due thereto, and for begetting in them a true and ſolid Repentance, and Contrition for their Sin, and ſo for ſaving their Souls. For which I refer the Reader to what hath been ſaid before, §. 16. and the many teſtimonies of the Fathers collected by <hi>Morinus De Paenitent,</hi> l. 3. c. 11, &amp; 12,—and <hi>l.</hi> 10.
<hi>c.</hi> 24. To which effects theſe <hi>Penances</hi> were eſteemed very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous; and though not, as to all of them, any proper Satisfactions, yet a means very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial for perfecting the Sinner's Repentance, and Sorrow for ſin, and procuring the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to them of the Merits and Satisfactions of Chriſt: Gods <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſtill accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying one another, as in reſpect of Chriſts ſufferings, and ſatisfactions, paid for our ſins by Him; ſo in reſpect of ſome temporal ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of our own, either freely offered and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by our ſelves, or, if not Prevented by theſe, inflicted on us by God to ſuch a degree as ſeemeth meet to his Divine Majeſty.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>42</label> 2. We may find; That there were, then, ſomtimes
<hi>Indulgences</hi> granted of ſuch <hi>Penances,</hi> all, or part, to ſome Perſons, thought rightly qualified for them, upon certain juſt cauſes of a greater advancement of piety, and Gods Glory and Service thereby; either in reſpect of ſuch Perſons private, or ſome other pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and greater, good. Which <hi>cauſe</hi> was thought a ſufficient motive for ſuch a relaxati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41841:33"/>and prevalent with God for ratifying ſuch indulgent act of the Church-Governors (to whom our Lord hath committed in his ſtead the power of binding and looſing Sinners); whereby the ſame puniſhment of ſin, due to the <hi>Divine Juſtice,</hi> is preſumed to be remitted by God to perſons, if being, as they appear, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently contrite, upon ſuch <hi>Indulgence</hi> granted, as would have been upon the <hi>Penances</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: for, elſe, if ſuch puniſhment in <hi>Gods</hi> Court (and not only that of the
<hi>Church</hi>) had not been taken away by them, the <hi>Indulgence,</hi> conceded as a favour, would have been really much to the Penitents loſs; whilſt, after it, thoſe heavier puniſhments remaine to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on, and undergone by, them, from which their much eaſier Penances (if not indulged) would have diſcharged them: And ſo this <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer</hi> of the
<hi>Keys</hi> would have been rather to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> than <hi>Edification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>43</label> To come to ſome Inſtances. Such was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Indulgence, or Remiſſion (<hi>in the perſon of Chriſt</hi> as he ſaith,<note n="‖" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10.</note> or by the Commiſſion of <hi>Quorum remiſeritis</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jo.</hi> 20.23.</note>) of part of the Penance that was formerly impoſed by him upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous <hi>Corinthian,</hi> as for the ſcandal given to the Heathen, and the Church, ſo alſo chiefly for the <hi>ſaving of his Soul,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.5. Yet ſuch remiſſion of them was not without ſeveral juſt <hi>Motives,</hi> inciting the Apoſtle thereto, and which he judged more acceptable to God; &amp; ſo, more effectual for procuring the application of Chriſts Merits for this Sinners pardon, than the remainder of his Penance, had it been fulfilled;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41841:34"/>Such as were the gratifying the Interceſſions for this perſon of the
<hi>Saints</hi> in <hi>Corinth;</hi> and preventing their apprehenſions of the Apoſtles too great <hi>ſeverity;</hi> the <hi>exceſſive</hi> ſorrow and confuſion appearing already in the Penitent; and leaſt perhaps through a deſpondency of mind he ſhould throw off the
<hi>Chriſtian</hi> Faith, and abandon himſelf to vice; in all which the Apoſtle ſaw
<hi>Satans wiles,</hi> See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6, 7, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>44</label> Such, again, were the <hi>Indulgences</hi> uſed in the Primitive times upon ſeveral (judged by them) <hi>juſt cauſes</hi> moving the Church-Governors thereto, either for the <hi>private</hi> good of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, or
<hi>publick</hi> of Religion. 1ſt. Such an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently were, in reſpect of the <hi>private good</hi> of the Penitent. 1. An extraordinary diligence and fervour in their performing Penance, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing in them a great reformation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo this ſeeming ſufficient for quitting the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of their debt; in the Indulgment of whom was alſo a publick good intended, that ſo the negligent might, hereby, be excited to like fervor, upon hopes of like favour. 2. The puſillanimity, or weakneſs, or temptations of the Penitent, whereby it was feared, that he might through deſpair ſink under the burden laid upon him, or throw it off his ſhoulders, revolt to Hereſie, or Gentiliſme. 3. In times of great perſecution, the better fitting and arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Penitent for <hi>Martyrdome,</hi> by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving a reconcilement to God and the Church; and, after it, the <hi>Holy Communion;</hi> and the ſame alſo was done in his being expoſed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41841:34"/>to any other eminent danger of death, by ſickneſs or otherwiſe; in which neceſſity, <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution,</hi> and the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> were adminiſtred, though the
<hi>Penance</hi> unfiniſhed: (As ſtill the inability of any further doing Penance, to ſuch perſons as are ſuppoſed contrite, and otherwiſe well diſpoſed at the hour of death, is thought a ſufficient ground of an <hi>Indulgence.</hi>) 4. Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo ſome
<hi>Heroical</hi> Act of the Penitent was accepted inſtead of further Penance: As perſons returned from <hi>Hereſie</hi> were uſually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Church upon eaſie terms, and without exacting from them the Penances due to ſo great a ſin, both for other reaſons tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to advancement of <hi>true Religion,</hi> and for the great Confuſion ſuch perſons expoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to in the publick confeſſing and renounc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their former Opinions; and profeſſing of that Faith, they had before cenſured and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; <hi>Errors</hi> that prejudice our <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> being with much more difficulty ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by us, than thoſe <hi>Sins</hi> that are only the exorbitancies of our <hi>Paſſions.</hi> So ſomtimes the <hi>Lapſed,</hi> after their having denied Chriſt, in their returning boldly to confeſs and ſuffer for him, were for this indulged all the Penance impoſed for their former lapſe.<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus, l. 9 c. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Again, Such Cauſes or Motives in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>publick good,</hi> anciently was the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring of <hi>Martyrs</hi> (i. e. ſuch who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſuffered loſs of goods, limbs, tortures, for the Chriſtian profeſſion, or were impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and deſtined to ſuch tortures) in conceding Indulgencies of their Penance to ſuch perſons,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41841:35"/>for whom theſe petitioned, or gave their <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatory Letters,</hi> or Tickets; and for whom theſe Martyrs promiſed their Interceſſions with God; and this done by the Church, to ſhew the power and value which ſhe believed ſuch ſufferings and interceſſions to have with God; and hereby alſo to encourage many others to
<hi>Martyrdom.</hi> Such alſo was the preventing of the growth of <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> and the enlarging of the Catholick Faith in the receiving of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks uſually into the Church with much indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and not clogging them with ſuch great Penances as ſuch a Crime deſerved<note n="‖" place="margin">Ibid. l. 9. c. 8.</note> to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage more to come in, and prevent their fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther infecting of others.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>45</label> Now, a ſtrict correſpondence to ſuch <hi>anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> cuſtoms have the <hi>latter</hi> times of the Church obſerved (in their continuing of
<hi>Indulgences</hi>) in theſe two principal points; 1. that ſuch <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> be to a perſon <hi>rightly diſpoſed</hi> by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſo far as the Church can judg of it; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe without this, as no remiſſion of Sin, ſo no reaſon to expect ſuch divine relaxation of puniſhment to a yet impenitent Sinner. And 2. next, That there be a <hi>juſt</hi> and weighty <hi>Cauſe</hi> for granting it; elſe it would quite ruine the <hi>Churches</hi> Diſcipline, and abuſe the power ſhe is intruſted with, to remit the Penance, and expect that God ſhould withdraw ſuch puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and change that ordinary courſe of his juſtice, by which he makes men ſenſible of his hate to Sin, upon any light and frivolous Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, which may daily occurr. <hi>That there be a cauſe,</hi> I ſay not, exactly the ſame alwaies
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41841:35"/>with thoſe ancient, forementioned, (a thing not neceſſary; for the Ancient alſo, we ſee, were various); but <hi>juſt</hi> ſtill, and judged pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the quality of the Indulgence, as theirs was. In latter times then, (after a much remiſſer impoſing of Penances for great crimes, than was anciently, becauſe of the hardneſs of mens hearts; and a reluctance to receive, or bear them; When once <hi>Commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of Penances were become more in uſe, and Abſolution frequently, in great offences alſo, was joyned immediatly with Confeſſion, and the Penance deferred till afterward,) In theſe latter times, I ſay, ſuch Cauſes have been a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Penitent, inſtead of ſuch Penances de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined by him, (which though now not enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet now are as much, as anciently, due from him as to the ſatisfying of the Divine juſtice), upon ſome other acts of piety or devotion, more willingly performable by him; and theſe eſpecially ſuch, as, by their tending to ſome publick and eminent good, may be more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, and proportionable to the relaxation of ſuch Penances. Such as are the enjoyning of <hi>Almes, Prayers, Faſts,</hi> &amp;c. for averting ſome imminent Judgment, or danger from the Church; for the conquering of Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, and the Churches Enemies (ſuch was the recovery of the Holy Land); for converting of Hereticks, for relief of the Poor, in ſome time of great diſtreſs; for the building of Churches, Hoſpitals, or other pious Benefactions, where much neceſſity of them: And, among the reſt, this motive, not the leaſt conſiderable, (men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41841:36"/>alſo by <hi>Bellarmin De Indulgent,</hi> l. 2. c. 18.) namely an excitement of the people to Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Confeſſion, to Prayers, and doing Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances now, (when they reject theſe any way proportionable to their faults, and as ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Divine Juſtice) at leaſt for the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Indulgences</hi> (which are by them ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed a much eaſier relief): the procurement of which Indulgences hath been much uſed by many wiſe and Holy Prelates; as namely, by St. <hi>Carlo Borromeo,</hi> to this purpoſe; and <hi>Ipſo uſu conſtat</hi> (ſaith <hi>Suarez</hi>) <hi>gratiam &amp; favorem Indulgentiarum multum conferre ad Spiritualem profectum fidelium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſp. 49. §. 1.</note>
               <hi>ut melius ac frequentius a peccatorum vinculis liberentur;</hi> That men, that are not already in the ſtate of Grace, may, by their preparation for the benefit of the <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> be brought thereto; and ſo, after a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Eternal puniſhment by their Contrition, and the power of the Keys, be alſo, by this favour upon ſome pious work, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of the temporal, or at leaſt of ſome part thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>46</label> In theſe two things therefore, 1 a <hi>worthy</hi> perſon to be indulged 2 and a <hi>juſt</hi> cauſe of ſuch indulgement, the <hi>preſent</hi> uſe of Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces runs parallel with the <hi>ancient.</hi> And then the preſent difference (which is confeſſed) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the latter and former times, 1. One, that the former were Indulgences of Penances <hi>enjoyned;</hi> the preſent of the <hi>ſelf-ſame Penances in the ſame meaſure due</hi> to Gods juſtice (and to be paid now, as much as then, for obtaining from him a relaxation from ſuch puniſhment;)
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:41841:36"/>but, for the Penitents indiſpoſition, after a long deſuetude of ſuch a practice, not enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed now, as formerly. 2. The other, that thoſe were uſually granted to
<hi>ſome</hi> particular perſons, appearing penitent; theſe indefinitely to <hi>all,</hi> but upon the ſame condition, that they be penitent (which alſo they muſt teſtifie, by their repairing to the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Penance,</hi>) otherwiſe, they are taught, that they receive no benefit thereby. Now a difference in theſe, I ſay, ſeems to alter nothing in the ſubſtance of Indulgences; and, the one way to be as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the conſtitution of the preſent times, as the other was of the ancient.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>47</label> The Church's Doctrine about Indulgences thus delivered; As for many other Queſtions, touching the manner how theſe Indulgences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit the receiver, whether by the way of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution</hi> or <hi>Solution;</hi> whether with or without a Counter-ſatisfaction paid to Gods Juſtice: and this when, or how, or by whom, paid, &amp; the like, the preſent Church is no more concerned to ſtate them, than the ancient; and what ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities therein may be thought to preſs or prejudice the one, will as much the other. In this Author's inquiring, then, from what So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, or Satisfactions, or Church-treaſures, theſe Indulgences become admitted and ratified by the Divine Juſtice, much pains and his many Queries might have been ſpared: the Church herein hath determined nothing; and he, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Catholicks, hath the liberty to take that opinion that likes him beſt. <hi>Doctor Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> in his <hi>Reſolution</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">l. 2. c. 6.</note> written for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41841:37"/>ſuch Proteſtant Queſtioners hath told him in this matter—<hi>Catera etiam dubia ſunt, &amp; a Theologis in utramque partem agitata, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirum, An ſit the ſaurus aliquis meritorum &amp; ſatisfactionum in Eccleſiâ, cujus diſpenſatores ſint Romanus Pontifex, &amp; reliqui Eccleſiae Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores? And paena, quae ex naturâ rei &amp; coram Deo ſolvenda ſit pro peccato, ſive publico, ſive ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creto, poſſit, ab-alio quocunque adimpleri per mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolutionis &amp; ſatisfactionis debitae, quam ab ipſomet peccatore?</hi> And F. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eron</hi> in his Rule of Faith<note n="*" place="margin">c.
17.</note>—<hi>Since</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>neither our profeſſion of Faith, nor the Council of</hi> Trent <hi>take any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of this matter, why ſhould we preſs ſuch opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, or propoſe more to them</hi> [Separatiſts] <hi>than theſe engage it to?</hi> Here then, if this our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary will grant, that there can be no remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſin, or of any puniſhment thereof, eternal or temporal, for ſatisfying in rigour the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice, but by the application of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabundant, and infinite merits and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, (a thing which I ſuppoſe no Proteſtant will deny) no more is deſired of him, or any. For the other Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the <hi>ſatisfactions</hi> of the <hi>Saints;</hi> though it is certain, here. 1 That God may, if he pleaſeth, accept the ſatisfactions of one perſon for the debt of another (for ſo he did in our Lord's); and 2 again, that, for what is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect in the Saints ſatisfactions, he may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat it with his Sons; yet I know no Roman Divines that do hold any ſuch ſatisfactions of Saints in this matter <hi>abſolutely neceſſary,</hi> but that our Lords alone are <hi>all-ſufficient;</hi> and, if the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41841:37"/>Saints great ſufferings for their Fellow-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers (not to be denied) are alſo thrown into this <hi>Treaſure;</hi> this is more to honour them, than that it needs any recruit by them. <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurus Eccleſiae</hi> (ſaith <hi>Suarez</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg. diſp. 51. §. 3.</note>) <hi>non eſt ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter neceſſarius ut Indulgentiae concedantur, ſumn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que habeant effectum.</hi> And, <hi>Sicut Chriſtus eſt unicus Redemptor, ita etiam eſt per ſe ſufficiens ſine adminiculo aliorum ſanctorum.</hi> And—<hi>Non eſt opus ut adjungantur ſatisfactiones ex paſſioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Sanctorum paſſionbus Chriſti, quaſi hae per ſe non ſufficiant. Sed hoc tum glorioſum Chriſto, a quo eſt omne bonum Sanctorum, tum ipſis etiam ſanctis perhonorificum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bellarmin</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg. l. 1. c. 4.</note>.</p>
            <p>This ſaid of the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> proceed we to conſider the preſent <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>Indulgences,</hi> and the great dammage done to Piety &amp; Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereby, which this Author ſo earneſtly chargeth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>48</label> And here 1ſt. The Subjects of the Roman Church are generally inſtructed, that no Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence can benefit them, as to any remiſſion of the guilt of Sin, as it is an injury and offence done to God; or of the <hi>Eternal</hi> puniſhment thereof; or, to the making their peace with <hi>God,</hi> with which theſe eternal pains are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent; but only as to the <hi>temporal,</hi> that is ſtill retained by God after our reconciliation and peace made with him, for the ſatisfaction of his Juſtice in ſome part, which thinks it not fit to let our former wickedneſs paſs altogether free from ſome temporal
<hi>puniſhment,</hi> (which if this Author pleaſe he may call <hi>Chaſtiſement</hi>) to ſhew his hatred of ſin, even when he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41841:38"/>into favour the Sinner. For, as the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Seſſ. 14. c. 8.</note>— <hi>Divinam clementiam decet, ne ita nobis abſque ullâ ſatisfactione pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta dimittantur, ut occaſione arreptâ, peccata le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viora putantes, velut injurij &amp; contumelioſi Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritui Sancto in graviora labamur.</hi> [Of which ordinary courſe of Gods Juſtice, even toward thoſe already re-admitted into grace and friendſhip, he who doubts, may at his leiſure conſider well theſe paſſages of Scripture— <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.12.—27.12, 13, 14.—<hi>Numb.</hi> 14.34.—2
<hi>Sam.</hi> 12.10, 13, 14.—2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.10, 13.—2 <hi>King.</hi> 20.6, 18. compared with 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.31. — 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.37. — 35.22, 23.—1
<hi>King.</hi> 13.22. — <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.34. (where the puniſhment, threatned verſe 10. being remitted, yet others leſs than that are reſerved, whenſoever their new ſins ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord alſo to remember <hi>the laſt.</hi>). <hi>Joſh.</hi>
22.17.—<hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.31. &amp;c.— <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.31. —1 <hi>Pet.</hi>
4.18.—<hi>Ecclus.</hi> 5.4.—<hi>Pſal.</hi> 98.8. —1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31,
32.—1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15. (which text ſhews a temporary ſuffering to remain alſo in the next world for faults not fully expiated and accounted-for here by our judging our ſelves, that we may eſcape the judgment of God. Of which faults, either in their nature, or by our Repentance, and the Sacrament of Penance rendred, <hi>not mortal</hi> to us, thus <hi>Caeſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Arelatenſis</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Hom. 8.</note>—<hi>Quicquid de iſtis peccatis redemptum non fuerit illo igne purgandam eſt, de quo Apoſtolus,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>Redemptum non fuerit,</hi> i.e. as he ſaith before by our Penances—<hi>Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is Orationibus &amp; frequentibus jejuniis &amp; largi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oribus
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41841:38"/>cleemoſynis,</hi> &amp;c. Nor is this poſtume puniſhment, ſince it is revealed and made known to us here, purely vindicative for ſin; but, as other Temporal puniſhments here, deſign'd to excite us to a cleanſing and correcting betimes, whatever is ill built by us for ſear of it; and, by our lighter penances here, to a preventing it; And if the preaching of Hell-torments to come may profit us, ſo may thoſe of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry): Again,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 12.32.<note n="‖" place="margin">De Civ. Dei. l. 21. c. 24.</note> From which Text St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> collected—<hi>Sunt quibus, etſi non in iſto, tamen remittetur</hi> [i. e. not for the eternal, remitted alwaies here or not at all, but a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral pain or puniſhment] <hi>in futuro.</hi> Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples alſo of ſuch temporal puniſhments, averti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible or removable by ſome penal works of our own; and our greater ſuffering from God, changed into thoſe leſſer from our ſelves, See in <hi>Jona</hi> 3.10. compared with 7, and
8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.29.—2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.6, 7.— 33.12,
13. — 2 <hi>King.</hi> 7.1. compared with 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.30.—1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31,
32. I have quoted here the more Texts, to ſhew that Gods <hi>Mercy</hi> ordinarily includes alſo ſome perſonal ſatisfaction, in ſome part at leaſt, to his <hi>Juſtice, Juſtitia &amp; pax oſculatae ſunt</hi>—<hi>Miſeri cordiam &amp; judicium cantabo tibi Domine:</hi> that he may be both loved and feared.]</p>
            <p>They are taught therefore, that a true <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition</hi> in the ſubject (the requiſites of which ſee before §. 10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) is ſtill preſuppoſed to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of any <hi>Indulgence;</hi> and that he who hopes any gain thereby, muſt alſo, if in Mortal ſin, by the Sacrament of Penance, render himſelf firſt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41841:39"/>in the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Grace: Contritis &amp; Confeſſis</hi> being the <hi>Condition</hi> on the part of the <hi>indulged,</hi> expreſſed, or implyed in all Indulgences.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>49</label> As for the ordinary expreſſion in theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, promiſing a <hi>remiſſion</hi> of their <hi>ſins,</hi> the firſt of this Authors hard Queſtions, (who asks, how it conſiſts with this Doctrine of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences their reſpecting not the fault, but the temporal puniſhment thereof) it is anſwered long ſince by
<hi>Bellarmin</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg. l. 1. c. 7.</note> (and it were well, if this Author with his old objections would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to his Proteſtant Readers the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks old Anſwers; and to the Catholick Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders his own Reply to them) — <hi>Id propterea dici, quod indulgentia conjungitur ordinarie cum confeſſione Sacramentali; &amp; facit, ut qui per Sacramentum Paenitentiae,</hi> [which is received as a preparation for the Indulgence] <hi>fuit abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus a culpâ, per Indulgentiam abſolvatur a paenâ</hi> and, that the Indulgences ſpeak of the remiſſion of ſins, <hi>quoad paenam:</hi> or as Suarez<note n="*" place="margin">De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg. Diſp. 50. §. 1.</note> — <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvit a culpâ &amp; paenâ non quia Indulgentiae utramque tollat: ſed quia, ut habeat effectum, debet ſupponere remiſſam culpam, &amp; ipſa complet totius paenae remiſſionem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>50</label> Things ſtanding thus, to what end hath this Author ſought out, and cited ſome teſtimonies of Roman Writers? One ſaying<note n="‖" place="margin">p. 525.</note> — <hi>That af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Indulgences were grown common, many men did abſtain leſs from evil actions.</hi> A ſecond, <hi>That they were only profitable to the Idle and Wicked.</hi> A third, <hi>That true Chriſtian piety was deſtroyed by them, and that all manner of wickedneſs did ſpring from thence; and that men
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41841:39"/>were affraid of committing no kind of ſin, when at ſo cheap a rate they could purchaſe a remiſſion of them.</hi> A fourth, <hi>That let men do what wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they will, by them they ſhall be free from puniſhment,</hi> &amp;c. beſides all his own invective ſtuff from <hi>pag.</hi> 415. to <hi>p.</hi> 499. or §. 3. to §. 8. (where he would perſwade his Reader, that the Roman Indulgences countenance the <hi>impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi> to a
<hi>continuance</hi> in their <hi>ſins,</hi> or promiſe to them any the leaſt relief as to their <hi>pardon</hi>), I ſay, what mean all theſe impertinences? when as Indulgences belong to none but juſt perſons; and none, but the already penitent and reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as Catholicks are generally taught) are at all concerned in, or ſuccoured by, them. And it muſt be by a moſt
<hi>Groſs</hi> and <hi>highly-Culpable</hi> ignorance, if any heretofore have ſo far miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Churches conſtant Doctrine of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, as to imagine the leaſt good from them, as to their Salvation, if they either ſtill <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> in any Mortal ſin, or afterward <hi>returned</hi> to it; and, if the pardon of ſuch ſin were not firſt procured from God by a ſincere repentance. <hi>There is</hi> (ſaith this Author,<note n="‖" place="margin">p. 497.</note> after his learned Collection of old Indulgences) <hi>one odd conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on implied in ſome of theſe Prayers</hi> (he ought to have ſaid, in <hi>all</hi>)
<hi>called being in the ſtate of Grace, the want of which may hinder the effect from them; but a due Confeſſion with Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will at any time put a man into it.</hi> But, by his leave, there is another <hi>odd Condition</hi> beſides, which Catholicks call <hi>Contrition,</hi> or
<hi>Repentance;</hi> and what Catholicks mean by it, may be ſeen before, §. 10. and 23, which this Author (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41841:40"/>to his wonted candor) hath left out, and without which his <hi>due Confeſſion and Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> ſignifie nothing; and if they have this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed alſo to put them in the ſtate of Grace, much good may they have of their Indulgence; for alſo Proteſtants, and this Author hold this Contrition or Repentance of ſuch a ſtrange ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that they admit all into the ſtate of Grace, though unabſolved, or unconfeſſed by it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>51</label> What means then ſuch a Tragical clamour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Roman Indulgences, as nouriſhing and licenſing mens ſins, and as ſold dear, and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily bought
[<hi>i. e.</hi> with almes, and other pious works,] on this account; and at laſt deceiving the purchaſer; whereas, ſuppoſe them all ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to fail, and to be meer frauds, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to fail to any ſuch unpenitent Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; they fail only to thoſe, that (however this
<hi>bargain,</hi> as they call it, proves) are already in Gods Grace and favour, and the ſtate of Salvation, and to whom perhaps the very grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch Indulgence (by reaſon of their diligent preparation for it) was the occaſion of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into ſuch a ſtate; and Indulgences fail to theſe for nothing more, but what the ſame Indulgences pretend to give, <hi>viz.</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſome temporal puniſhment, upon which failing follow; ſome
<hi>dilation,</hi> perhaps, of the poſſeſſion of their future bliſs, whilſt their Contrition, Confeſſion, and the pious Work they do for ſuch an Indulgence, are forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming forth their <hi>reward.</hi> But Proteſtants, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying any ſuch temporal puniſhment to remain,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:41841:40"/>after remiſſion of the ſin, conſequently muſt affirm, that Catholicks gain much by what they <hi>do;</hi> and loſe nothing at all by what they are
<hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed,</hi> though the Indulgence utterly fail them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>52</label> 2ly. As Catholicks are taught, that a <hi>right diſpoſition</hi> is neceſſary in the <hi>Penitent,</hi> ſo, that for the
<hi>Indulgence,</hi> is alſo neceſſary a <hi>juſt cauſe,</hi> or motive of granting it, and ſome way <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable</hi> to the quality of the penance that is relaxed by it; <hi>i. e.</hi> a cauſe prudently eſtimated more acceptable to God, and ſooner procuring the application of our Lords ſatisfactions for the remitting of ſuch puniſhment of ſin, than ſuch penances would be. Nothing is more obvious than this in Catholick Authors; and upon this ground, the ſaying of one <hi>Pater No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> or giving the Almes of a penny, or the like, is not thought by them a ſufficient cauſe (where is no other motive thereof) for the Church-Governours thereupon to concede a <hi>plenary Indulgence.</hi> Neither is it here pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that all paſt Indulgences of Popes, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that may be produced, have always therefore neceſſarily had, or included ſuch a cauſe; neither are Popes maintained infallible in their judgment herein—<hi>Quia per indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas atque ſuper fluas</hi>
[and, <hi>cur indiſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etae, &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtuae,</hi> (ſaith Bellarmin<note n="*" place="margin">De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dul. l 1. c. 12.</note>)
<hi>niſi quia ot oſae, manes &amp; irritae ſunt?</hi>] <hi>quas quidam Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claeſiarum Praelati facere non verentur, &amp; claves Eccleſiae contemnuntur, &amp; paenitentialis ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factio enervatur, decerninus,</hi> &amp;c. Thus <hi>Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> 3. long ago in the great <hi>Lateran</hi> Council<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 62.</note> And
<hi>Sixtus</hi> 4. having been ſomwhat Prodigal
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41841:41"/>in this kind, recalled many Indulgences for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly conceded by him. See
<hi>Extravag. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun.</hi> l. 5. <hi>tit.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 5. And ſo <hi>Clement</hi> 8.
<hi>effuſas nimis Indulgentiarum conceſſiones reſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere aggreſſus eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Baronius</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">A D. 147.</note>. And of the poſſibility of the failing of the Pope himſelf ſomtimes in this ſufficiency of the cauſe, thus ſpeaks a Jeſuite<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sua ez.</hi> De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg. Diſp. 56. §. 3.</note> — <hi>Quamvis Pontifex ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe declararet ſe moveri propter talem cauſam, quam reputat ſufficientem ad tantam indulgenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am concedendam, non eſſet infallibile vel cauſam eſſe talem, vel (quod conſequens eſt) totam indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiam eſſe validam. Quia talis declaratio Pontiſicis non eſt de doctrinâ ad ſidem pertinente, ſed de quodam facto particulari, quod ad pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ſpectat; in quo Pontiſex non habet infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem aſſiſtentiam Spiritus Sancti, ſed in his tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quae ad doctrinam ſidei, &amp; morum ſpectant.</hi> And again, <hi>Quamvis Pontifex exiſtimet aut de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claret talem cauſam ſubeſſe, nihilominus decipi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, quia quoad hoc, prudentiâ, &amp; exiſtimatione humanâ gubernatur, poſſetque etiam humano af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu moveri.</hi> Thus <hi>Suarez</hi> comparing the Popes diſpenſing in Penances with that in vows. And thus <hi>Eſtius</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">In. 4. Sent. Diſt. 20. §. 9.</note>—<hi>Si nullâ rationabili cauſâ movente, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntifex vel Epiſcopus Indulgentiam concederet, exiſtimandum non eſt, eam alicujus efficaciae, ſeu, valo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is fore.</hi> What a many Jeſts and Sarcaſmes now hath this unſerious Writer loſt here in playing upon the Pope's infallibility in this matter (the chief common-place of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants when ſeeking quarrels,) perhaps con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſeem
<hi>ignorant</hi> herein, that he may ſhew <hi>wit?</hi> Though mean while, the Chriſtian Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41841:41"/>and Obedience in the Subjects of this Church is far from diſtruſting the prudence, or fidelity, eſpecially of this their chief Paſtor, aſſiſted with ſo wiſe a Council in his diſpenſing theſe favours; and far from weighing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſing, whether the cauſe of ſuch promulgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be ſufficient, or no; Which as it is a thing of difficult reſolution (where many circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are to be conſidered, that are not ſo well known to Subjects, and ſuch cauſe not expreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or not totally, in the Indulgence; for the pious work may be diverſe from the cauſe, or motive of the promulgation of ſuch a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez De Indulg. Diſp. 56. §. 3</note>) as, I ſay, it ſeems to be a matter of <hi>difficult</hi> reſolution, ſo the aſſurance thereof (as I ſhall ſhew by and by) is of <hi>little</hi> conſequence.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>53</label> As for Indulgences their <hi>Valent quantum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> the <hi>ſonant</hi> is to be underſtood not of that ſenſe which an illiterate perſon, not well inſtructed, may poſſibly take them in, but with thoſe commonly-known limitations, or ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions belonging to them, and particularly thoſe now mentioned. <hi>Valent quantum ſonaent.</hi> 1 To perſons rightly prepared; and, 2 if paſſed upon a juſt and ſufficient cauſe, which are, or ought, to be, common <hi>praecognita,</hi> to all that make uſe of them: Scarce any promiſe paſſed amongſt men, but includes ſome condition, which being well known, is thought not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be expreſſed. And when we find Remiſſion in the Scriptures promiſed, in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places, to <hi>Faith,</hi> to <hi>Almes,</hi> to the
<hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to the <hi>love of God,</hi> to our <hi>For giving our Neighbours ſins againſt us,</hi> &amp;c. I hope, we
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41841:42"/>may rightly ſay, theſe Texts <hi>valent quantum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> and that the Holy Ghoſt in them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends no fraud; and yet ſome other Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be underſtood, which are commonly known and learnt from other Scriptures, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which none of theſe Texts rigidly and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken, are true, and valid. If then ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Indulgences, upon the defect of ſome condition requiſite to their validity, ſhould fail at leaſt in part of what they promiſe, yet as raſhly, and untruly, as uncivilly, doth our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor therefore pronounce the Promulgator a <hi>Cheat:</hi> Becauſe one may poſſibly be miſtaken without a deſign to deceive; and this Author himſelf, when in a calmer temper, may diſcover a <hi>Medium</hi> between ſpeaking a truth, and cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Otherwiſe it will follow, that himſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, in all he ſaith, is either infallible, or a Cheat.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>45</label> 3ly. They are taught, that, though perhaps there ſhould be ſome invalidity in an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, by reaſon of ſome defect in the cauſe, as to the full effect thereof, yet is not the Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence therefore <hi>totally</hi> invalid; any pious cauſe whatever ſerving for a partial effect; and ſo, that it would prove an overſight in any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to loſe this benefit. And if the releaſment of ſome temporal puniſhment, by the omitting our penances, and the Indulgences failing of its full effect, be not had; yet
1ſt. Some other pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous work, enjoyned by the Indulgence, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, which hath its reward:
2ly. Whilſt ſome part of ſuch temporal puniſhment, that remains ſo uncompounded for, may retard for
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:41841:42"/>ſome time ones future bliſs; yet his preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to render himſelf in the ſtate of Grace, and ſo capable of the benefit of the Indulgence (how dimuinitive ſoever this be) may be of much more conſequence to him, than is ſuch puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment uncancelled; whilſt it ſecures the main buſineſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> his <hi>Salvation:</hi> and this way, he gains much more by the Indulgence, than he loſeth, another. 3ly. It is alſo very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that the <hi>Penances</hi> now a-days remitted by Indulgences are ſuch, as are due indeed to Gods Juſtice, and theſe as great as ever, yet moſt of them are not now impoſed as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they have been; and ſo we ſhould have as much omitted ſuch a quantity of theſe Penances as is not enjoyned (which is the moſt) without, as with, our receiving an
<hi>Indulgence</hi> for them. And ſo indeed it is but a ſmall penance, that the moſt do forbear by gaining an Indulgence; and as much temporal puniſhment we may think would remain unſatisfied for, <hi>without</hi> ſuch Indulgence granted to us, as now we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come anſwerable for, by any <hi>defect</hi> in it; and ſo, if we have no gain by it, neither is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great loſs; I mean, from our <hi>neglects</hi> in doing <hi>penance</hi> upon the <hi>ſecurity</hi> of the <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</hi> But 4ly. No loſs there is but a ſure gain by it, if we take care both to <hi>perform</hi> all our penances enjoyned, (in theſe latter times, not ſo burdenſome, nor bearing any porporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thoſe preſcribed by ancient Canons), and alſo to
<hi>gain</hi> the Indulgence by doing the pious works it enjoyns, for that, wherein our penan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces performed may fall ſhort of the ſatisfaction due.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:41841:43"/>If any then ſhall urge here, that it is difficult to know the true validity of an Indulgence, or the ſufficiency of its cauſe, I anſwer; As it is <hi>difficult,</hi> ſo (I have ſhewed here) not much <hi>neceſſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>55</label> And laſtly, ſince Indulgences are a priviledg or favour, that none are compelled to make uſe of, thoſe, who either ſcruple their <hi>validity,</hi> or fear a <hi>relaxation</hi> of neceſſary Chriſtian Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline by them, may let them alone, do their <hi>Penance,</hi> and all is well. And thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, who ſo much diſlike them, are wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to ſtay in the Communion of the Church, and have none of them. Neither had
<hi>Luther</hi> any juſt cauſe to run out of the Church, for fear Indulgences ſhould have gotten ſome of his money.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>56</label> 4ly. Though, upon the conceſſion of a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Indulgence none are ſtrictly <hi>obliged</hi> to the performance of any penances, either thoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned them, or others due for the ſatisfaction of any part of the Temporal puniſhment of their ſin: Yet 1ſt. As theſe penal deeds, ſuch as Almes, Watching, Faſting, and Prayers are numbred among other good works, that are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways very acceptable to, and highly rewarda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with God, and may poſſeſs them of an high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Degree of Glory, ſo all are adviſed to a frequentation of them ſtill on this account; which <hi>augmentation</hi> of <hi>glory,</hi> and our future re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by theſe penal, as they are alſo good works, is much more to be eſteemed (as <hi>Card. Lugo</hi> obſerves<note n="‖" place="margin">De Sac. Paeuit. Diſp. 27. §. 2.</note>) than the <hi>Redemption</hi> of our <hi>Temporal</hi> pain by the benefit of Indulgences.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41841:43"/>2. And again, as they are any way profitable and requiſite to thoſe two ends of Penances of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten forementioned<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> §. 15 17.</note> as
1 the begetting of a true and ſolid Contrition for ſins paſt, without which had the very foundation of Indulgences fails; or 2 the cure of former vicious habits, the moderating of our paſſions, and prevention of ſin for the time to come; a relapſe into which in effect as to ſalvation ruines again what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences have formerly procured; and much better were it for the Penitent to forgoe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence; than ſuch Penance, the omiſſion whereof ſhould betray him to be re-enſlaved to ſin; Here alſo, I ſay, he is ſtill adviſed, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as he hath more reaſon to ſuſpect his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eſtate, to a continuance of ſuch Penances, notwithſtanding what-ever favour done him by Indulgences [of which matter thus <hi>P. Laeymann</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Lib. 5. tract. 7. c. 3.</note> out of <hi>Albertus Magnus</hi> — <hi>Conſultiſſimum eſſe, ut ſemper tota paenitentia</hi> [namely, that is enjoyned us] <hi>impleatur, quia plerumque minor, quam peccatis debeatur, injuncta eſt per modum medicinae reſervantis a recidivâ; &amp; ſaepe incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, an Indulgentiam lucrati ſimue</hi> [touched be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore]; <hi>vel ſaltem, an it a plene, ut ab omni pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ immunes exiſtamus.</hi> And — <hi>Paenitentiae, quoe pro peccat is injungi ſolent, exignae ſunt, &amp; ſaepe tantum loco Medicina ſeu curationis peccatorum imperatae, quas omnimodo implere expedit.</hi> Thus alſo <hi>Bellarmin</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg l. 2. c. 13.</note> in anſwer to <hi>Chemnitius,</hi> urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing — <hi>Non bebere relaxari per Indulgentias ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crcitia virtutum, fructus paenitentiae, et novae vitae, &amp; carnis mortificationem, alioqui noxiae &amp; pernicioſae eſſent Indulgencae</hi> — <hi>De paenis ſponte
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:41841:44"/>ſuſceptis reſpondemus; non debere
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as relaxari, quatenus utiles ſunt ad novitatem vitae, &amp; carnis mortificationem; ſed poſſe relaxari quatenus ſunt panae debitae peccatis</hi> [i. e. poſt novitatem vitae ad adeptam.] And elſewhere (ſaith he)<note n="*" place="margin">De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg. l. 1. c. 7.</note> — <hi>Hoc tempore qui ſe parant ad Indulgentias conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendas confiteri ſolent peccata Sacerdoti, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctam ſatisfactionem implere; non igitur ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimantes, ſibi tantum injunctas paenitentias con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donari, ſed alias longe majores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſaid here, the Penitent, notwithſtanding Indulgences, is <hi>adviſed</hi> to perform his penances impoſed; but ſome Roman Dctors ſay, <hi>obliged,</hi> if ſuch Penances be expreſly impoſed by his Confeſſor, not as ſatisfactory or vindicative for ſin paſt, but as judged by him morally ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for preſerving one from future, [of which thus
<hi>Suarez</hi> ‖ <hi>Cum in Paenitentiâ injuncta duplex ratio inveniri poſſit, nimirum vindictae, &amp; medicinae praeſervantis, quamvis ex vi Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae ceſſet ſatisfactio Sacramentalis ſub priori ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, non tamen ſub poſteriori, ſi ſub illâ poſita ſit. — Quia Indulgentia tollit debitum; non ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men tollitur materia ſen neceſſitas medicina.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<note n="‖" place="margin">De Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit D. 50. §.
2.</note> — <hi>Intelligendum eſt per has Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias remitti paenitentias impoſitas, ut ſatisfactivae ſunt, non ut medicinales; quia Indulgentia non datur in deſtructionem, ſed in aedificationem ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum.</hi> And — <hi>His temporibus, conſiderato modo quo paenitentiae imponi ſolent, raro vel nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam omittere licet paenitentias impoſitas propter Indulgentias: quia rever â imponuntur leviſſimae paenitentiae, &amp; quae vix ſufficiunt per modum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinae.</hi>] And that paſſage of <hi>Card. Bellarmin,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:41841:44"/>Indulg,</hi> l. 1. c. 7. ſeems much to confirm this — <hi>Interdum etiam Pontifices</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Indulgentiarum praeſcribunt, ut Sacerdotes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jungant paenitentias ſalutares iis, qui indulgenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am conſequi deſiderant</hi> —
<hi>Relaxare autem non intendunt paenitentias illas ſalutares, quas jubent imponi.</hi>] And thoſe Doctors of a contrary opinion, yet grant an obligation ſtill of the penitents performing them, though not from the Prieſts injunction, yet from the morall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the thing as to avoiding ſin, See <hi>Card. Lugo, De Sacram. Paenitent. D.</hi> 27. §. 2. who alſo concludes — <hi>Conſulendum ſemper eſſe paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti ut opera impoſita, quoad fieri poſſit, adim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat; nec debere panitentias omitti indulgentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum occaſione, quia illa opera impoſita etiam fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt a medico ex deſiderio ſalutis, &amp; quia proſunt ad meritum; quod pluris faciendum eſt, quam redemptio panae temporalis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>57</label> As <hi>Indulgences</hi> therefore are a great conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to Chriſtians in reſpect of the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Puniſhments, or Penances, for removing them, (<hi>longe majores,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> than thoſe enjoyned), that they are liable to by their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſins; ſo are they by prudent Chriſtians made little or no uſe of for the omiſſion of any Penances, they can well perform, in their having a continual eye to the other two ends now named, which muſt be made good for reaping any benefit by an Indulgence; and to the third alſo, for the <hi>advancing</hi> of their future <hi>happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> And this, which is ſaid here, may, I ſuppoſe, ſatisfie the <hi>Objection</hi> of our Author<note n="‖" place="margin">p. 526.</note> — that by Indulgences Catholicks are excuſed
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:41841:45"/>from doing the beſt parts of their Religion, <hi>viz.</hi> Severe Mortification, Faſtings, Prayers, Almes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which, 1ſt, If it have any ſtrength in it, holds as much againſt ancient In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, as the modern; nor preſſeth it the one more than the other, both theſe remitting the like penal Satisfactions. 2ly. So far as ſuch penal works are neceſſary, as other <hi>good works,</hi> to the purchaſe or augmentation of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal happineſs; or to repentance for ſins paſt; or to leaving off ſin for the future, none are diſſwaded from them by Indulgences; but on the contrary, for the ampler partaking of the benefit of the Indulgence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are adviſed to, and alſo enjoyned them. <hi>Luther</hi> and
<hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius</hi> long ago moved the ſame Objection, and <hi>Bellarmin</hi> long ago gave ſuch an Anſwer,<note n="‖" place="margin">De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg. l. 2. c 1. and l 2 c. 13.</note> which this Author (as his uſe is) inſtead of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing, conceals.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>58</label> 5ly. It ſeems alſo reaſonable (for which ſee
<hi>Eſtius</hi> in 4. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 20. §. 10. and <hi>Layman Moral Theol.</hi> l.
5.7. <hi>tract.</hi> 5. c. and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors referred-to by them), ſince a much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter penance by a plenary Indulgence is remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to one, than to another, as ſuch is a greater ſinner; or, being an equal offender, hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly done leſs penance for his ſin; and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that the <hi>pious works,</hi> enjoyned, are not varyed proportionably to the different debts of thoſe perſons, who are by the <hi>Indulgence</hi> equally releaſed, reaſonable I ſay, That there be ſuppoſed in the Suſcipient (to obtain the full effect of the Indulgence) a proportionable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, mortification, and degree of Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:41841:45"/>to diſpoſe him for it, according to his greater offences formerly, and ſmaller humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation for them; [To this purpoſe <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Del Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. l. 2. c. 14.</note> on St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> ſaying<note n="*" place="margin">In Serm. de Lapſis.</note> — <hi>Quam mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na deliquimus, tam granditer defleamus,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thus — <hi>Non ſignificat dolorem abſolute offenſioni aequandum eſſe, quod fieri non poteſt; Sed proportionem illam inter peccata &amp; dolorem de peccatis eſſe debere, ut de majore peccato magis, de minore minus doleamus.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ib. c. 11.</note> And * — <hi>Pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum eſt, ne homo ſe ipſe fallat, &amp; dum in ſe acrem &amp; intenſam contritionem excitare non ſatagit, revera ne appreciative quidem toto corde crimina deteſtetur.</hi> And — <hi>Non negamus</hi> (ſaith
<hi>Lugo</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">De Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. Diſp. 2. §. 7.</note> in anſwer alſo to the Fathers) <hi>expedire, ut pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator conetur ſummâ intenſione dolere, ut certior ſit paenitentia,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>In quo ſenſu debent accipi Patres, qui Summum dolorem exigunt</hi> — And <hi>Concil. Trident.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Seſſ. 14. c.
8.</note> — <hi>Sane &amp; Divinae Juſtitiae ratio exigere videtur, ut aliter a Domino in Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam recipiantur qui ante Baptiſnum per ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam deliquerint; aliter vero, qui ſemel a pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; Daemonis ſervitute liberati, &amp; accepto Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus Sancti dono, ſcientes templum Dei violare, &amp; Spiritum Sanctum contriſtare non formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verint.</hi> Which reaſon ſeems to hold as much for ſorrow for ſin, as for ſatisfaction, eſpecially if we conſider the like expreſſion, <hi>Ibid.</hi> c. 2. — <hi>non ſine magnis noſtris fletibus &amp; laboribus,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
            <p>Reaſonable alſo it ſeems, that where the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous work is indefinitely propoſed, as, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the giving of Almes, without any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain quantity expreſſed, this work ſhould be
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:41841:46"/>performed to ſuch a degree, as ſeems more to ſuite with the greater favour any one receives; knowing this, that the diſpenſations of God's Mercies by the Church-Governours (who are entruſted in them, as Stewards, and not as Lords) ought to be adjuſted, as much as may be, to the receivers different capacity thereof. And, if it be ſaid here, that this leaves one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain of a due preparation, and ſo, of the full effect of the Indulgence: I anſwer, that every one is left uncertain in a greater matter, than this, reſpecting Indulgences; namely, in his having a true <hi>Contrition,</hi> and being in the
<hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>59</label> Here then we ſee Motives enow, (without denying Indulgences
<hi>valere quantum ſonant,</hi> as it is expounded before, and this Language is ordinarily underſtood), for <hi>Bellarmins</hi> pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent man both to receive and make uſe of all the Indulgences he can procure, nor lightly to diſtruſt either the judgment or fidelity of thoſe to whom our Lord hath committed the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing of them; and that alſo, 1 for the non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of his own due preparation, and 2 the danger of a relapſe, and 3 the advancing his juſtification and future reward, and alſo 4 as the Indulgence may poſſibly not be ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on a cauſe ſufficient, as to the total effect thereof; that, I ſay, for ſome of theſe reaſons —<hi>Simul</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> together with his making uſe of the Indulgence]
<hi>etiam ſtudeat dignos paeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae fructus ferre</hi> [which clauſe this Author o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits]
<hi>ac pro ſuis peccatis Domino ſatisfacere.</hi> Of which the Cardinal gives theſe very reaſons
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:41841:46"/>in the ſame Paragraph, <hi>Ad tertium— Quia</hi> (ſaith he)
<hi>poteſt fieri, ut aliquando Indulgentia non ſortiatur effectum, ob defectum ejus qui illam ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit; vel ob defectum authoritatis in eo, qui illam concedit; vel ob defectum cauſae. Et Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus populus non ignorat ad fidem pertinere, quod ſit in Eccleſiâ poteſtas indulgentias concedendi; non autem, quod in particulari non poſſit fieri, ut indulgentia vel non ſit rata, vel non proſit.</hi> As he ſaith elſewhere of receiving the Sacraments —<note n="*" place="margin">De Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. l. 2. c. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quia nemo certo ſcire poteſt ſe veram con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritionem habuiſſe; itaque, ut quis de adeptâ in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgentiâ ſecurior ſit, debet etiam omnia illa re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>media adhibere, quae Deus ad peccatà purganda inſtituit.</hi> Which Reaſons of the Cardinal our Author, (making his prudent man, for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral pages, the ſubject of his mirth) inſtead of refuting (as his cuſtome is) omits. For, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, they would quite ſpoile his ſport.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>60</label> 6. For ſeveral <hi>Abuſes</hi> that have been, or are ſtill, found in the <hi>uſe</hi> of <hi>Indulgences;</hi> As they are by Proteſtants, and by this Author particularly, much exagitated, ſo they are by Catholicks confeſſed and deplored. <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3d. in the great Lateran Council held <hi>A. D:</hi> 1215.
<hi>Can.</hi> 62. complains of <hi>Indulgences undiſcreet and ſuperfluous</hi> [i. e.
<hi>inanes &amp; irritae,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bellarmin</hi>] <hi>quibus paenitentialis ſatisfactio enervatur;</hi> and of the miſ-behaviours of the Queſtors, or Collectors in thoſe days.
<hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the 5th. in the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Vienna,</hi> held <hi>A. D.</hi> 1311. cenſures the evil practices of thoſe times much more.<note n="‖" place="margin">Conſtit Clemen. l. 5. tit 9. c. 2;</note> Part of which <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> I will here tranſcribe; to ſhew the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41841:47"/>Reader, that the blame, laid on the Pope and the Church, was the fault of the wicked Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and under-Officers of the inferior Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, to whom the publiſhing of Indulgences, and collection of the peoples Almes for ſome publick pious uſes, was committed; and that Indulgences, as by theſe as well in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, as collections, miſrepreſented to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and perverted, are ſo much inveighed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by ſeveral Roman Writers.—<hi>Cum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui</hi> (ſaith he there) <hi>ex hujusmodi Quaeſtoribus</hi> [of whom he ſaid a little before,—<hi>Mos in ſuis predicationibus ſimplices decipere, &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum extorquere in animarum periculum, &amp; plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimorum ſcandalum] ſicut ad noſtram audientiam eſt perlatum, non ſine multâ temeritatis audaciâ &amp; deceptione multiplici animarum, indulgentias populo, motu ſuo proprio, de facto concedant; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per votis diſpenſent; a perjuriis, homicidiis, &amp; peccatis aliis ſibi conſitentes abſolvant; male ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata incerta (data ſibi aliqua pecuniae quantitate) remittant; tertiam aut quartam partem de pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiis injunctis relaxent; animas tres, vel plures parentum vel amicorum illorum, qui elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſynas eis conferunt, de purgatorio (ut aſſerunt mendaciter) extrahant, &amp; ad gaudia paradiſi perducant; benefactoribus locorum, quorum Quaeſtores exiſtunt, remiſſionem plenariam pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum Indulgeant, &amp; aliqui ex ipſis eos a paenâ &amp; a culpâ (ut eorum verbis utamur) abſolvant. Nos, abuſus hujuſmodi, per quos cenſura vileſcit Eccleſiaſtica, &amp; cldvium Eccleſiae authoritas ducitur in contemptum, omnimode aboleri vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes, inhibemus,</hi> &amp;c. Laſtly, the Council
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:41841:47"/>of <hi>Trent,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Seſſ 21. c. 9.</note> after the loſt labour of ſeveral pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Councils to reform theſe perſons, (who alſo gave ſo great ſcandal to <hi>Luther</hi> and his followers) quite abrogated this
<hi>Office</hi> and the <hi>priviledges</hi> belonging thereto; and hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the publiſhing of ſuch Indulgences, and collection of Charities to the <hi>Ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nary</hi> of the place, and two of the Chapter joyned with him, to be done <hi>nullâ prorſus mercede acceptâ;</hi> i. e. when theſe Alms are directed to ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain publick work; and not left to the peoples own diſtribution of them, to what poor and neceſſitous perſons themſelves think good, in ſuch a quantity, as every ones devotion ſhall move him to, as in many Indulgences they are; where we ſee, that all the <hi>Sales, Harveſts, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Avarice, Cheating</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Huckſters,</hi> occurring almoſt in every page of our Authors diſcourſe, comes only to this; the relieving of ſome poor, and the occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome deeds of Charity to the rich, where themſelves judg it beſt beſtowed; And doth this Author think, in this liberty he takes to ſay what he pleaſes, that if words ſpoken, words alſo printed, and thoſe ſomwhat more than
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall not be called to an account?<note place="margin">Mat. 12.36.</note> But ſuppoſe it be a Collection of the peoples Charity for ſome publick work, as the building of a
<hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>Hoſpital,</hi> the maintaining of a <hi>juſt War</hi> againſt ſome Enemy and oppreſſor of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and this amounting to ſome vaſt ſum of money; may every one therefore take the liberty to charge the Pope, or the Churches Prelates with fraud, covetouſneſs,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:41841:48"/>putting all, or a great part thereof in their own Coffers, and pretending only not intending a publick benefit, at pleaſure, and without proof? Or, this being a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uth, may he therefore deny the lawfulneſs of
<hi>Indulgences,</hi> and defame the <hi>Church</hi> that allows them, upon ſuch a
<hi>Perſonal</hi> fault?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>61</label> Perſonal abuſes in Indulgences are granted, whilſt the Doctrine and practice allowed by the Church are juſtified. A good Catholick this Author may be, and be obliged to believe, no more than now he doth, ſeveral things, which in this diſcourſe he eagerly oppoſeth. Doth he condemn conceſſions of Indulgences for <hi>frivolous</hi> cauſes, and ſome <hi>ſlight</hi> work? So do the Catholick Authors. And doth he not hold the
<hi>Popes</hi> judgment to be <hi>infallible</hi> in theſe? Neither do they. Is he for no
<hi>Treaſure</hi> of the <hi>Church?</hi> If the infinite and inexhauſtible trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Merits and ſatisfactions of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be only allowed by him, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Divines hold no other Treaſure <hi>neceſſary.</hi> Will he have Indulgences only remit <hi>Canonical Penances?</hi> Thoſe Authors, that hold ſo, are not cenſured by the Roman Church. Doth he think, that ſome of the Roman Doctors, in their ſtating of Indulgences have ſwerved from the Doctrine of the <hi>ancient</hi> Church? he may enjoy the Churches Communion, and hold with others of them thoſe tenents that pleaſe him better. I have here frequently quoted ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of them, to ſhew that nothing here ſaid by me is <hi>ſingular.</hi> Doth ſuch a frequency of Iudulgences as ruines Church-Diſcipline, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:41841:48"/>renders the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Keys</hi> contemptible, diſpleaſe him? So doth it the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Seſſ.
25. Decr. de Indulg.</note> (deſiring a greater moderation therein, &amp; a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to the pattern of Antiquity): So hath it likewiſe done ſeveral <hi>Popes,</hi> as is ſaid before. Doth he deteſt the baſe Arts, and miſ-informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the people, for filthy lucres ſake, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing them much more than Indulgences ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to, or the Churches Doctrine warrants? So have
<hi>Councils,</hi> and <hi>Popes,</hi> as I have ſhewn, cenſured and endeavoured to ſuppreſs them. Are ſuch conplaints of the abuſe of Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences made now? So were they in St. <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>'s time. Of which he ſaid<note n="*" place="margin">Serma de Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</note> — <hi>Irrita pax: pernicioſa dantibus, nihil profutura accipientibus.</hi> And—<note n="‖" place="margin">Epiſt. 11. Ad Martyres &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor.</note> 
               <hi>Ea concedere quae in perniciem vertun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, decipere eſt: nec erigitur ſic lapſus</hi> [from the Indulgence] <hi>ſed per Dei offenſam magis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellitur ad ruinam.</hi> But not therefore, for ſuch abuſes, the uſe of Indulgences to be abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated. To conclude, the preſent <hi>allowed practice</hi> of Indulgences, by occaſioning the examination of mens Conſciences, and a ſence and ſorrow for their ſins, a repairing to the Sacraments, and performing many penances, ſeems rather to improve <hi>Chriſtian Diſcipline</hi> (as the times are now degenerated from the ancient) than to impair it; And ordinarily, by the
<hi>Indulged</hi> his diſpoſing of his own Alms, this practice is ſufficiently cleared from Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, Bargains, Sales, Cheating, this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors main charge. Again, the
<hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> concerning them is very compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and general: Nor is there any part of this
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:41841:49"/>Authors book, wherein ſo much may be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, without violating any thing taught by <hi>It.</hi> And as no Point commonly is more baited by Proteſtants, than this of Indulgences, ſo none ſeems to afford them leſs pretence of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, or to give leſs cauſe of departing from the Churches Communion (yet this is ſaid to be the firſt, that occaſioned that of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and the Reformation) ſince it is a <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,</hi> or Favour, that none are <hi>compelled</hi> to make uſe of, and thoſe who have any fears, or ſcruples concerning it, and therefore would have <hi>no Indulgences,</hi> may let them alone, do their penances, and all is well.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>62</label> And here I might well paſs by the Fifteen Queſtions, every one alſo containing many ſub-Queſtions in it, with which this Author<note n="‖" place="margin">c. 6 §. 9. p. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> concludes his Diſcourſe of Indulgences, and ſaith, the Roman Doctrine of Indulgences with a touch of theſe <hi>flyes in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eces like a Glaſs-drop,</hi> (though this Doctrine hath been touched by the chiefeſt of theſe Queſtions long ago, asked by <hi>Luther, Calvin, Chemnitius,</hi> and others; and the Catholicks Anſwers to them, ſeem to have made them vaniſh away like ſo many wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-bubbles: Neither hath this Author, for all his terrible and deſtructive touches, had the courage to touch theſe
<hi>Anſwers.</hi>) Theſe, I ſay, I might paſs by, having already ſpoken to all that ſeems material, and pertinent therein, in the precedent Diſcourſe. Beſides; He that maintains a thing as a point of his Faith, cannot therefore reaſonably be obliged to reſolve all manner of <hi>Queſtions,</hi> that may be put concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:41841:49"/>it; It is ſufficient, that he hath a good evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſo much, as he doth, or is obliged to maintain; or, as the Church hath determined. Many queſtions may be asked, wherein there appears not light enough for giving a certain reſolution; and this anſwer only needs be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to them, that, to maintain all that the <hi>Church,</hi> or our <hi>Faith</hi> requires, it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to anſwer them. Many Queſtions there are concerning Indulgences ſtated <hi>Pro.</hi> and <hi>Con.</hi> by learned Catholicks, whilſt all of them agree in the lawfulneſs and benefit of them; and, Who doubts of the Holy Trinity, becauſe he cannot clear all difficulties about it? Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> thought it a good Anſwer to
<hi>Bellarmin</hi> concerning the Real Preſence— <hi>Praeſentiam credimus non minus quam vos veram. De modo praeſentiae nil temere definimus:</hi> And eſpecially this liberty may be claimed, when this Author is in ſuch an unſerious and drolling humour, with which, in ſuch ſacred matters, his Adverſary hath no inclination to a correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, asking ſuch Queſtions as theſe: <hi>What ſatisfaction Gods Juſtice receives for remitting a temporal puniſhment upon an Indulgence grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, where, when, how, by whom, it is paid?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Q 14.</note> 
               <hi>in what way the payment is made? whether ſo much ready caſh of the Churches Treaſure</hi> [i. e. of our Lords ſufferings for us] <hi>is paid down upon the nail, according to the proportion of every ones ſins,</hi> [or temporal puniſhment]; <hi>or God is told where ſuch a treaſure lies, and bid go and ſatisfie himſelf for ſo much as is to be diſcharged of the Debt?</hi> But indeed ſuch extravagant Interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatories
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:41841:50"/>made in theſe Spiritual matters, as if the Churches treaſure were kept under lock and key, and counted like money out of a bag, are rather to be contemned, than replied to. Yet, that this Author may not pleaſe himſelf too much therein, or his Proteſtant Reader o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-value them, I ſhall return to them briefly that which I conceive ſufficient to undeceive him, (giving here only the ſum of them, and leaving the Reader to view them more at large in the Book).</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>63</label> To the Firſt, <hi>Why in a plenary Indulgence the expreſſion runs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qu. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Remiſſion and Pardon of all their ſins, when the Indulgence relates only to the Temporal Puniſhment thereof?</hi> The Anſwer is ſet down before §. 49. <hi>Remiſſion of ſin</hi> is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Indulgence, becauſe an Indulgence alwaies ſuppoſeth remiſſion of the ſin (<hi>quoad culpam</hi> or
<hi>offenſam</hi>), and of its <hi>eternal</hi> puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the uſe of the Sacrament of Penance, that is joyned with the Indulgence; and then It compleats all <hi>quoad paenam</hi> too, in remiſſion alſo of the <hi>temporal</hi> puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>64</label> To the Second. <hi>How any puniſhment of the fault can be ſtil due,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qu. 2.</note> 
               <hi>when the fault is already pardoned?</hi> R. One would think our Author had never heard of <hi>Reatus culpae,</hi> and <hi>paenae;</hi> or rather, he knew, the Lady had not. By Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the <hi>Sin,</hi> Catholicks mean, of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity it puts between God and the Sinner, whereby he is again received into his favour, with which is alſo alwaies neceſſarily joyned the <hi>remiſſion</hi> of the <hi>Eternal Puniſhment;</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of which cannot conſiſt with our reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:41841:50"/>into his friendſhip, as the retention of ſome temporal puniſhment may. The ſin then, as to this <hi>enmity, wholly</hi> pardoned, yet, as to its puniſhment, is remitted only in <hi>part;</hi> and in part ſtill un-remitted, and to be anſwered-for. As a Parent, ſtraight, upon a Childs confeſſion of a fault, moving him to pity, re-admits him into his loſt ſavour (which we call forgiving his fault; and do learn this Language from what
<hi>Nathan</hi> ſaid from God to <hi>David;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing —<hi>Dominus tranſtulit peccatum tuum</hi>) but nevertheleſs after this,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.13.</note> for many good ends, corrects him for it, as God did <hi>David,</hi> ver. 14.—<hi>Propter hoc, filius qui natus eſt tibi,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo ſaith the Pſalmiſt of the Children of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Deſert<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi>
98.8.</note>—<hi>Domine Deus noſter, tu propitius fuiſti eis</hi> [there is pardoning the ſin, and yet], <hi>&amp; ulciſcens in omnes adinventio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes eorum;</hi> [i. e. the temporal puniſhment of their pardoned ſins he there inflicted on them, not entring into the Land of promiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] Perhaps this Queſtioner may better compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend this, if I ſet it him down in the Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Proteſtant, <hi>Chemnitius</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Exam. Conc. Trid. part. 2. De Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fact.</note> —<hi>Fide prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſtum, accipimus ſimul remiſſionem culpae &amp; paenae aeternae. Sed, quod ad paenas temporales in hac vitâ attinet, poſt acceptam remiſſionem pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum ſubjiciuntur</hi>
[juſtificati] <hi>in hac vitâ vel communibus calamitatibus, vel peculiaribus paenis propter certa ſeu privata quaedam peccata. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Adam, David, Populus Iſrael, Miriam. Teſtantur idem calamitates Baptizatorum poſt Baptiſmum. Oſtendunt etiam Scripturae exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla, Deum aliquando &amp; poſt reconciliationem, ſeu
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:41841:51"/>remiſſionem quibuſdam ſingulares paenas ob pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata in hac vitâ imponere, quanquam hoc non ſit univerſale.</hi>—<hi>Scriptura etiam dicit, de reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis; orpus mortuum eſt propter peccatum,</hi> Rom. 8. And 2. Reg. 12, <hi>Quia feciſti hoc,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>Non quaſi Deus illis nondum ſatis ſit reconciliatus, ſeu aliquid offenſae retinuerit, etiam poſt datam remiſſionem peccatorum; Sed illis imponuntur ad caſtigationem ſui, &amp; ad exemplum aliorum: Ne, acceptâ reconciliatione, obliviſcantur, quanta ſit abominatio peccati, &amp; quae magnitudo irae Dei ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus peccatum.</hi> Thus He</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>65</label> To the Third. <hi>What temporal puniſhment re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remains to be ſatisfied for by us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qu. 3.</note> 
               <hi>from which we may be freed by Indulgences?</hi> R. We can be freed only from thoſe temporal puniſhments by
<hi>Indulgences,</hi> from which we may by our <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</hi> If asked, from what temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments our penances may relieve us? I anſwer; from ſuch, as God purpoſeth to inflict on any here, or hereafter, in this world, or the next (if he ſpare us here) in relation to our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſonal and actual ſins, unleſs our own penances and humiliations do prevent them. But then, ſpeaking of this preſent life, where many ſufferings and afflictions happen to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians upon many other accounts, than the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing and chaſtiſing them for ſome former ſins; and where ſome of thoſe alſo, that are inflicted for former ſins, may be not upon any humiliation or penances avertible; which, or of what kind thoſe be, that are avertible; or whether of any kind ſome, but not others; God only knows, not we. As for Death taken
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:41841:51"/>in general, it is a puniſhment of Original ſin, not removable by Penances; but, for any thing we know, a premature, or ſome other kind of death, to ſome particular perſons, may. Mean while, that Penances, Humiliations, Faſtings Watchings, Prayers, Alms,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> (ſuch as the <hi>Ninevites</hi> uſed) may reſcue us from ſome temporal puniſhments for our ſins, that God would otherwiſe inflict, ſurely this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor will not deny; For the Proteſtants to ſuch an end appoint certain days of Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I now then demand of him, whether ſuch our humiliations free us <hi>from all temporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, or only ſome one kind? Whether diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, pains and death, be not part of the temporal puniſhment of ſin; and whether men may be freed from theſe by ſuch humiliations? Whether from the effects of the Juſtice of God in extraordinary Judgments? if not, how can a man</hi> by ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliations <hi>be ſaid to be freed from the temporal puniſhment of ſin, that is as liable to it as any one elſe?</hi> The anſwer here, ſitted to our <hi>humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and
<hi>penances,</hi> will ſerve as well for <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences</hi> from ſuch penances. And ſo I leave his own Anſwer to ſatisfie his own Objection.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>66</label> To the Fourth. <hi>If freed from only one ſort of the temporal puniſhment of ſin, what ſort that is;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qu. 4.</note> 
               <hi>that the Indulged may know, what puniſhment he is freed from?</hi> R. The Anſwer to the former Queſtion ſatisfies alſo this. I ſay then again: The freedom is from ſuch temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſin, as the Divine Juſtice purpoſed to inflict, unleſs prevented herein by our penan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. I add here, which puniſhments, <hi>what,</hi> or
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:41841:52"/>
               <hi>how many,</hi> they ſhall be, as none can tell the Indulged, ſo neither is he concerned to know; he certainly gaining by the <hi>Indulgence,</hi> ſo long as the pious work performed by him is of a leſs value than the puniſhment remitted to him. However the Roman Authors be divided in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, all maintain to the truly penitent a <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> benefit by a <hi>lawful</hi> Indulgence.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>67</label> To the Fifth. <hi>If it be from Canonical Penance that one is freed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qu. 5.</note> 
               <hi>whether he be wholly freed from the obligation of that, or no? and if he be, what power the Prieſt hath to enjoyn Penance after it?</hi> [i. e. as I underſtand him, after a perſon is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the benefit of the Indulgence.] I Anſer: After the gaining of the Indulgence, the Prieſt hath no power to enjoyn any more penance for ſins committed before it, <hi>i. e.</hi> in order to the ſatisfaction of any temporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>68</label> To the Sixth. <hi>Why the ſatisfaction of Chriſt might not as well remit the temporal puniſhment at that time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qu. 6.</note> 
               <hi>when the fault is remitted upon the account of this ſatisfaction, as afterward by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences?</hi> R. It might, had God ſo pleaſed to remit to ſinners, offending him more highly by a relapſe from their baptiſmal Grace, thoſe their ſins, and all the puniſhments by his Juſtice belonging to them, at once. But that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom, for many good ends, <hi>de facto</hi> doth not remit all the puniſhment together with the ſin, appears from the Texts alleaged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore §. 48.</p>
            <p>This to his ſix firſt Queſtions, wherein he ſeems a little more ſerious.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>69</label> The other Nine
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:41841:52"/>that remain, are all ſpent about the Churches Treaſure, as it relates to the ſatisfying the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice for the Indulgences conceded by the Church; To all which it were ſufficient to return him that litle ſhort anſwer of Doctor <hi>Holden</hi> mentioned before<note n="‖" place="margin">§. 47. De reſol. fidei l. 2. c. 6.</note> —<hi>Caetera omnia dubia ſunt,</hi> &amp;c. —<hi>Nimirum an ſit theſaurus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquis meritorum &amp; ſatisfactionum in Eccleſiâ; cujus diſpenſatores ſint Romanus Pontifex, &amp; reliqui Eccleſiae Paſtores.</hi> The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> (as Doctor <hi>Taylor</hi> obſerves) hath ſaid nothing of ſuch a <hi>Treaſure;</hi> neither is it more neceſſary to be diſputed now, as to the benefit of Indulgences, than in Saint
<hi>Cyprians</hi> time. There was no remiſſion, then, or now, from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pain or penance of ſin, but through the <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> and <hi>ſatisfactions</hi> of our <hi>Lord;</hi> and either their Indulgences are liable to the ſame Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or, ours exempt. And thus I might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs all the following. But, becauſe they may not ſeem to ſome of greater concernment, or gravity, than indeed they are, I ſhall alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them. And, this Treaſure being ſaid to conſiſt partly of the <hi>ſatisfactions</hi> of our <hi>Lord,</hi> partly of his <hi>Saints,</hi> I ſhall apply my ſelf firſt to thoſe things that are queſtioned by him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Lords ſatisfactions, in his 7, 8, 9, 14th. queſtions; and then to thoſe concerning the Saints in Qu. 10, 11, 12, 13.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>70</label> Concerning the former of theſe <hi>ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> This is certain, that the great, rich, and inexhauſtible Treaſure of Chriſtians, and of the Church (I call it the Churches Treaſure, becauſe our Lord diſpenſeth it by the Churches
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:41841:53"/>Miniſtry) by which our Redemption from Sin, and all its puniſhments, is purchaſed, are the <hi>Merits</hi> and <hi>Satisfactions</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And this Treaſure is not disburſed and laid out pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly for all ſinners whatever, but thoſe only, on whom, rightly prepared and diſpoſed, the Succeſſors of our Lord by his appointment, do confer the Sacraments, inſtituted by him for remiſſion of ſin. Here, therefore, we will ſuppoſe this Sacrament to be <hi>Baptiſme.</hi> Upon the adminiſtration whereof, to the baptized, by the Miniſtry of the Clergy, are applyed the Merits and Satisfactions of Chriſt tendred to, and accepted by, <hi>Gods Juſtice</hi> for the remiſſion of their Sins, and all puniſhment thereof, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, or Temporal. No Proteſtant, I ſuppoſe, gain-ſaying this, Now I beg leave to return, to this Author, his own <hi>Queſtions,</hi> the better to make appear the great levity and vanity of them; only changing the ſubject, and asking them not concerning <hi>Indulgences</hi> but <hi>Baptiſme;</hi> wherein this Author muſt grant this Treaſure of our Lords ſatisfactions, to the rightly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, to be applyed for remiſſion of ſin, and its puniſhment; ſo that they may every whit as well be asked of the one, as of the other. And then, what Anſwers he thinks fit to give con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the one, he and his party may take the ſame alſo for the other. And, if he will war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant them for ſatisfactory, I hope he will think better of the Roman Doctrine concerning the <hi>Churches Treaſure,</hi> according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe<note n="‖" place="margin">p 524.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>71</label> To begin,<note place="margin">Qu. 7.</note> then, with the Seventh queſtion.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:41841:53"/>Here, preſuppoſing that our Lords ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are infinite, and not ſo exhauſted by the diſcharging to Gods Juſtice the debt of the ſins and puniſhments of all thoſe baptized hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, but that there remains great plenty of them that may ſtill be applied in the <hi>baptiſm</hi> of others, and ſtill be redundant; this, I ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true, and clear, I deſire this Author would tell me, (repeating here the 7th. queſtion) <hi>How, here, the parts of Chriſts ſatisfaction come to be divided into that which was neceſſary,</hi> for thoſe already baptized, <hi>and that which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundant ſtill</hi> for others; and part of theſe be <hi>neceſſary to ſatisfie for the fault,</hi> another part redundant, or remaining, <hi>to ſatisfie for the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral or eternal puniſhment thereof? Whether</hi> in general <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Paſſion and Sufferings <hi>did any more than God required? Whether any thing</hi> of that, all <hi>which God required, can be ſaid to be redundant? If the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e be, how ſome part comes to be applyed</hi> already, <hi>and the other to remain ſtill</hi> for others <hi>in the Churches Treaſure? What parts can be made of an infinite and entire ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction?</hi> [where note, that ſpeaking of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of our Lords ſatisfactions, part, or the whole, no other Language is, or needs to be uſed in <hi>Indulgences,</hi> than in <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> Let the entire ſatisfaction of our Lord be applied to one Sinner in baptiſm, ſo as it remains en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire alſo ſtill, for another; and be applyed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire for remiſſion of ſin in baptiſm, ſo as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains intire alſo for remiſſion of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments belonging to ſin, temporal, or eternal; and after all, that ever hereafter ſhall receive
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41841:54"/>baptiſm, that it remains intire ſtill, (becauſe infinite), for infinite more perſons, if they were in being; and that it be ſo beſtowed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire already, that ſtill it remains intire to be beſtowed; and as is well. For as <hi>Suarez</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">De Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. Diſp. 51. §. 1.</note> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to the ſilly queſtion, In what place this Treaſure is kept?—<hi>Res ſpiritualis eſt &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis, non in materiali loco, ſed in divinâ accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione &amp; preſentiâ exiſtens:</hi> ſo may I concerning its parts; <hi>Res ſpiritualis eſt, non habens partes,</hi> &amp;c. And it is this Author here, in making ſuch queſtions, troubles us with theſe Notions; How it is divided? where kept? when, and how much, paid? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To proceed now in his queſtions]
<hi>And if ſo little be neceſſary</hi> for all already baptized, <hi>what needs ſo much redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant</hi> for remitting any ſin or puniſhment of others that ſhall be baptized hereafter?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>72</label> Come we to the Eighth. Here we ask; <hi>Whether all the ſatisfaction of Chriſt taken to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether was not great enough to remit the eternal puniſhment of the whole world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qu. 8.</note> as well as of theſe that are, or that ever ſhall be, baptized? <hi>If it were, whether all the redundant parts of that,</hi> which would have redeemed the reſt, ſince not all, but a very ſmall part of the world is, or ſhall be redeemed, or baptized, be caſt into the Churches treaſure too? <hi>and who hath the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this treaſure, and what uſe is made of ſo much treaſure</hi> beyond what all that ever were, or ſhall be baptized do ſtand in need of; and which, as remitting the eternal puniſhment, is <hi>much more uſeful, than that which ſerves only to remit the temporal</hi> in Indulgences? <hi>And what
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:41841:54"/>account can the Church-Governours give, if ſuffering ſo vaſt a part of the Churches treaſure to lie idle, and make no uſe of it for the benefit of thoſe that need it;</hi> namely, of all that part of the world to whom it is not already applyed? [Mean while this Author may know, that the Church. Governors do take their beſt care, that none do want this application, who need it, and are rightly diſpoſed for it; and where God hath made any promiſe to ratifie their act].</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>73</label> The Ninth Succeeds. In which we further enquire; If our Lords Succeſſors have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them the cuſtody and diſpoſing of ſuch a treaſure of Chriſts merits and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the rightly diſpoſed,<note place="margin">Qu. 9.</note> in their adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacraments, <hi>why may they not, if they think of it, procure another mighty treaſure of the abſolute power of God, which is never uſed, as for making new worlds,</hi> &amp;c? <hi>And may they not by the help of this</hi> Treaſure of Gods power
<hi>deliver Souls out of Hell, as well as by the other</hi> from it? <hi>And if this be ſo much the greater kindneſs, they ought to think of it, and employ this treaſure for theſe purpoſes. And why may they not think of another treaſure of the light of the Sun that is more than enough for the uſe of the world, and to lay it up in ſtore for the benefit of purblind and aged?</hi> [Doth not this better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>Socinian,</hi> or an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> than a grave Divine? and might he not have done well to have choſen another ſubject, for ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly levity, than the <hi>infinite Merits</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions</hi> of our
<hi>Lord?</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:41841:55"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>74</label> The following queſtions to the 14th. are concerning the ſatisfactions of Saints;<note place="margin">Qu. 14.</note> of which by and by. Review we next then the <hi>Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth.</hi> Where, if ſatisfaction, by the ſufferings of our Lord, be tendred to <hi>Gods Juſtice</hi> for what ever puniſhment of penitent Sinners that are baptized, <hi>we deſire to know, when, and by whom the payment of theſe</hi> ſufferings or ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions of our Lord, is made to God? <hi>If it was made</hi> by Chriſt (the Perſon whoſe ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions make the Churches Treaſure) <hi>for that end, what have his Miniſters to do to diſpenſe that,</hi> now in their conferring the Sacraments, <hi>which God hath accepted long ago</hi> from our Lord when he died, <hi>for payment? But if the payment be made now by the Miniſters, in what way do they make it? do they take out ſo much ready caſh of the Churches treaſure, and pay it down upon the naile according to the proportion of every ones ſin</hi> that is baptized? <hi>Or do they only tell God where ſuch a treaſure lies, and bid him go and ſatisfie himſelf for ſo much as they then diſcharge of the</hi> baptized perſons <hi>debt</hi> for his ſins? <hi>[Diſce ſapere ad ſobrietatem].</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>75</label> This we ask of our Lords, next, for the
<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions</hi> of the <hi>Saints;</hi> thoſe of one being accepted for averting ſome temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from another;<note place="margin">Q. 10.</note> On which ſubject are this Authors queſtions, from the 9th. to the 14th. Here ſuppoſe (which not ſeldome happens) an Holy Man, upon ſome great offending of God by ſome of near relation to himſelf, Prays, Faſts, wears Sackcloath, and uſeth other Penan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Mortifications meerly on the others
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:41841:55"/>behalf for preventing ſome temporal judgment that he fears hangs over his head: And God, accepting ſuch humiliation of his, for a perſon ſo diſpoſed as to be capable of it, averts this judgment, which, otherwiſe, he would have inflicted upon the others Crimes; (a thing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, I ſuppoſe, this Author will grant not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>often done, or at leaſt poſſible to be ſo. And now let us return to his 10th. Queſtion, and demand of him: <hi>If the ſatisfaction of Chriſt be ſo redundant,</hi> as it is made, <hi>how comes it not to be ſufficient for ſo poor an end,</hi> as this temporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of this ſinner is; <hi>but that</hi> the humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations and penances of this holy man <hi>muſt make up a ſhare in this infinite treaſure</hi> of our Lords ſufferings? [But note here, upon this word <hi>Muſt;</hi> that none ſay, there is any neceſſity of the ſatisfactions of Saints to be added to our Lords; or ſaith, that our Lords are not <hi>ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,</hi> as our Author invidiouſly here propoſeth the caſe.] <hi>Is not this worſe, than to light a Candle to help the Sun, to ſuppoſe Chriſts ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction ſo infinite, as to be ſufficient to redeem more worlds, and yet not enough to deliver from a temporal puniſhment without</hi> the humiliation of this holy man? [<hi>Not enough,</hi> none ſaith ſo. All-ſufficient Chriſts ſatisfactions are; but yet God to honour his Saints, and for other ends of his Wiſdome, is pleaſed to do favours to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers upon the penal works and humiliations, or alſo prayers, of his Saints in their behalf; but all theſe ſtill accepted by God through his <hi>Sons Satisfactions.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>76</label> To go on with the Eleventh.<note place="margin">Qu. 11.</note> Here we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:41841:56"/>the ſame again. <hi>How comes</hi> this Holy Man to do ſuch large Penances
<hi>with regard to Gods Juſtice</hi> and Wrath, <hi>if the ſanctification of Chriſt were of ſo infinite a nature? And if he practice</hi> mortifications and penances, <hi>is he not ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rewarded for them? If he be, how come theſe to help the other,</hi> his Friend,
<hi>which he is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly recompenſed for himſelf.</hi> [Here I ask al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; How come our
<hi>prayers</hi> to procure from God ſome benefit to others, when for the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of them, we our ſelves likewiſe are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded by him; a thing not doubted of? The ſame pious work or ſuffering may obtain a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold recompence, and that as to ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, by way of
<hi>Impetration</hi> from Gods bounty and mercy which enlargeth its ſelf without bounds,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm. De Indulg. l. 1. c. 2. §. 2. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitio.</note> how far it pleaſeth. But it is grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that when we ſpeak of a ſtrick <hi>compenſation</hi> or ſatisfaction made to Gods Juſtice, thus no work or ſuffering of ours, that is equivalent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfactory only for <hi>anothers debt</hi> (ſuppoſe, of temporal puniſhments), can be alſo of <hi>our own:</hi> for none can ſo pay to Gods Juſtice two debts with that ſum, which is due for one of them only.]</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>77</label> In the Twelfth, We ask: <hi>If the ſatisfaction of Chriſt doth only obtain Grace for this</hi> Holy man to do penance himſelf,<note place="margin">Q.
12.</note> for averting <hi>the temporal puniſhment of his own ſin,</hi> [But, who ſaith thus?] <hi>how can the application,</hi> or accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Holy Mans penances <hi>free another from the temporal puniſhment of his ſin,</hi> without his doing any penance? <hi>Or have his penances being joyned with Chriſts ſatisfactions greater
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:41841:56"/>power with God for this other perſon, than the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions of Chriſt have for himſelf?</hi> [What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Authors meaning is in this Queſtion, which perhaps I do not rightly comprehend, Chriſts ſatisfactions alone are affirmed, both for Common Penitents and Saints, all ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and not only do obtain <hi>grace</hi> for Saints, to ſatisfie themſelves, for a temporal puniſhment; but alſo, when applyed by an Indulgence, do procure a remiſſion of ſuch temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them, without their own <hi>Penances</hi> or
<hi>Satisfactions.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>78</label> We continue, in the Thirteenth, the ſame demand:<note place="margin">Qu. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Why the ſatisfaction of Chriſt may not ſerve</hi> [But, who are they, that ſay, it may not? See before §. 47.] <hi>without</hi> this Holy Mans penances
<hi>to remit only the</hi> other perſons <hi>temporal puniſhment for his ſin, when the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Chriſt was ſufficient alone to remit both eternal and temporal to</hi> that perſon <hi>in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſme? Or was the force of it ſpent then, that it needs a freſh ſupply afterwards</hi> from this Holy Mans penances? <hi>But if then it could be applyed to a higher end, without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther help, why not where it is to have far leſs efficacy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have now paſſed through all his Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning the <hi>Churches Treaſure;</hi> many of them, as they ſeem to me, very irreverent and impertinent; of which (as I ſaid) he may accept of that Anſwer in his application of them to <hi>Indulgences</hi> which he gives us in ours to the <hi>Sacrament.</hi> The laſt Queſtion yet remains.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:41841:57"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>79</label> Viz: <hi>How came this treaſure of the Church,</hi> i. e. the <hi>ſuperfluities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qu. 15.</note> as he calls them, of <hi>Chriſts ſatisfactions</hi> for the temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſin which are applyed in Indulgences, <hi>into the Popes keeping; and who gave him the Keys of them? when every Prieſt is truſted in the Sacrament of Penance, with the treaſure of Chriſts neceſſary ſatisfaction for the remitting of the eternal puniſhment?</hi> R. After I have firſt told him (for the language is uſed by him here) that I know no Roman Divine that ſtiles Chriſts ſatisfactions for the remitting of Sin, and the eternal puniſhment, <hi>neceſſary,</hi> and of the temporal, <hi>ſuperfluous:</hi> I Anſwer; That in the doubt, what perſons have the lawful <hi>power</hi> of <hi>conced<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng</hi> Indulgences, it is ſufficient that Proteſtants then be ſatisfied, when they are firſt agreed to admitt them. Mean while what needs our Author trouble himſelf, or us, with ſuch a queſtion? The Pope, ſurely, hath as much power of, and right to keep, the Keys, as any. Of thoſe Indulgences, then, which he concedes, none needs diſpute the validity: But not to leave this unſpoken to. I ſay 1ſt. That, as not the Conceſſion of Indulgences, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of the power of <hi>Abſolution</hi> (this alſo being an Act of Juriſdiction and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature) i.e. neither the application of Chriſts Merits and Satisfactions, for the eternal, nor for the temporal puniſhment of Sin, doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Inferiour Clergy, but dependently from the Biſhops and Governours of the Church; which Commiſſion they receive alſo with a reſervation of ſeveral Caſes, wherein
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:41841:57"/>they may not <hi>abſolve.</hi> Next; for Church-Governours: Not only the Pope, but other Biſhops <hi>de facto</hi> have conceded Indulgences in ancient times, and do ſtill. But whether the conceding of them doth belong to all Biſhops <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> or only to the ſuprem Governour the Pope, is diſputed among the Schoolmen. The Council of
<hi>Trent,</hi> (though there they were much diſputed) hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined nothing about the Limits of ſuch Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Juriſdictions; but left them to the former current Eccleſiaſtical Cuſtoms and Practices; Several limitations and reſtraints of them have been made by the ſupreme Biſhop of the Church the Succeſſor of St. <hi>Peter</hi> (to whom in the firſt place our Lord committed the Keys <hi>[Tibi dabo Claves]</hi> not only with a Precedency to, but Power and Authority over, the reſt): and have been made to very good ends, that things might be done with better <hi>order</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion, and with leſs confuſion, and relaxation of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> as it is alſo particularly in this <hi>granting</hi> of
<hi>Indulgences;</hi> And ſo long as the Biſhops acquieſce therein, ſuch queſtions, as this, ſeem rather moved to the diſturbance of the Churches peace, than any edification in the Chriſtian Faith. And ſo I leave it. The Roman School-Divines, to this and ſeveral other of his queſtions, have not been ſilent; nor wanted his Predeceſſors the wit to ask them before him. If he looks ſo much into their Books, as he pretends, why takes he no notice of their Anſwers? Is it not becauſe he finds ſo much Reaſon in them, as he is loth to divulge to his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:41841:58"/>party, unleſs he could do it with greater ſatisfaction?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>80</label> This to his queſtions. But now, after all theſe
<hi>Invectives</hi> againſt the Roman Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, <hi>i. e.</hi> againſt the remitting of ſome Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and this not <hi>gratis;</hi> but, for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pious Works done in liue thereof [perhaps ſo many times Viſiting a Church, and therein for ſome time <hi>offering</hi> up his <hi>Devotions, Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> on certain days, giving ſo much <hi>Alms,</hi> and the like]; and for a <hi>Cauſe,</hi> that, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing ſome publick, or private good, bears ſome proportion to that which is remitted, or alſo far exceeds it; as warring againſt Infidels oppreſſing the Church, Converſion of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, building of Churches, Hoſpitals,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> And, again, For the remiſſion of which Penan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the Perſon is required firſt to examine the quality of his ſins, and to excite a <hi>Contrition</hi> ſutable thereto, to repair to the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Penance, Confeſſion,</hi> and
<hi>Abſolution,</hi> and alſo to perform ſuch <hi>penances</hi> as may be thought ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and medicinal to the conquering his luſts, and preventing the like miſcarriages for the time to come, and all this to be done by him to render himſelf capable of the benefit of an
<hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence:</hi> I ſay, after all this inveighing againſt ſuch a practice of the Roman Church, wherein (as uſually in all other Points conteſted, ſhe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtands upon her
<hi>guard</hi> and defence of Cuſtoms deſcending to her from <hi>Ancient</hi> Times; and the Accuſers, and Invaders, are the other Party); with what greater ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity do the Proteſtant Miniſters treat a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:41841:58"/>that, after the loſing his Baptiſmal Grace, labours under mortal ſin? What Penances, what better thing, than thoſe Roman <hi>pious Works,</hi> which they deride, do they impoſe? They indeed, as <hi>Catholicks</hi> alſo, exhort ſuch a perſon to
<hi>repentance</hi> of his ſin, and <hi>amendment</hi> of his life; and tell him, as Catholicks alſo do, that theſe are neceſſary; but then the ſureſt way to acquiring a true
<hi>repentance,</hi> and the chiefeſt means of working in him a <hi>reformation</hi> of life,
<hi>i. e.</hi> ſolitude, penance, mortifications, abſtinences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they preſs not to him; and of the <hi>neceſſity</hi> alſo of the <hi>Churches Keys</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſuch <hi>Mortal</hi> ſin committed after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm they do not inform him.</p>
            <p>They tell him, that he needs fear no further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckonings for his ſin, as to any puniſhment or ſufferings for it, if once repented of; that <hi>ſin, &amp; all its puniſhments</hi> are wiped off at once [for, ſaith our Author,<note n="*" place="margin">p. 519. Queſt 2.</note>
               <hi>how can that fault be ſaid to be remitted, which is yet puniſhed?</hi>] and therefore that our doing any <hi>penance,</hi> for avoiding ſuch puniſhment, is needleſs. The Indulgences in the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church, only <hi>ſomtimes</hi> uſed for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting ſuch penances, (yet this not without commutation) are cried out of<note n="‖" place="margin">Rom. Idol. p.
526.</note> 
               <hi>as excuſing them from doing the beſt parts of their Religion;</hi> Yet, among Proteſtants, ſuch penances are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <hi>always,</hi> in their being never at all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; and yet their piety and Religion thrives well enough without them; and they are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther required as the <hi>beſt,</hi> nor <hi>any</hi> part of it. They cry out of the lightening ſomtimes of mens burdens in the Church of Rome by <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences;</hi>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:41841:59"/>but themſelves will not touch thoſe lighter burdens (mentioned before), that are laid on them for gaining theſe Indulgences, with one of their fingers. Nothing is done
<hi>right</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> whilſt among them nothing is done <hi>at all;</hi> and <hi>therefore,</hi> in the other is nothing done <hi>right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>81</label> To Conclude theſe diſcourſes; let all pious Chriſtians in general beware of ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive and <hi>Negative Way</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> as to ſo great a part of the Churches Practicals: Which thus endeavours to pull down all that ſtands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, but it ſelf builds nothing; and, under pretence of reforming Religion, and Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, only defaceth them; and ſo leaves the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines thereof to be trampled upon by Atheiſts. Here are (ſpeaking of the <hi>moſt</hi> part, and thoſe that ſtand at a
<hi>farther diſtance</hi> from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church) no <hi>Mental</hi> prayer; no
<hi>Purgation</hi> or <hi>Mortification</hi> in order thereto; no <hi>Abſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of
<hi>life;</hi> no <hi>Contemplation,</hi> no ſtate of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, no <hi>Aſpirations,</hi> no
<hi>Active</hi> or <hi>Paſſive <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nions,</hi> talked of. No <hi>Evangelical Councils;</hi> but thoſe ſo called, help <hi>precepts</hi> to ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, of which none finds himſelf to be one; no recommending of <hi>ſolitude;</hi> of <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle life;</hi> of quitting the poſſeſſion and cares of Riches,—<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſoliciti ſint quae ſunt Domini, quo modo placeant Deo</hi> 1 Cor. 7.32.—and <hi>ut facultatem praebeat ſine impedimento Dominum obſecrandi;</hi> No <hi>Sacerdotal Confeſſion;</hi> and ſo no
<hi>Caſuiſts</hi> to ſatisfie ſcruples; &amp; ſo no liability of ſuch to be miſconſtrued in ſtating ſuch points; as the <hi>Roman Caſuiſts</hi> are moſt ſhamefully by
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:41841:59"/>Proteſtants citing their words, and defalking Circumſtances, which continually alter the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>Queſtion;</hi> No <hi>Penances,</hi> or
<hi>Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to appeaſe Gods wrath for their ſins, thoſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> being ſufficient; and ſo, no need of <hi>Indulgences;</hi> No <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of the
<hi>Altar:</hi> No <hi>Corporal preſence</hi> of our <hi>Lords Body</hi> there; and ſo no ſolemn Ceremonies attending it; No <hi>Adoration</hi> there, and ſo no queſtioning of them for <hi>Idolatry:</hi> No <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Penance</hi> for deliverance from
<hi>Mortal</hi> ſin, and ſo no <hi>Grace</hi> expected from the <hi>Opus operatum</hi> of it; When people are ſick, no care of <hi>confeſſing</hi> them; or of not letting them depart hence without their <hi>Viaticum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.15.</note> and without
<hi>Extreme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction in the name of the Lord.</hi> No recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending themſelves to the
<hi>Prayers</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> to help them with their <hi>Interceſſions</hi> to God: No
<hi>Purgatory</hi> or preſent Middle State of any faithful Souls, however departed hence with imperfect reformation of life; but all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſent immediatly to <hi>Hell,</hi> that do not go im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly to <hi>Heaven,</hi> and to the <hi>Beatifical Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> and ſo no <hi>Prayers,</hi> no <hi>Oblations,</hi> no <hi>All-Souls-days,</hi> no Anniverſaries, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefiting of ſuch <hi>Souls,</hi> No <hi>ſaving ſo as by fire;</hi> No ſufferings to be endured hereafter, if the <hi>moſt extreme</hi> be once eſcaped; and what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſoul departing hence is not worthy of the <hi>loweſt</hi> Miſery,<note place="margin">1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>inſtantly</hi> aſcends into the <hi>higheſt</hi> Bliſs: And there too, no <hi>Degrees</hi> of <hi>Glory;</hi> but in <hi>Chriſt</hi> all equal. But then if it be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, how few of thoſe, who ſeem to dye pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, are well prepared (by reaſon of their
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:41841:60"/>repentance and imperfect reformation of manners) to enter <hi>immediatly</hi> to the fruition of <hi>Gods preſence,</hi> and poſſeſſion of <hi>eternal joyes,</hi> and how much many Proteſtants diſparage a death-bed Repentance, whilſt thus they ſend no Souls to <hi>Purgatory,</hi> they ſend the more to <hi>Hell:</hi> In extremes they are the one way, or the other; whilſt the Church, guided by Scripture, expounded by Tradition, goes in a middle way, rather inclined to <hi>mercy,</hi> than <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour.</hi> Again, No <hi>Vowes;</hi> no
<hi>macerations</hi> of the Body; no <hi>Vigils;</hi> no Obſerving <hi>Faſts;</hi> hardly any
<hi>Feſtivals,</hi> much leſs their <hi>Octaves.</hi> But every one left to pray, to repent, after his own way; faſt, when he pleaſeth; do good works out of <hi>gratitude</hi> to him, who hath <hi>done</hi> and <hi>ſuffered</hi> for him all that God requires; to believe firmly and without wavering the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of all his ſins, how hainous ſoever, and ſo to magnifie the more Gods Mercy, and Chriſts Merits, to read the Scriptures without asking the Eunuck's Queſtion <hi>Quomodo poſſum intelligere, niſi quis oſtenderit mihi,</hi> &amp;c. and not to doubt but that God will illuminate him in the underſtanding of them as much as is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, when as he ſtops his ears to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of thoſe Miſſioners ſent by our Lord to teach him in them; No ſuch <hi>numerous</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of the <hi>Articles</hi> of their Faith, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations of former obliging Councils, nor yoke of Aſſent or Belief impoſed; but boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their indulging to all men liberty of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinon in thoſe things, where the former Church they ſay hath uſed Tyranny. No ſure <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:41841:60"/>ſave only that of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> (for this alone ſerves their turn); no <hi>Church-Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity;</hi> and I had almoſt ſaid, no Church-Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. A fine contrived way of Religion for invading others, and no need of defending it ſelf: For on
<hi>Affirmes</hi> lies the <hi>Proofe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe <hi>Church-Practices</hi> before Luthers appearance, are thrown off by many, (for I cannot ſay it of all; Thoſe among them, I hope will conſider, whom theſe things concern;) Nor have they any reverence to their gray hairs, or their great antiquity: But, for their defence againſt this (not to be denied), they bring in <hi>Antichriſt</hi> to farther them; bring him not into the <hi>world</hi> only, in ſuch early days, but into the <hi>Church;</hi> and in the Church, place him alſo in the chiefeſt <hi>Chair</hi> therof, in the latter end of the
<hi>Fourth</hi> Age, or beginning of the <hi>Fifth:</hi> (for many of theſe Cuſtoms, rejected by them, are then found in the Church); and there he hath ſate ever ſince, and given laws to Chriſtianity (if we will believe them) for a <hi>thouſand</hi> years, till the
<hi>Reformation</hi> appeared, notwithſtanding our Lords Promiſe to the Church of <hi>Portae inferi non pravalebunt.</hi> And, ſince this his coming, all theſe things are found
<hi>Superſtition, Wil-worſhip, Mandata Hominum,</hi> with theſe Reformers: and, upon the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, many other Sects, Sub-reformers of the Reformed, are hard at work to pull down the remainder of Church-<hi>Government, Ceremonies, Diſcipline,</hi> which theſe firſt Demoliſhers have yet left ſtanding. And having thus diſmiſſed and rid their hands of all theſe former Church-Cuſtoms
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:41841:61"/>they have now the leiſure to make ſport with them too, and call them to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. And for fitting the Churches Tenants and Practices the better for their drollery, they miſ-relate, and miſ-repreſent them ſo far, as that they can manifeſt them unreaſonable and ridiculous; and the extravagancy of any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſt or Schoolman is applyed, and imputed, to the Church; whilſt the Proteſtant Reader, though otherwiſe never ſo prudent and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet unſtudied and unexperienced in theſe things, believes their relation as a truth; and the Learned, amongſt Catholicks, are aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſee the Churches Doctrine ſo diſguiſed and falſified. <hi>Tuautem exaltare, Domine, in virtute tuâ;</hi> and, as there want not many to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade thy Truth, ſo raiſe up alwaies thoſe that may defend it with the ſtrength, not which they have of themſelves (that is none), but which they receive from Thee; who uſeſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the <hi>Wiſe</hi> of this world with things <hi>weak,</hi> and deſpiſed, <hi>that no fleſh may glory in thy ſight.</hi> And, as for the Enemies of thy Church and Truth, whoever they be, <hi>Imple facies eorum ignominiâ Domine, ut quaerant nomen tuum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41841:61"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
